{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-13T18:36:29Z","author":["Hoekzema, Kendra","Sidlauskas, Brian L."],"title":"Data from: Molecular phylogenetics and microsatellite analysis reveals cryptic species of speckled dace (Cyprinidae: Rhinichthys osculus) in Oregon’s Great Basin","host":"Hoekzema K, Sidlauskas BL (2014) Molecular phylogenetics and microsatellite analysis reveals cryptic species of speckled dace (Cyprinidae: Rhinichthys osculus) in Oregon’s Great Basin. Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution 77: 238-250.","keywords":["S7","ND2","sequence alignment"],"description":"Speckled dace (Rhinichthys osculus) is a small cyprinid that occurs throughout western North America and is the most commonly occurring fish in Oregon. Because of the high genetic and morphological variation in this species across its range, it has been referred to as a species complex; however, no revision to its taxonomy has occurred since 1984. Here, the phylogenetics and population genetics of speckled dace are examined throughout Oregon’s Great Basin to describe genetic variation and infer the geographic boundaries between distinct taxonomic entities and populations. We tested the validity of a putative subspecies, Foskett Spring speckled dace, that occurs in a single spring within Warner Valley in Southeast Oregon and is listed Federally as threatened. Dace were collected from Foskett Spring and all surrounding basins containing speckled dace (Warner, Goose Lake, Lake Abert, Silver Lake, and Malheur), as well as Stinking Lake Spring (located within Malheur), created phylogenetic trees from mitochondrial ND2 and nuclear S7 sequence data, and genotyped eight microsatellite loci for population-level analyses. Three highly divergent clades warrant species-level status: Malheur stream dace, Stinking Lake Spring dace, and dace from the other four basins combined. Although Foskett Spring dace were not monophyletic, substantial population structure occurs at the basin-level and separates Foskett Spring dace from other dace in the surrounding Warner Valley. Thus, we recommend ESU status for the isolated population of speckled dace in Foskett Spring. The high, previously unrecognized, taxonomic diversity within this region indicates a need for a range-wide phylogeographic study of speckled dace and an investigation of the morphological distinctiveness of the putative new species.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.v64q8/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.v64q8/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61520","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61520","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24795214","doi:10.1016/j.ympev.2014.04.027"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v64q8"}}