{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-15T15:54:41Z","author":["van den Heuvel, Eleanor","Benedetti, Andrea","Thomas, Doneal","Tannenbaum, Cara","Agnew, Rona"],"title":"Data from: Effectiveness of continence promotion for older women via community organisations: a cluster randomised trial","host":"Tannenbaum C, Agnew R, Benedetti A, Thomas D, van den Heuvel E (2013) Effectiveness of continence promotion for older women via community organisations: a cluster randomised trial. \nBMJ Open 3: e004135.","keywords":["Geriatric medicine","Urinary incontinences","Public health"],"description":"Objectives: The primary objective of this cluster randomised controlled trial was to compare the effectiveness of the three experimental continence promotion interventions against a control intervention on urinary symptom improvement in older women with untreated incontinence recruited from community organisations. Setting: 71 community organisations across the United Kingdom Participants: 259 women aged 60 years and older with untreated incontinence entered the trial; 88% completed the 3-month follow-up. Interventions: The three active interventions consisted of a single 60-minute group workshop on 1) continence education (20 clusters, 64 women); 2) evidence-based self-management (17 clusters, 70 women); or 3) combined education and self-management (17 clusters, 61 women). The control intervention was a single 60-minute educational group workshop on memory loss, polypharmacy and osteoporosis (17 clusters, 64 women). Primary and secondary outcome measures: The primary outcome was self-reported improvement in incontinence 3 months post-intervention at the level of the individual. The secondary outcome was change in the International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire (ICIQ). Changes in incontinence-related knowledge and behaviours were also assessed. Results: The highest rate of urinary symptom improvement occurred in the combined intervention group (66% vs 11% of the control group, prevalence difference 55%, 95% CI 43%-67%, intracluster correlation 0). Thirty percent versus 6% of participants reported significant improvement respectively (prevalence difference 23%, 95% CI 10%-36%, intracluster correlation 0). The number-needed-to-treat was 2 to achieve any improvement in incontinence symptoms, and 5 to attain significant improvement. Compared to controls, the combined group reported an adjusted mean 2.05 point (95% CI 0.87-3.24) greater improvement on the ICIQ. Changes in knowledge and self-reported risk-reduction behaviours paralleled rates of improvement in all intervention arms. Conclusion: Continence education combined with evidence-based self-management improves symptoms of incontinence among untreated older women. Community organisations represent an untapped vector for delivering effective continence promotion interventions.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8tg11/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.57220","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.57220","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24334159","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004135"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8tg11"}}