{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"87;;2013","keywords":["crinoid","Lake Valley Formation","camerate"],"host":"Rhenberg EC, Kammer TW (2013) Camerate crinoids from the Nunn Member (Osagean) of the Lower Mississippian Lake Valley Formation, New Mexico. Journal of Paleontology 87(2): 312-340.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.f13r3/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.f13r3/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.f13r3/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.f13r3/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44404","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2013-03-28T18:11:28Z","author":["Rhenberg, Elizabeth C.","Kammer, Thomas W."],"title":"Data from: Camerate crinoids from the Nunn Member (Osagean) of the Lower Mississippian Lake Valley Formation, New Mexico","description":"The Nunn Member (Early Osagean) of the Lake Valley Formation of New Mexico is known for its abundance and diversity of crinoids. Although crinoids were first reported in the late 1800's, there has not been a comprehensive study of the crinoids, and a complete list of the crinoid taxa does not exist. All subclasses of crinoids occur in the Lake Valley, but the camerates are by far the dominant group. Study of the Macurda collection from the University of Michigan, the Laudon collection from the University of New Mexico, and new collections provided more than 7000 specimens, 4,500 of which were identifiable camerates. Sixty-one species of camerates are recognized in the Nunn Member, including five new species: Blairocrinus macurdai, Iotacrinus novamexicanus, Agaricocrinus alamogordoensis, Uperocrinus kuesi, and Collicrinus laudoni. This camerate fauna is very similar to that of the lower Burlington Limestone of the Mississippi Valley. An update of the crinoid taxa in the Lake Valley Formation allows for a better understanding of the temporal and geographic relationships of crinoid faunas across North American during the Early Mississippian when camerates were at their global diversity maximum. The majority of the camerates come from the western New Mexico outcrops where the Nunn is thicker and the marine shelf was shallower, but several also occur in association with the deep-water Waulsortian mounds.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44404","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1666/12-033R.1","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f13r3"}}