{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-03-04T15:31:52Z","author":["Matocq, Marjorie D.","Murphy, Peter J.","Shurtliff, Quinn Rodney"],"title":"Data from: Ecological segregation in a small mammal hybrid zone: habitat-specific mating opportunities and selection against hybrids restrict gene flow on a fine spatial scale","host":"Shurtliff QR, Murphy PJ, Matocq MD (2013) Ecological segregation in a small mammal hybrid zone: habitat-specific mating opportunities and selection against hybrids restrict gene flow on a fine spatial scale. Evolution 68(3): 729–742.","keywords":["Gene Flow","Hybridization"],"description":"The degree to which closely related species interbreed is determined by a complex interaction of ecological, behavioral, and genetic factors. We examine the degree of interbreeding between two woodrat species, Neotoma bryanti and N. lepida, at a sharp ecological transition. We identify the ecological association of each genotypic class, assess the opportunity for mating between these groups, and test whether they have similar patterns of year-to-year persistence on our study site. We find that 13% of individuals have a hybrid signature but that the two parental populations and backcrosses are highly segregated by habitat type and use. Also, we find that adult hybrids are comparable to parental types in terms of year-to-year persistence on our site but that, among juveniles, significantly fewer hybrids reach adulthood on site compared to their purebred counterparts. Our analyses show that this hybrid zone is maintained by occasional nonassortative mating coupled with hybrid fertility, but that these factors are balanced by lower apparent survival of juvenile hybrids and habitat-based preference or selection that limits heterospecific mating while promoting backcrossing to habitat-specific genotypes. This system presents a novel example of the role that sharp resource gradients play in reproductive isolation and the potential for genetic introgression.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.648k2/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55366","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55366","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12299","PMID:24152220"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.648k2"}}