{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-24T14:15:24Z","author":["Gavin-Smyth, Jackie","Matute, Daniel R."],"title":"Data from: Fine mapping of dominant X-linked incompatibility alleles in Drosophila hybrids","host":"Matute DR, Gavin-Smyth J (2014) Fine mapping of dominant X-linked incompatibility alleles in Drosophila hybrids. PLoS Genetics 10(4): e1004270.","keywords":["hybrid incompatibilities","hybridization","epistasis"],"description":"Sex chromosomes have a large effect on reproductive isolation and play an important role in hybrid inviability. In Drosophila hybrids, X-linked genes have pronounced deleterious effects on fitness in male hybrids, which have only one X chromosome. Several studies have succeeded at locating and identifying recessive X-linked alleles involved in hybrid inviability. Nonetheless, the density of dominant X-linked alleles involved in interspecific hybrid viability remains largely unknown. In this report, we study the effects of a panel of small fragments of the D. melanogaster X-chromosome carried on the D. melanogaster Y-chromosome in three kinds of hybrid males: D. melanogaster/D. santomea, D. melanogaster/D. simulans and D. melanogaster/D. mauritiana. D. santomea and D. melanogaster diverged over 10 million years ago, while D. simulans (and D. mauritiana) diverged from D. melanogaster over 3 million years ago. We find that the X-chromosome from D. melanogaster carries dominant alleles that are lethal in mel/san, mel/sim, and mel/mau hybrids, and more of these alleles are revealed in the most divergent cross. We then compare these effects on hybrid viability with two D. melanogaster intraspecific crosses. Unlike the interspecific crosses, we found no X-linked alleles that cause lethality in intraspecific crosses. Our results reveal the existence of dominant alleles on the X-chromosome of D. melanogaster which cause lethality in three different interspecific hybrids. These alleles only cause inviability in hybrid males, yet have little effect in hybrid females. This suggests that X-linked elements that cause hybrid inviability in males might not do so in hybrid females due to differing sex chromosome interactions.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ft6r5/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.59989","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.59989","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24743238","doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1004270"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ft6r5"}}