{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-29T16:18:39Z","author":["Dai, Minhan","Zhao, Zihao","Herndl, Gerhard J.","Jiao, Nianzhi","Zhang, Yao"],"title":"Data from: Drivers shaping the diversity and biogeography of total and active bacterial communities in the South China Sea","host":"Zhang Y, Zhao Z, Dai M, Jiao N, Herndl GJ (2014) Drivers shaping the diversity and biogeography of total and active bacterial communities in the South China Sea. Molecular Ecology 23(9): 2260–2274.","keywords":["Active versus total bacterial communities","Network interaction","Biogeography","Geographic distance","Diversity","Environmental selection"],"description":"To test the hypothesis that different drivers shape the diversity and biogeography of the total and active bacterial community, we examined the bacterial community composition along two transects, one from the inner Pearl River estuary to the open waters of the South China Sea (SCS) and the other from the Luzon Strait to the SCS basin, using 454 pyrosequencing of the 16S rRNA and 16S rRNA gene (V1-3 regions) and thereby, characterizing the active and total bacterial community, respectively. The diversity and biogeographic patterns differed substantially between the active and total bacterial communities. Although the composition of both, the total and active bacterial community was strongly correlated with environmental factors and weakly correlated with geographic distance, the active bacterial community displayed higher environmental sensitivity than the total community and particularly, a greater distance effect largely caused by the active assemblage from deep waters. The 16S rRNA versus rDNA relationships indicated that the active bacteria were low in relative abundance in the SCS. This might be due to a high competition between active bacterial taxa as indicated by our community network models. Based on these analyses, we speculate that high competition could cause some dispersal limitation of the active bacterial community resulting in a distinct distance-decay relationship. Altogether, our results indicated that the biogeographic distribution of bacteria in the SCS is the result of both environmental control and distance-decay.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61382","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61382","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12739","PMID:24684298"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s8c2c"}}