{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-03-04T15:38:20Z","author":["Lee, Ming-Chun","Marx, Christopher James","Carroll, Sean Michael"],"title":"Data from: Sign epistasis limits evolutionary trade-offs at the confluence of single- and multi-carbon metabolism in Methylobacterium extorquens AM1","host":"Carroll SM, Lee M, Marx CJ (2013) Sign epistasis limits evolutionary trade-offs at the confluence of single- and multi-carbon metabolism in Methylobacterium extorquens AM1. Evolution 68(3): 760–771.","keywords":["Trade-Offs","Selection - Experimental","Pleiotropy","Epistasis","Physiology","Adaptation"],"description":"Adaptation of one set of traits is often accompanied by attenuation of traits important in other selective environments, leading to fitness trade-offs. The mechanisms that either promote or prevent the emergence of trade-offs remain largely unknown, and are difficult to discern in most systems. Here, we investigate the basis of trade-offs that emerged during experimental evolution of Methylobacterium extorquens AM1 to distinct growth substrates. After 1500 generations of adaptation to a multi-carbon substrate, succinate (S), many lineages had lost the ability to use one-carbon compounds such as methanol (M), generating a mixture of M+ and M− evolved phenotypes. We show that trade-offs in M− strains consistently arise via antagonistic pleiotropy through recurrent selection for loss-of-function mutations to ftfL (formate-tetrahydrofolate ligase), which improved growth on S while simultaneously eliminating growth on M. But if loss of FtfL was beneficial, why were M trade-offs not found in all populations? We discovered that eliminating FtfL was not universally beneficial on S, as it was neutral or even deleterious in certain evolved lineages that remained M+. This suggests that sign epistasis with earlier arising mutations prevented the emergence of mutations that drove trade-offs through antagonistic pleiotropy, limiting the evolution of metabolic specialists in some populations.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n2645/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55166","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55166","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24164359","doi:10.1111/evo.12301"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n2645"}}