{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-17T18:12:57Z","author":["Liu, Gang","Shafer, Aaron B. A.","Hu, Defu"],"title":"Data from: Evaluating the reintroduction project of Przewalski’s horse in China using genetic and pedigree data","host":"Liu G, Shafer ABA, Zimmermann W, Hu D, Wang W, Chu H, Cao J, Zhao C (2014) Evaluating the reintroduction project of Przewalski’s horse in China using genetic and pedigree data. Biological Conservation 171(2014): 288-298.","keywords":["population structure","microsatellite","pedigree","Przewalski’s horse","genetic diversity","reintroduction"],"description":"Przewalski's horse went extinct in the wild in the mid 1960’s. Starting in 1985, individuals were brought from western zoos to two centers in China and breeding programs were initiated. With the increasing size of captive populations, two reintroduction projects were launched in the northwestern China in 2001 and 2010. Knowledge on genetic diversity in China’s horse populations is limited, but would help improve the genetic management and assess the success of the reintroduction. Accordingly, one reintroduced and two captive populations were examined with 10 microsatellite loci together with pedigree data. The results showed higher level of diversity within the captive populations than the reintroduced population, indicating some alleles may have been lost during reintroduction. Genetic differentiation was detected among populations (FST=0.09±0.05, RhoST=0.05±0.02) and Bayesian clustering supported the presence of three subpopulations. The highest genetic differentiation was observed between the captive and reintroduced populations, and inbreeding coefficients were generally higher in the reintroduced population. Temporal estimates of both pedigree and microsatellite data showed a high, but decreasing level inbreeding. Through simulations, we estimated that the reintroduced population needs more than 100 individuals to retain approximately 90% of its current, already depauperate, genetic diversity. We have provided recommendations for the management program concerning introgressed genes from domestic horse and the number and origin of individuals for future reintroductions.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.s4933/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.s4933/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.s4933/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.s4933/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.s4933/5"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56327","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56327","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1016/j.biocon.2013.11.022","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s4933"}}