{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-11T15:08:14Z","author":["Robert, Alexandre","Bolton, Mark","Paiva, Vítor H.","Bried, Joël","Jiguet, Frédéric"],"title":"Data from: Nest fidelity is driven by multi-scale information in a long-lived seabird","host":"Robert A, Paiva VH, Bolton M, Jiguet F, Bried J (2014) Nest fidelity is driven by multi-scale information in a long-lived seabird. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1793): 20141692.","keywords":["Breeding habitat selection","site fidelity","predictability","environmental stochasticity"],"description":"Although the reproductive success of most organisms depends on factors acting at several spatial scales, little is known about how organisms are able to synthesize multi-scale information to optimize reproduction. Using longitudinal data from a long-lived seabird, Monteiro's storm-petrel, we show that average breeding success is strongly related to oceanic conditions at the population level, and we postulate that (i) individuals use proximal information (their own reproduction outcome in year t) to assess the qualities of their mate and nest and to decide to retain them or not in year t + 1; (ii) the intensity of these responses depends on the quality of the oceanic environment in year t, which affects the predictability of reproduction outcome in year t + 1. Our results confirm that mate and nest fidelities are higher following successful reproduction and that the relationship between the success of a given pair and subsequent nest fidelity is stronger in years with unfavourable oceanic conditions, suggesting that individuals rely on distant information to modulate their use of proximal information and adjust their breeding strategy.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.kp497/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67654","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67654","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.1692","PMID:25209940"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.kp497"}}