{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-04-26T18:44:02Z","author":["Neiman, Maurine","Krist, Amy C.","Kay, Adam D."],"title":"Data from: Sensitivity to phosphorus limitation increases with ploidy level in a New Zealand snail","host":"Neiman M, Kay AD, Krist AC (2012) Data from: Sensitivity to phosphorus limitation increases with ploidy level in a New Zealand snail. Evolution 67(5): 1511-1517.","keywords":["polyploidy","ecological stoichiometry","phosphorus","growth rate","Sex"],"description":"Evolutionary and ecological factors that explain natural variation in ploidy level remain poorly understood. One intriguing possibility is that nutrient costs associated with higher per-cell nucleic acid content could differentially influence the fitness of different ploidy levels. Here, we test this hypothesis by determining whether access to phosphorus (P), a main component of nucleic acids, differentially affects growth rate in asexual freshwater snails (Potamopyrgus antipodarum) that differ in ploidy. As expected if larger genomes generate higher dietary P requirements, tetraploid P. antipodarum experienced a more than two-fold greater reduction in growth rate in low- vs. high-P conditions relative to triploids. Mirroring these results, tetraploid P. antipodarum also had a significant reduction in body P content under low P relative to high P, while triploid body P content was unaffected. Taken together, these results set the stage for the possibility that P availability could influence the distribution and relative frequency of P. antipodarum of different ploidy levels. These findings could be applicable to many other animal taxa featuring ploidy-level variation, which includes most mixed sexual/asexual taxa.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.ct601/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.ct601/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44635","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44635","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12026","PMID:23617926"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ct601"}}