{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-17T17:19:12Z","author":["Bolliger, Janine","Holderegger, Rolf","Aavik, Tsipe"],"title":"Data from: The structural and functional connectivity of the grassland plant Lychnis flos-cuculi","host":"Aavik T, Holderegger R, Bolliger J (2013) The structural and functional connectivity of the grassland plant Lychnis flos-cuculi. Heredity 112: 471–478.","keywords":["inbreeding","gene flow","landscape genetics","graph theory","genetic diversity"],"description":"Understanding the relationship between structural and functional connectivity is essential for successful restoration and conservation management, particularly in intensely managed agricultural landscapes. We evaluated the relationship between structural and functional connectivity of the wetland plant Lychnis flos-cuculi in a fragmented agricultural landscape using landscape genetic and network approaches. First, we studied the effect of structural connectivity, such as geographic distance and various landscape elements (forest, agricultural land, settlements and ditch verges), on gene flow among populations as a measurement of functional connectivity. Second, we examined the effect of structural graph-theoretic connectivity measures on gene flow among populations and on genetic diversity within populations of L. flos-cuculi. Among landscape elements, forests hindered gene flow in L. flos-cuculi, whereas gene flow was independent of geographic distance. Among the structural graph-theoretic connectivity variables, only intrapopulation connectivity, which was based on population size, had a significant positive effect on gene flow, that is, more gene flow took place among larger populations. Unexpectedly, interpopulation connectivity of populations, which takes into account the spatial location and distance among populations, did not influence gene flow in L. flos-cuculi. However, higher observed heterozygosity and lower inbreeding was observed in populations characterised by higher structural interpopulation connectivity. This finding shows that a spatially coherent network of populations is significant for maintaining the genetic diversity of populations. Nevertheless, lack of significant relationships between gene flow and most of the structural connectivity measures suggests that structural connectivity does not necessarily correspond to functional connectivity.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.147r0/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.147r0/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55558","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55558","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.120","PMID:24253937"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.147r0"}}