{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-16T14:58:13Z","author":["Mescher, Mark C.","Salvaudon, Lucie","De Moraes, Consuelo M."],"title":"Data from: Outcomes of co-infection by two potyviruses: implications for the evolution of manipulative strategies","host":"Salvaudon L, De Moraes CM, Mescher MC (2013) Outcomes of co-infection by two potyviruses: implications for the evolution of manipulative strategies. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 280(1756): 20122959.","keywords":["plant volatiles","vector transmission","Plant viruses","chemical ecologyhost manipulation"],"description":"Recent studies have documented effects of plant-viruses on host plants that appear to enhance transmission by insect vectors.  But, almost no empirical work has explored the implications of such apparent manipulation for interactions among co-infecting pathogens. We examined single and mixed infections of two potyviruses, Watermelon mosaic virus (WMV) and Zucchini yellow mosaic virus (ZYMV), that frequently co-occur in cucurbitaceae populations and share the same aphid vectors. We found that ZYMV isolates replicated at similar rates in single and mixed infections, while WMV strains accumulated to signficantly lower levels in the presence of ZYMV. Furthermore, ZYMV induced changes in leaf colour and volatile emissions that enhanced aphid (Aphis gossypii) recruitment to infected plants. In contrast, WMV did not elicit strong effects on plant-aphid interactions. Nevertheless, WMV was still readily transmitted from mixed infections, despite fairing poorly in in-plant competition. These findings suggest that pathogen effects on host-vector interactions may well influence competition among co-infecting pathogens. For example, if non-manipulative pathogens benefit from the increased vector traffic elicited by manipulative competitors, their costs of competition may be mitigated to some extent. Conversely, the benefits of manipulation may be limited by free-rider effects in systems where there is strong competition among pathogens for host resources and/or access to vectors.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7db1n/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.45691","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.45691","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23407835","doi:10.1098/rspb.2012.2959"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7db1n"}}