{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-11T16:32:47Z","author":["Furness, Andrew Ian","Reznick, David N.","Walsh, Matthew R."],"title":"Data from: Convergence of life history phenotypes in a Trinidadian killifish (Rivulus hartii)","host":"Furness AI, Walsh MR, Reznick DN (2011) Convergence of life history phenotypes in a Trinidadian killifish (Rivulus hartii). Evolution 66(4): 1240-1254.","keywords":["Adaptation","Life-History Evolution","Convergent Evolution"],"description":"Convergent evolution is characterized by the independent evolution of similar phenotypes within similar selective environments. Previous work on Trinidadian killifish, Rivulus hartii, demonstrated repeatable life history differences across communities that differ in predation intensity. These studies were performed in rivers located on the south slope of Trinidad’s Northern Range Mountains. There exists a parallel series of rivers on the north slope of these mountains. As on the south slope, Rivulus is found across a gradient of fish predation. However, the predatory fish species in north-slope rivers are derived from marine families, whereas south-slope rivers contain a predatory fish fauna characteristic of the South American mainland. If predator-induced mortality and the associated indirect effects are the causal factors selecting for life history patterns in Rivulus, and these are similar in north and south-slope rivers, then the specific predatory species should be interchangeable and we would expect convergence of life history phenotypes across slopes. Here, we characterize the life history phenotypes of Rivulus from north-slope communities. We find similar patterns of life history divergence across analogous predator communities. Between slopes, minor differences in Rivulus life history traits exist and one potential cause of these differences is the abundance of Macrobrachium prawns in north-slope rivers.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2jt025jk/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35900","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35900","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22486701","doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2011.01520.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2jt025jk"}}