{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-15T18:53:43Z","author":["Lewis, Zenobia","Heys, Chloe","Price, Thomas A. R.","Hurst, Gregory D. D.","Lizé, Anne"],"title":"Data from: Extreme cost of rivalry in a monandrous species: male–male interactions result in failure to acquire mates and reduced longevity","host":"Lizé A, Price TAR, Heys C, Lewis Z, Hurst GDD (2014) Extreme cost of rivalry in a monandrous species: male–male interactions result in failure to acquire mates and reduced longevity. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1786): 20140631.","keywords":["copulation","rival exposure","copulation duration","longevity","male-male competition","copulation latency"],"description":"Mating system variation is profound in animals. In insects, female willingness to remate varies from mating with hundreds of males (extreme polyandry) to never remating (monandry). This variation in female behaviour is predicted to affect the pattern of selection on males, with intense pre-copulatory sexual selection under monandry compared to a mix of pre- and post-copulatory forces affecting fitness under polyandry. We tested the hypothesis that differences in female mating biology would be reflected in different costs of pre-copulatory competition between males. We observed that exposure to rival males early in life was highly costly for males of a monandrous species, but had lower costs in the polyandrous species. Males from the monandrous species housed with competitors showed reduced ability to obtain a mate and decreased longevity. These effects were specific to exposure to rivals compared with other types of social interactions (heterospecific male and mated female) and were either absent or weaker in males of the polyandrous species. We conclude that males in monandrous species suffer severe physiological costs from interactions with rivals and note the significance of male–male interactions as a source of stress in laboratory culture.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3nv8n/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.63481","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.63481","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24827446","doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.0631"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3nv8n"}}