{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-04T17:29:13Z","author":["Gao, Wu-Jun","Li, Shu-Fen","Lu, Long-Dou","Dong, Tian-Yu","Zhao, Xin-Peng","Deng, Chuan-Liang"],"series":"9;5;2014","title":"Data from: Analysis of transposable elements in the genome of Asparagus officinalis from high coverage sequence data","host":"Li S, Gao W, Zhao X, Dong T, Deng C, Lu L (2014) Analysis of transposable elements in the genome of Asparagus officinalis from high coverage sequence data. PLoS ONE 9(5): e97189.","description":"Asparagus officinalis is an economically and nutritionally important vegetable crop that is widely cultivated and is used as a model dioecious species to study plant sex determination and sex chromosome evolution. To improve our understanding of its genome composition, especially with respect to transposable elements (TEs), which make up the majority of the genome, we performed Illumina HiSeq2000 sequencing of both male and female asparagus genomes followed by bioinformatics analysis. We generated 17 Gb of sequence (12×coverage) and assembled them into 163,406 scaffolds with a total cumulated length of 400 Mbp, which represent about 30% of asparagus genome. Overall, TEs masked about 53% of the A. officinalis assembly. Majority of the identified TEs belonged to LTR retrotransposons, which constitute about 28% of genomic DNA, with Ty1/copia elements being more diverse and accumulated to higher copy numbers than Ty3/gypsy. Compared with LTR retrotransposons, non-LTR retrotransposons and DNA transposons were relatively rare. In addition, comparison of the abundance of the TE groups between male and female genomes showed that the overall TE composition was highly similar, with only slight differences in the abundance of several TE groups, which is consistent with the relatively recent origin of asparagus sex chromosomes. This study greatly improves our knowledge of the repetitive sequence construction of asparagus, which facilitates the identification of TEs responsible for the early evolution of plant sex chromosomes and is helpful for further studies on this dioecious plant.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s71t4/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.65519","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.65519","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24810432","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0097189"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s71t4"}}