{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-02-01T15:29:37Z","author":["Sih, Andrew","Stachowicz, John J.","Pruitt, Jonathan N."],"title":"Data from: Behavioral types of predator and prey jointly determine prey survival: potential implications for the maintenance of within species behavioral variation","host":"Pruitt JN, Stachowicz JJ, Sih A (2011) Behavioral types of predator and prey jointly determine prey survival: potential implications for the maintenance of within species behavioral variation. The American Naturalist 179(2): 217-227.","keywords":["Ecology: population","Selection: natural","Ecology: behavioral","Coevolution","Behavior","Behavior: antipredator","Behavior: evolution"],"description":"Recent studies in animal behavior have emphasized the ecological importance of individual variation in behavioral types (e.g. boldness, activity). Such studies have emphasized how variation in one species affects its interaction with other species. But few (if any) studies simultaneously examine variation in multiple interacting species, despite the potential for coevolutionary responses to work to either maintain or eliminate variation in interacting populations. Here, we investigate how individual differences in behavioral types of both predators (Ochre Seastars, Pisaster ochraceus) and prey (Black Turban Snails, Chlorostoma funebralis) interact to mediate predation rates. We assessed activity-level, degree of predator avoidance behavior, and maximum shell diameter of individual C. funebralis and activity-levels of individual P. ochraceus. We then placed 46 individually-marked C. funebralis into outdoor mesocosms with a single P. ochraceus and allowed them to interact for 14 days. Overall, predator avoidance behavior and maximum shell diameter were positively associated with survival for C. funebralis, however, the effects of these traits depended on the predator's behavioral type: greater predator avoidance behavior was favored with active P. ochraceus and low predator avoidance behavior was favored with inactive P. ochraceus. We argue that, even in two-species interactions, trait variation in heterospecifics could be an important factor maintaining trait variation within populations.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.190pk253/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35318","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35318","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/663680","PMID:22218311"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.190pk253"}}