{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-01-26T17:07:13Z","author":["Linden, David","Harris, Margaret","Roberts, Anthony P.","Linden, Stefanie C.","Le Noury, Joanna","Baker, Darren","Healy, David","Whitaker, Chris"],"title":"Data from: The incidence of admissions for schizophrenia and related psychoses in two cohorts: 1875-1924 and 1994-2010","host":"Healy D, Le Noury J, Linden SC, Harris M, Whitaker C, Linden D, Baker D, Roberts AP (2012) The incidence of admissions for schizophrenia and related psychoses in two cohorts: 1875-1924 and 1994-2010. BMJ Open 2(1): e000447.","keywords":["PUBLIC HEALTH","Schizophrenia & psychotic disorders","Adult psychiatry","Medical History","TOXICOLOGY"],"description":"OBJECTIVES: To investigate changes in incidence of admissions for schizophrenia and related non-affective psychoses in North Wales. DESIGN: Data from two epidemiologically complete cohorts of patients presenting for the first time to mental health services in North Wales between 1875-1924 and 1994-2010 are used in this study to map the incidence of hospital admissions for schizophrenia and non-affective psychoses. SETTING: The North Wales Asylum Denbigh (archived patient case notes) and the North West Wales District General Hospital psychiatric unit. POPULATION: 3168 patients admitted to the North Wales Asylum Denbigh 1875-1924 and 355 patients admitted to the District General Hospital psychiatric unit 1994-2010. RESULTS: There was an increasing admission incidence for schizophrenia between 1875 and 1900, a higher admission rate in the 1990s for males, followed by a drop in rates of admission for both genders since 2006. Admission incidences switch from parity between the sexes in the historical period to a doubling of the admission rates for men compared to women in the modern period. This admission pattern differs from the admission patterns for affective psychoses or organic disorders. CONCLUSION: There have been changes in the incidence of admissions for schizophrenia in North Wales.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.ct00428d/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.ct00428d/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36825","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36825","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2011-000447","PMID:22267688"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ct00428d"}}