{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-17T17:21:14Z","author":["Huang, Lei","Wang, Cai-Hong","Zheng, Xiao-Ming","Yuan, Xiao-Ping","Zhou, Hai-Feng","Wei, Xing-Hua","Xu, Qun","Ge, Song"],"title":"Data from: Genetic diversity and classification of Oryza sativa with emphasis on Chinese rice germplasm","host":"Wang C, Zheng X, Xu Q, Yuan X, Huang L, Zhou H, Wei X, Ge S (2014) Genetic diversity and classification of Oryza sativa with emphasis on Chinese rice germplasm. Heredity 112: 489–496.","description":"Despite extensive studies on cultivated rice, the genetic structure and subdivision of this crop remain unclear at both global and local scales. Using 84 nuclear simple sequence repeat markers, we genotyped a panel of 153 global rice cultivars covering all previously recognized groups and 826 cultivars representing the diversity of Chinese rice germplasm. On the basis of model-based grouping, neighbour-joining tree and principal coordinate analysis, we confirmed the widely accepted five major groups of rice cultivars (indica, aus, aromatic, temperate japonica and tropical japonica), and demonstrated that rayada rice was unique in genealogy and should be treated as a new (the sixth) major group of rice germplasm. With reference to the global classification of rice cultivars, we identified three major groups (indica, temperate japonica and tropical japonica) in Chinese rice germplasm and showed that Chinese temperate japonica contained higher diversity than that of global samples, whereas Chinese indica and tropical japonica maintained slightly lower diversity than that present in the global samples. Particularly, we observed that all seasonal, drought-tolerant and endosperm types occurred within each of three major groups of Chinese cultivars, which does not support previous claims that seasonal differentiation exists in Indica and drought-tolerant differentiation is present in Japonica. It is most likely that differentiation of cultivar types arose multiple times stemming from artificial selection for adaptation to local environments.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.m8jj7/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55465","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55465","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24326293","doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.130"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.m8jj7"}}