{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["48:1, 54-64","Systematic Biology"],"keywords":["morphology","congruence","gene sequences","phylogeny","eutherian mammals"],"host":"Liu F-GR, Miyamoto MM(1999) Phylogenetic assessment of molecular and morphological data for eutherian mammals. Systematic Biology 48(1): 54-64","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.523/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.523","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T17:47:13Z","author":["Liu, Fu-Guo R.","Miyamoto, Michael M."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenetic assessment of molecular and morphological data for eutherian mammals","description":"The interordinal relationships of eutherian (placental) mammals were evaluated by a phylogenetic analysis of four published data sets (three sequence and one morphological). The nature and degree of support and conflict for particular groups were assessed by separate bootstrap and homogeneity tests that were followed by combined analyses of the sequence and morphological data. Between orders, strong support (i.e., >95% bootstrap scores) was found for a paraphyletic Artiodactyla (relative to Cetacea) and a monophyletic Cetartiodactyla (Artiodactyla and Cetacea) and Paenungulata (Hyracoidea, Proboscidea, and Sirenia). In turn, some reasonable to strong evidence (>85%) was obtained for Hyracoidea with Sirenia, Dermoptera with Scandentia, Glires (Lagomorpha with Rodentia), and Afrotheria (Amblysomus, Macroscelidea, Paenungulata, and Tubulidentata). Otherwise, no other interordinal clades were supported at these reasonable to strong levels. This overall lack of resolution for eutherian interordinal clusters agrees with other studies that further progress will continue to be slow and difficult. Further resolution will require the integration of more recently published data, the continued sampling of taxa and characters, and the use of more powerful methods of data analysis.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.523","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1080/106351599260436","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.523"}}