{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-14T14:42:06Z","author":["Kai, Yoshiaki","Ingram, Travis"],"title":"Data from: The geography of morphological convergence in the radiations of Pacific Sebastes rockfishes","keywords":["Phylogenetics: comparative","Ocean","Biogeography","Speciation: ecological","Morphology","Macroevolution","Fish","Adaptive radiation"],"description":"The evolution of convergent phenotypes in lineages subject to similar selective pressures is a common feature of adaptive radiation. In geographically replicated radiations, repeated convergence occurs between clades occupying distinct regions or islands. Alternatively, a clade may repeatedly reach the same adaptive peaks in broad-scale sympatry, resulting in extensive convergence within a region. Rockfish (Sebastes sp.) have radiated in both the northeast and northwest Pacific, allowing tests of the extent and geographic pattern of convergence in a marine environment. We use a suite of phylogenetically-informed methods to test for morphological convergence in rockfish. We examined patterns of faunal similarity using nearest neighbor distances in morphospace and the frequency of morphologically similar yet distantly related species pairs. The extent of convergence both between regions and within the northeast Pacific exceeds the expectation under a Brownian motion null model, although constraints on trait space could account for the similarity. We then use a recently developed method (SURFACE) to identify adaptive peak shifts in Sebastes' evolutionary history. We found that the majority of convergent peak shifts occur within the northeast Pacific rather than between regions, and that the signal of peak shifts is strongest for traits related to trophic morphology. Pacific rockfish thus demonstrate a tendency toward morphological convergence within one of the two broad geographic regions in which they have diversified.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s5s3s/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64178","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64178","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s5s3s"}}