{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-24T15:30:47Z","author":["Vaughan, Ian P.","Jurasović, Jasna","Šerić Jelaska, Lucija","Symondson, William O. C.","Brown, David S."],"title":"Data from: Molecular field analysis of trophic relationships in soil-dwelling invertebrates to identify mercury, lead and cadmium transmission through forest ecosystems","host":"Šerić Jelaska L, Jurasović J, Brown DS, Vaughan IP, Symondson WOC (2014) Molecular field analysis of trophic relationships in soil-dwelling invertebrates to identify mercury, lead and cadmium transmission through forest ecosystems. Molecular Ecology 23(15): 3755-3766.","keywords":["earthworms","slugs","molecular gut content analyses","carabid beetles","prey choice","metal bioaccumulation"],"description":"Contamination pathways in complex food chains in soil ecosystems can be difficult to elucidate. Molecular analysis of predator gut content can, however, rapidly reveal previously unidentified trophic interactions between invertebrates and thereby uncover pathways of pollutant spread. Here we measured concentrations of the toxic metals lead, cadmium and mercury in carabid beetle predators and their prey. Invertebrates were sampled at one control and four heavy metal polluted sites in order to reveal the impact of diet composition and seasonal variation in prey availability on metal burden in carabids and metal transfer pathways through forest ecosystems. This is the first report, to our knowledge, of carabid diet composition based on PCR analysis of gut contents at the forest community level, rather than in cultivated fields. Extensive screening using group- and species-specific primers revealed that carabids ate primarily earthworms and slugs, as well as smaller numbers of woodlice and springtails. Metal concentrations in carabids correlated with seasonal changes in diet. Mercury accumulated in beetle predators more than in their slug prey. Since earthworms, slugs and carabid beetles are the major prey of many birds and mammals, prey-predator transfer and associated toxicity are major risks at mercury-contaminated sites. Carabids may be useful bioindicators for assessing the impact of pollutants on soil ecosystems, as long as species and seasonal factors are taken into account.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.5n02f/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.5n02f/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55233","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55233","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24138157","doi:10.1111/mec.12566"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5n02f"}}