{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-20T20:18:27Z","author":["Cleris, Loredana","Carlo-Stella, Carmelo","Righi, Marco","Giacomini, Arianna"],"title":"Data from: D quantification of tumor vasculature in lymphoma xenografts in NOD/SCID mice allows to detect differences among vascular-targeted therapies","host":"Righi M, Giacomini A, Cleris L, Carlo-Stella C (2013) Data from: D quantification of tumor vasculature in lymphoma xenografts in NOD/SCID mice allows to detect differences among vascular-targeted therapies. PLoS One 8(3): e59691.","keywords":["microvessel distribution","vascular-targeted therapies","tumor angiogenesis","antivascular drugs","mathematical morphology","image analysis"],"description":"Quantitative characterization of the in vivo effects of vascular-targeted therapies on tumor vessels is hampered by the absence of useful 3D vascular network descriptors aside from microvessel density. In this study, we extended the quantification of planar vessel distribution to the analysis of vascular volumes by studying the effects of antiangiogenic (sorafenib and sunitinib) or antivascular (combretastatin A4 phosphate) treatments on the quantity and spatial distributions of thin microvessels. These observations were restricted to perinecrotic areas of treated human multiple myeloma tumors xenografted in immunodeficient mice and to microvessels with an approximate cross-sectional area lower than 75 µm2. Finally, vessel skeletonization minimized artifacts due to possible differential wall staining and allowed a comparison of the various treatment effects. Antiangiogenic drug treatment reduced the number of vessels of every caliber (at least 2-fold fewer vessels vs. controls; p<0.001, n = 8) and caused a heterogeneous distribution of the remaining vessels. In contrast, the effects of combretastatin A4 phosphate mainly appeared to be restricted to a homogeneous reduction in the number of thin microvessels (not more than 2-fold less vs. controls; p<0.001, n = 8) with marginal effects on spatial distribution. Unexpectedly, these results also highlighted a strict relationship between microvessel quantity, distribution and cross-sectional area. Treatment-specific changes in the curves describing this relationship were consistent with the effects ascribed to the different drugs. This finding suggests that our results can highlight differences among vascular-targeted therapies, providing hints on the processes underlying sample vascularization together with the detailed characterization of a pathological vascular tree.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/20","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/21","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/22","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/23","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47023","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47023","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0059691","PMID:23555747"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6c44q"}}