{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-12-11T19:38:20Z","author":["Ligon, Russell A.","McGraw, Kevin J."],"title":"Data from: Chameleons communicate with complex colour changes during contests: different body regions convey different information","host":"Ligon RA, McGraw KJ (2013) Chameleons communicate with complex colour changes during contests: different body regions convey different information. Biology Letters 9(6): 20130892.","keywords":["Agonistic signaling","Physiological colour change","Combat","Communication","Chameleons","Colour signals"],"description":"Many animals display static coloration (e.g. of feathers or fur) that can serve as a reliable sexual or social signal, but the communication function of rapidly changing colours (as in chameleons and cephalopods) is poorly understood. We used recently developed photographic and mathematical modelling tools to examine how rapid colour changes of veiled chameleons Chamaeleo calyptratus predict aggressive behaviour during male–male competitions. Males that achieved brighter stripe coloration were more likely to approach their opponent, and those that attained brighter head coloration were more likely to win fights; speed of head colour change was also an important predictor of contest outcome. This correlative study represents the first quantification of rapid colour change using organism-specific visual models and provides evidence that the rate of colour change, in addition to maximum display coloration, can be an important component of communication. Interestingly, the body and head locations of the relevant colour signals map onto the behavioural displays given during specific contest stages, with lateral displays from a distance followed by directed, head-on approaches prior to combat, suggesting that different colour change signals may evolve to communicate different information (motivation and fighting ability, respectively).","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8jp03/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56334","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56334","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24335271","doi:10.1098/rsbl.2013.0892"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8jp03"}}