{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-29T01:57:36Z","author":["Ducamp, Jean-Jacques","Boutin, Jean-Marie","Eraud, Cyril","Fox, James W.","Lormée, Hervé","Rivière, Marcel"],"title":"Data from: Migration routes and staging areas of trans-Saharan Turtle Doves appraised from light-level geolocators","host":"Eraud C, Rivière M, Lormée H, Fox JW, Ducamp J, Boutin J (2013) Migration routes and staging areas of trans-Saharan Turtle Doves appraised from light-level geolocators. PLoS ONE 8(3): e59396.","keywords":["geolocators","trans-saharan migration","birds"],"description":"The identification of migration routes, wintering grounds and stopover sites are crucial issues for the understanding of the Palearctic-African bird migration system as well as for the development of relevant conservation strategies for trans-Saharan migrants. Using miniaturized light-level geolocators we report a comprehensive and detailed year round track of a granivorous trans-Saharan migrant, the European Turtle Dove (Streptopelia turtur). From five recovered loggers, our data provide new insights on migratory journeys and winter destinations of Turtle Doves originating from a breeding population in Western France. Data confirm that Turtle Doves wintered in West Africa. The main wintering area encompassed Western Mali, the Inner Delta Niger and the Malian/Mauritanian border. Some individuals also extended their wintering ranges over North Guinea, North-West of Burkina Faso and the Ivory-Coast. Our results reveal that all individuals did not spend the winter period at a single location; some of them experienced a clear eastward shift of several hundred kilometres. We also found evidence for a loop migration pattern, with a post-breeding migration flyway lying west of the spring route. Finally, we found that on their way back to breeding grounds Turtle Doves needed to refuel after crossing the Sahara desert. Contrary to previous suggestions, our data reveal that birds used stopover sites for several weeks, presumably in Morocco and North Algeria. This later finding is a crucial issue for future conservation strategies because environmental conditions on these staging areas might play a pivotal role in population dynamics of this declining species.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.bv24t/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.bv24t/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.bv24t/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.bv24t/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47155","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47155","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0059396","PMID:23544064"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.bv24t"}}