{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-14T18:53:57Z","author":["Benson, Roger B. J.","Várkonyi, Peter L.","Reisz, Robert R.","Domokos, Gábor"],"title":"Data from: Shell geometry and habitat determination in extinct and extant turtles (Reptilia: Testudinata)","host":"Benson RBJ, Domokos G, Várkonyi PL, Reisz RR (2011) Shell geometry and habitat determination in extinct and extant turtles (Reptilia: Testudinata). Paleobiology 37(4): 547-562.","description":"A number of means, including forelimb proportions and shell bone histology have been used to infer the paleoecology of extinct turtles. However, the height to width ratio of the shell (as a one-parameter shell model) has been dismissed because of its unreliability, and more complex aspects of shell geometry have generally been overlooked. Here we employ a more reliable, three-parameter geometric model of the shell outline in anterior view as a means to assess turtle paleoecology. The accuracy of predictions of extant turtle ecology based on our three-parameter shell model is comparable to that derived from forelimb proportions when distinguishing between three ecological classes (terrestrial, semi-aquatic and aquatic). Higher accuracy is obtained when distinguishing between two classes (terrestrial and non-terrestrial) since the contours of aquatic and semi-aquatic turtles are often very similar. Our model classifies Proterochersis robusta, a stem turtle from the Late Triassic of Germany, as non-terrestrial, and likely semi-aquatic. Our method, combined with inferences based on limb proportions, indicates a diverse range of ecotypes represented by Late Triassic stem turtles. This implies that the ecological diversification of stem-group turtles may have been rapid, or a substantial period of currently cryptic diversification preceded the first fossil appearance of the turtle stem lineage during the Late Triassic.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8705/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8705","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8705","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1666/10052.1","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8705"}}