{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Systematic Biology","keywords":["tree support","higher phylogeny","fungal evolution","large scale molecular phylogeny"],"host":"Moncalvo J-M, Lutzoni FM, Rehner SA, Johnson J, Vilgalys R (2000) Phylogenetic relationships of Agaric fungi based on nuclear large subunit ribosomal DNA sequences. Systematic Biology 49: 278-305.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.561/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.561","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T17:50:39Z","author":["Johnson, Jacqui","Lutzoni, François M.","Vilgalys, Rytas","Moncalvo, Jean-Marc","Rehner, Stephen A."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenetic relationships of Agaric fungi based on nuclear large subunit ribosomal DNA sequences","description":"Phylogenetic relationships of mushrooms and their relatives within the order Agaricales were addressed using nuclear large subunit ribosomal DNA sequences. Approximately 900 bases of the 5' end of the nucleus-encoded large subunit RNA gene (nLSU-rDNA) were sequenced for 154 selected taxa representing most families within the Agaricales. Several phylogenetic methods were used, including weighted and equally weighted parsimony (MP), maximum likelihood (ML), and distance methods (NJ). The starting tree for branch swapping in the ML analyses was the tree with the highest ML score among previously produced MP and NJ trees. A high degree of consensus was observed between phylogenetic estimates obtained through MP and ML. NJ trees differed according to the distance model that was used, however, all NJ trees still supported most of the same terminal groupings as MP and ML trees. NJ trees were always significantly suboptimal when evaluated against the best MP and ML trees, using both parsimony and likelihood tests. Our analyses suggest that weighted parsimony and ML provide the best estimates of Agaricales phylogeny. Similar support was observed between bootstrapping and jackknifing methods for evaluation of tree robustness. Phylogenetic analyses revealed many groups of agaricoid fungi that are supported by moderate to high bootstrap or jackknife levels or are consistent with morphology-based classification schemes. Analyzes also support separate placement of the boletes and russules, which are basal to the main core group of gilled mushrooms (the Agaricineae of Singer). Examples of monophyletic groups include the families Amanitaceae, Coprinaceae (excluding Coprinus comatus and subfamily Panaeolideae), Agaricaceae (excluding the Cystodermateae), and Strophariaceae pro parte (Stropharia, Pholiota, and Hypholoma); the mycorrhizal species of Tricholoma (including Leucopaxillus, also mycorrhizal); Mycena and Resinomycena; Termitomyces, Podabrella, and Lyophyllum; and Pleurotus with Hohenbuehelia. Several nonmonophyletic groups revealed by these data include the families Tricholomataceae, Cortinariaceae, and Hygrophoraceae and the genera Clitocybe, Omphalina, and Marasmius. This study provides a framework for future systematics studies in the Agaricales and suggestions for analyzing large molecular data sets.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.561","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1093/sysbio/49.2.278","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.561"}}