{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-24T21:14:49Z","author":["Boots, Michael","Bottery, Michael J.","Atkinson, David","Fenton, Andrew","Pastok, Daria","Knell, Robert J.","Hoare, Mary-Jo","Ryder, Jonathan J.","Hurst, Gregory D. D."],"title":"Data from: Disease epidemiology in arthropods is altered by the presence of non-protective symbionts","host":"Ryder JJ, Hoare M, Pastok D, Bottery MJ, Boots M, Fenton A, Atkinson D, Knell RJ, Hurst GDD (2014) Disease epidemiology in arthropods is altered by the presence of non-protective symbionts. The American Naturalist 183(3): E89-E104.","keywords":["Interactions: host/parasite","Ecology: community","Epidemiology","Mating systems","Immunity: ecology","Population: dynamics","Interactions: host/pathogen","Interactions: symbiosis"],"description":"Inherited microbial symbionts can modulate host susceptibility to natural enemy attack. A wider range of symbionts influence host population demography without altering individual susceptibility, and it has been suggested that these may modify host disease risk through altering the rate of exposure to natural enemies. We present the first test of this thesis, specifically testing whether male-killing symbionts alter the epidemiology of a sexually transmitted infection (STI) carried by its host. STIs are typically expected to show female-biased epidemics, and we first present a simple model which indicates that male-biased STI epidemics may occur where symbionts create female-biased population sex ratios. We then examined the dynamics of a STI in the ladybird beetle Adalia bipunctata, which is also host to a male-killing bacterium. We present evidence that male-biased epidemics of the STI are observed in natural populations when the male-killer is common. Laboratory experiments did not support a role for differential susceptibility of male and female hosts to the STI, nor a protective role for the symbiont, in creating this bias. We conclude that the range of symbionts likely to alter parasite epidemiology will be much wider than previously envisaged, because it will additionally include those that impact host demography alone.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1b2f0/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54251","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54251","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/674827","PMID:24561609"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1b2f0"}}