{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-31T15:08:32Z","author":["Schal, Coby","Silverman, Jules","Shik, Jonathan Z."],"title":"Data from: Diet specialization in an extreme omnivore: nutritional regulation in glucose-averse German cockroaches","host":"Shik JZ, Schal C, Silverman J (2014) Diet specialization in an extreme omnivore: nutritional regulation in glucose-averse German cockroaches. Journal of Evolutionary Biology, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Life history evolution","Herbivory","Evolutionary physiology","Natural selection","Insects"],"description":"Organisms have diverse adaptations for balancing dietary nutrients, but often face trade-offs between ingesting nutrients and toxins in food. While extremely omnivorous cockroaches would seem excluded from such dietary trade-offs, German cockroaches (Blattella germanica) in multiple populations have rapidly evolved a unique dietary specialization – an aversion to glucose, the phagostimulant in toxic baits used for pest control. We used factorial feeding experiments within the geometric framework to test whether glucose-averse (GA) cockroaches with limited access to this critical metabolic fuel have compensatory behavioural and physiological strategies for meeting nutritional requirements. GA cockroaches had severely constrained intake, fat and N mass, and performance on glucose-based diets relative to wild-type (WT) cockroaches and did not appear to exhibit digestive strategies for retaining undereaten nutrients. However, a GA × WT ‘hybrid’ had lower glucose aversion than GA and greater access to macronutrients within glucose-based diets – while still having lower intake and survival than WT. Given these intermediate foraging constraints, hybrids may be a reservoir for this maladaptive trait in the absence of positive selection and may account for the rapid evolution of this trait following bait application.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.063h8/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67494","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67494","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25078384","doi:10.1111/jeb.12458"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.063h8"}}