{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"333;21-34;2010","keywords":["soil nitrogen","Nitrogen availability","biogeochemistry","Drylands","Biological soil crusts"],"host":"Castillo-Monroy AP, Maestre FT, Delgado-Baquerizo M, Gallardo A (2010) Biological soil crusts modulate nitrogen availability in semi-arid ecosystems: insights from a Mediterranean grassland. Plant and Soil 333(1-2):21-34.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2sp49/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.45382","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2013-01-07T18:44:44Z","author":["Castillo-Monroy, Andrea P.","Maestre, Fernando T.","Gallardo, Antonio","Delgado-Baquerizo, Manuel"],"title":"Data from: Biological soil crusts modulate nitrogen availability in semi-arid ecosystems: insights from a Mediterranean grassland","description":"Biological soil crusts (BSCs) greatly influence the N cycle of semi-arid ecosystems, as some organisms forming them are able to fix atmospheric N. However, BSCs are not always taken into account when studying biotic controls on N cycling and transformations. Our main objective was to understand how BSCs modulate the availability of N in a semi-arid Mediterranean ecosystem dominated by the tussock grass Stipa tenacissima. We selected the six most frequent soil cover types in the study area: S. tenacissima tussocks (ST), Retama sphaerocarpa shrubs (RS), and open areas with very low (BS), low (LC) medium (MC) and high (HC) cover of well developed and lichen-dominated BSCs. The temporal dynamics of available N dynamics followed changes in soil moisture. Available NH4+-N did not differ between microsites, while available NO3--N was substantially higher in the RS than in any other microsite. No significant differences in the amount of available NO3--N were found between ST and BS microsites, but these microsites had more NO3--N than those dominated by BSCs (LC, MC and HC). Our results suggest that BSCs may be inhibiting nitrification, and highlight the importance of this biotic community as a modulator of the availability of N in semi-arid ecosystems.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.45382","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1007/s11104-009-0276-7","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2sp49"}}