{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-09-02T20:48:19Z","author":["Cedeno, Virna","Cruz, Marilyn","Cunningham, Andrew","Goodman, Simon","Bataille, Arnaud"],"title":"Data from: Seasonal effects and fine-scale population dynamics of Aedes taeniorhynchus, a major disease vector in the Galapagos Islands","host":"Bataille A, Cunningham AA, Cruz M, Cedeno V, Goodman SJ (2010) Seasonal effects and fine-scale population dynamics of Aedes taeniorhynchus, a major disease vector in the Galapagos Islands. Molecular Ecology 19(20): 4491-4504.","keywords":["Speciation","microsatellite","mosquito","Population Dynamics","Adaptation","selection"],"description":"Characterization of the fine-scale population dynamics of the mosquito Aedes taeniorhynchus is needed in order to improve our understanding of its role as a disease vector in the Galapagos Islands. We used microsatellite data to assess the genetic structure of coastal and highland mosquito populations and patterns of gene flow between the two habitats through time on Santa Cruz Island. In addition, we assessed possible associations of mosquito abundance and genetic diversity with environmental variables. The coastal and highland mosquito populations were highly differentiated from each other all year round, with some gene flow detected only during periods of increased precipitation. The results support the hypothesis that selection arising from ecological differences between habitats is driving adaptation and divergence in A. taeniorhynchus, and maintaining long term genetic differentiation of the populations against gene flow. The highland and lowland populations may constitute an example of incipient speciation in progress. Highland populations were characterized by lower observed heterozygosity and allelic richness, suggesting a founder effect and/or lower breeding site availability in the highlands. A lack of reduction in genetic diversity over time in highland populations suggests that they survive dry periods as dormant eggs. Association between mosquito abundance and precipitation was strong in the highlands whereas tide height was the main factor affecting mosquito abundance on the coast. Our findings suggests differences in the infection dynamics of mosquito-borne parasites in the highlands compared to the coast, and a higher risk of mosquito-driven disease spread across these habitats during periods of increased precipitation.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2013/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.2013","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.2013","isReferencedBy":["PMID:20875066","doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04843.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2013"}}