{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-04T14:23:04Z","author":["Lopez-Fernandez, Hernan","Arbour, Jessica"],"title":"Data from: Adaptive landscape and functional diversity of Neotropical cichlids: implications for the ecology and evolution of Cichlinae (Cichlidae; Cichliformes)","keywords":["SURFACE","Phylomorphospace","Morphological Evolution","Disparity","Adaptation","Fish","Ornstein-Uhlenbeck","Selection"],"description":"Morphological, lineage and ecological diversity can vary substantially even among closely related lineages. Factors that influence morphological diversification, especially in functionally-relevant traits, can help to explain the modern distribution of disparity across phylogenies and communities. Multivariate axes of feeding functional morphology from 75 species of Neotropical cichlid and a stepwise-AIC algorithm were used to estimate the adaptive landscape of functional morphospace in Cichlinae. Adaptive landscape complexity and convergence, as well as the functional diversity of Cichlinae, were compared with expectations under null evolutionary models. Neotropical cichlid feeding varied primarily between morphologies associated with ram-feeding vs. suction-feeding/biting, and secondarily with oral jaw muscle size and pharyngeal crushing capacity. The number of changes in selective regimes and the amount of convergence between lineages was higher than expected under a null model of evolution, but convergence was not higher than expected under a similarly complex adaptive landscape. Functional disparity was compatible with an adaptive landscape model, while the distribution of evolutionary change through morphospace corresponded with a process of evolution towards a single adaptive peak. The continentally-distributed Neotropical cichlids have evolved relatively rapidly towards a number of adaptive peaks in functional trait space. Selection in Cichlinae functional morphospace is more complex than expected under null evolutionary models. The complexity of selective constraints in feeding morphology has likely been a significant contributor to the diversity of feeding ecology in this clade.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.j04r6/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70154","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70154","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.j04r6"}}