{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"94;;2007","keywords":["rpoC1","nrITS","molecular phylogenetics","atpB-rbcL spacer","matK"],"host":"Whitten WM, Blanco MA, Williams NH, Koehler S, Carnevali G, Singer RB, Endara L, Neubig KM (2007) Molecular phylogenetics of Maxillaria and related genera (Orchidaceae: Cymbidieae) based on combined molecular data sets. American Journal of Botany 94(11): 1860-1889.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.s449d/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.s449d/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.s449d/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.s449d/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46096","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2013-01-28T18:48:54Z","author":["Singer, Rodrigo B.","Neubig, Kurt M.","Koehler, Samantha","Williams, Norris H.","Endara, Lorena","Carnevali, Germán","Blanco, Mario A.","Whitten, W. Mark"],"title":"Data from: Molecular phylogenetics of Maxillaria and related genera (Orchidaceae: Cymbidieae) based on combined molecular data sets","description":"The orchid genus Maxillaria is one of the largest and most common of neotropical orchid genera, but its current generic boundaries and relationships have long been regarded as artificial. Phylogenetic relationships within subtribe Maxillariinae sensu Dressler (1993) with emphasis on Maxillaria s.l. were inferred using parsimony analyses of individual and combined DNA sequence data. We analyzed a combined matrix of nrITS DNA, the plastid matK gene and flanking trnK intron, and the plastid atpB-rbcL intergenic spacer for 619 individuals representing ca. 354 species. The plastid rpoC1 gene (ca. 2600 bp) was sequenced for 84 selected species and combined in a more limited analysis with the other data sets to provide greater resolution. In a well-resolved, supported consensus, most clades were present in more than one individual analysis. All the currently recognized minor genera of “core” Maxillariinae (Anthosiphon, Chrysocycnis, Cryptocentrum, Cyrtidiorchis, Mormolyca, Pityphyllum, and Trigonidium) are embedded within a polyphyletic Maxillaria s.l. Our results support the recognition of a more restricted Maxillaria, of some previously published segregate genera (Brasiliorchis, Camaridium, Christensonella, Heterotaxis, Ornithidium, Sauvetrea), and of several novel clades at the generic level. These revised monophyletic generic concepts should minimize further nomenclatural changes, encourage monographic studies, and facilitate more focused analyses of character evolution within Maxillariinae.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46096","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21636381","doi:10.3732/ajb.94.11.1860"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s449d"}}