{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-04-25T14:08:59Z","author":["Martin, Thomas E.","Cheng, Yi-Ru"],"title":"Data from: Nest predation risk and growth strategies of passerine species: grow fast or develop traits to escape risk?","host":"Cheng Y, Martin TE (2012) Nest predation risk and growth strategies of passerine species: grow fast or develop traits to escape risk? The American Naturalist 180(3): 285-295.","keywords":["passerine","nest predation","differential growth","locomotor","endothermy"],"description":"Different body components are thought to trade off in their growth and development rates, but the causes for relative prioritization of any trait remains a critical question. Offspring of species at higher risk of predation might prioritize development of locomotor traits that facilitate escaping risky environments over growth of mass. We tested this possibility in 12 altricial passerine species that differed in their risk of nest predation. We found that rates of growth and development of mass, wings, and endothermy increased with nest predation risk across species. In particular, species with higher nest predation risk exhibited relatively faster growth of wings than of mass, fledged with relatively larger wing sizes and smaller mass, and developed endothermy earlier at relatively smaller mass. This differential development can facilitate both escape from predators and survival outside of the nest environment. Tarsus growth was not differentially prioritized with respect to nest predation risk, and instead all species achieved adult tarsus size by age of fledging. We also tested whether different foraging modes (aerial, arboreal, and ground foragers) might explain the variation of differential growth of locomotor modules, but we found that little residual variation was explained. Our results suggest that differences in nest predation risk among species are associated with relative prioritization of body components to facilitate escape from the risky nest environment.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.33d6c/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.33d6c/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.39912","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.39912","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/667214","PMID:22854072"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.33d6c"}}