{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-05-21T16:38:42Z","author":["Marhabaie, Mohammad","Miller, Jeremy","Scharff, Nikolaj","Szuts, Tamas","Rezac, Milan","Griswold, Charles"],"title":"Data from: The velvet spiders: an atlas of the Eresidae (Arachnida, Araneae)","host":"Miller J, Griswold C, Scharff N, Rezac M, Szuts T, Marhabaie M (2012) The velvet spiders: an atlas of the Eresidae (Arachnida, Araneae). ZooKeys 195(special issue): 1-144.","keywords":["spinneret spigot morphology","molecular phylogeny","taxonomy","ladybird spiders"],"description":"The family Eresidae C. L. Koch, 1850 is reviewed at the genus level. The family comprises nine genera including one new genus. They are: Adonea Simon, 1873, Dorceus C. L. Koch, 1846, Dresserus Simon, 1876, Eresus Walckenaer, 1805, Gandanameno Lehtinen, 1967, Loureedia gen. n., Paradonea Lawrence, 1968, Seothyra Purcell, 1903, and Stegodyphus Simon, 1873. A key to all genera and major lineages is provided along with corresponding diagnoses, as well as descriptions of selected species. These are documented with collections of photographs, scanning electron micrographs, and illustrations. A new phylogeny of Eresidae based on molecular sequence data expands on a previously published analysis. A species of the genus Paradonea Lawrence, 1968 is sequenced and placed phylogenetically for the first time. New sequences from twenty Gandanameno Lehtinen, 1967 specimens were added to investigate species limits within the genus. The genus Loureedia gen. n. is proposed to accommodate Eresus annulipes Lucas, 1857. Two species, Eresus semicanus Simon, 1908 and Eresus jerbae El-Hennawy, 2005, are synonymized with Loureedia annulipes comb. n. One new species, Paradonea presleyi sp. n. is described. Eresus algericus El-Hennawy, 2004 is transferred to Adonea Simon, 1873. The female of Dorceus fastuosus C. L. Koch, 1846 is described for the first time. The first figures depicting Paradonea splendens (Lawrence, 1936) are presented.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.qj8t7r0q/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.qj8t7r0q/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.qj8t7r0q/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38401","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38401","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.3897/zookeys.195.2342","PMID:22679386"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qj8t7r0q"}}