{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-31T18:15:12Z","author":"Smith, Samuel C.","title":"Data from: Prevention of surgical site infection in lower limb skin lesion excisions with single dose oral antibiotic prophylaxis: a prospective randomised placebo-controlled double-blind trial","host":"Smith SC, Heal CF, Buttner PG (2014) Prevention of surgical site infection in lower limb skin lesion excisions with single dose oral antibiotic prophylaxis: a prospective randomised placebo-controlled double-blind trial. BMJ Open 4(7): e005270.","description":"Objectives: To determine the effectiveness of a single perioperative prophylactic 2 g dose of cephalexin in preventing surgical site infection (SSI) following excision of skin lesions from the lower limb. Design: Prospective double-blinded placebo-controlled trial testing for difference in infection rates. Setting: Primary care in regional North Queensland, Australia. Participants: 52 patients undergoing lower limb skin lesion excision. Interventions: 2 g dose of cephalexin 30–60 min before excision. Main outcome measures: Incidence of SSI. Results: Incidence of SSI was 12.5% (95% CI 2.7% to 32.4%) in the cephalexin group compared with 35.7% (95% CI 18.6% to 55.9%) in the placebo group (p=0.064). This represented an absolute reduction of 23.21% (95% CI −0.39% to 46.82%), relative reduction of 65.00% (95% CI −12.70% to 89.13%) and number-needed-to-treat of 4.3. Conclusions: Administration of a single 2 g dose of cephalexin 30–60 min before skin lesion excision from the lower limb may produce a reduction in the incidence of infection; however, this study was underpowered to statistically determine this. Trial registration number: ACTRN12611000595910.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.k3r47/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67270","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67270","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005270","PMID:25079934"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.k3r47"}}