{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-12-01T23:47:04Z","author":["Foitzik, Susanne","Rüger, Markus H.","Metzler, Dirk","Kureck, Ilka M."],"title":"Data from: Macro- and microgeographic genetic structure in an ant species with alternative reproductive tactics in sexuals","host":"Foitzik S, Rüger MH, Kureck IM, Metzler D (2011) Macro- and microgeographic genetic structure in an ant species with alternative reproductive tactics in sexuals. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 24(12): 2721-2730.","keywords":["Phylogeography","Population genetics","alternative mating strategies","Ecological genetics","Insects"],"description":"The genetic structure of social insect populations is influenced by their social organisation and dispersal modes. The ant Hypoponera opacior shows diverse reproductive behaviours with regular cycles of outbreeding via winged sexuals and inbreeding via within-nest mating wingless sexuals that reproduce by budding. This unusual life cycle should be reflected in the genetic population structure and we studied this on different scales using microsatellites. On a macrogeographic scale, populations were considerably structured and migration rates within the Chiricahuas were higher than those in-between mountain ranges. On a local scale, our analyses revealed population viscosity through dependant colony foundation and a high genetic diversity with a multi-colonial structure. The latter was also evident from recognition trials revealing consistent aggression between non-nestmates. Within-nest matings led to high inbreeding coefficients. Finally, the observed seasonal changes in relatedness can be explained by variation in queen number and differential dispersal of the two reproductive morphs.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.h8j0q71g/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.h8j0q71g/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34999","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34999","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1420-9101.2011.02397.x","PMID:21995865"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h8j0q71g"}}