{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-05T18:23:09Z","author":["Moran, Jennifer R.","Wu, Mao-Lien","Boussy, Ian A.","Ting, Chau-Ti","Earley, Eric J.","Wu, Chung-I","Hungate, Eric A.","Turissini, David A.","Jones, Corbin D."],"title":"Data from: A locus in Drosophila sechellia affecting tolerance of  a host plant toxin","host":"Hungate EA, Earley EJ, Boussy IA, Turissini DA, Ting C, Moran JR, Wu M, Wu C, Jones CD (2013) A locus in Drosophila sechellia affecting tolerance of a host plant toxin. Genetics 195(3): 1063-1075.","keywords":["host specialization","speciation","octanoic acid","adaptation"],"description":"Many insects feed on only one or a few types of host. These host specialists often evolve a preference for chemical cues emanting from their host and develop mechanisms for circumventing their host’s defenses. Adaptations like these are central to evolutionary biology, yet our understanding of their genetics remains incomplete. Drosophila sechellia, an emerging model for the genetics of host specialization, is an island endemic that has adapted to chemical toxins present in the fruit of its host plant, Morinda citrifolia. Its sibling species, D. simulans, and many other Drosophila species do not tolerate these toxins and avoid the fruit. Earlier work showed that a region with a strong effect on tolerance to the major toxin, octanoic acid, was on chromosome arm 3R. Using a novel assay we narrowed this region to a small span near the centromere containing 18 genes, including three odorant binding proteins. It has been hypothesized that the evolution of host specialization is facilitated by genetic linkage between alleles contributing to host preference and alleles contributing to host usage, such as tolerance to secondary compounds. We tested this hypothesis by measuring the effect of this tolerance locus on host preference behavior. Our data were inconsistent with the linkage hypothesis as flies bearing this tolerance region showed no increase in preference for media containing M. citrifolia toxins, which D. sechellia prefers. Thus, in contrast to some models for host preference, preference and tolerance are not tightly linked at this locus and increased tolerance per se is not sufficient to change preference. Our data are consistent with the previously proposed model that the evolution of D. sechellia as a M. citrifolia specialist occurred through a step-wise loss of aversion and gain of tolerance to M. citrifolia’s toxins.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rp6gt/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53188","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53188","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1534/genetics.113.154773","PMID:24037270"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rp6gt"}}