{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Molecular and Biochemical Parisitology","keywords":["hookworm","ASP","microarray","parasitic transition","mixed model ANOVA"],"host":"Moser JM, Freitas T, Arasu P, Gibson G (2005) Gene expression profiles associated with the transition to parasitism in Ancylostoma caninum larvae. Molecular and Biochemical Parasitology 143(1):39-48.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.972/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.972/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.972/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.972/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.972","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-01T20:18:04Z","author":["Moser, Jennifer M.","Gibson, Greg","Arasu, Prema","Freitas, Tori"],"title":"Data from: Gene expression profiles associated with the transition to parasitism in Ancylostoma caninum larvae","description":"Ancylostoma caninum is a common canine parasite responsible for anemia and death in infected dogs. Gene expression profiling was used to investigate molecular differences between two different forms of the third larval stage (L3s): infective free-living larvae and in vitro serum-stimulated larvae that mimic the initial stages of parasitism of a host. We developed an A. caninum cDNA microarray consisting of 4191 EST clones, and used it to identify a set of 113 genes that are differentially regulated between infective and parasitic larval stages. Real-time RT-PCR was used to confirm the expression differences of a subset of the genes. Of the genes repressed upon serum stimulation, seven encode members of the 'Ancylostoma secreted protein' ASP family, while another transcript encoding a 24 kDa excretory protein with similarity to ASP was up-regulated in serum-stimulated L3s. This suggests that different members of a protein family that has important implications for the hookworm's parasitic lifestyle are regulated in a complementary manner in response to serum stimulation. Comparison of two strains of A. caninum from North Carolina and Maryland only identified a single gene, one of the members of the ASP family, that was differentially repressed upon serum stimulation.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.972","isReferencedBy":["PMID:15979737","doi:10.1016/j.molbiopara.2005.04.012"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.972"}}