{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-22T14:43:15Z","author":["Sampedro, Luis","Zas, Rafael"],"title":"Data from: Heritability of seed weight in Maritime pine, a relevant trait in the transmission of environmental maternal effects","keywords":["Seed mass","Transgenerational plasticity","Conifer","Seed mass variability","Additive genetic variation","Seed provisioning","Quantitative genetics","Long-lived plants","Phenotypic plasticity"],"description":"Quantitative seed provisioning is an important life- history trait with strong effects on offspring phenotype and fitness. As for any other trait, heritability estimates are vital for understanding its evolutionary dynamics. However, being a trait in between two generations, estimating additive genetic variation of seed provisioning requires complex quantitative genetic approaches for distinguishing between true genetic and environmental maternal effects. Here, using Maritime pine as a long-lived plant model, we quantified additive genetic variation of cone and seed weight (SW) mean and SW within-individual variation. We used a powerful approach combining both half-sib analysis and parent-offspring regression using several common- garden tests established in contrasting environments to separate G, E and G×E effects. Both cone weight and SW mean showed significant genetic variation and were largely influenced by the maternal environment. Most of the large variation in SW mean was attributable to additive genetic effects (h¬2 = 0.55 - 0.74). SW showed no apparent G × E interaction, particularly when accounting for cone weight covariation, suggesting that the maternal genotypes actively control the SW mean irrespective of the amount of resources allocated to cones. Within-individual variation in SW was low (12%) relatively to between-individual variation (88%), and showed no genetic variation but was largely affected by the maternal environmental, with greater variation in the less favourable sites for pine growth. In summary, results were very consistent between the parental and the offspring common garden tests, and clearly indicated heritable genetic variation for SW mean but not for within-individual variation in SW.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.60j76/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68117","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68117","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.60j76"}}