{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-28T18:25:45Z","author":["Wisser, Randall J.","Hallauer, Arnel R.","Xu, Wenwei","Murray, Seth","Hessel, David","Weldekidan, Teclemariam","Hawk, James","Flint-Garcia, Sherry","Kleintop, Adrienne","Teixeira, Juliana","Leon, Natalia de","Lauter, Nick","Holland, James"],"title":"Data from: Hallauer's Tusón: a decade of selection for tropical- to-temperate phenological adaptation in maize","keywords":["flowering time","maize","selection response","photoperiod","climate change","adaptation"],"description":"Crop species exhibit an astounding capacity for environmental adaptation, but genetic bottlenecks resulting from intense selection for adaptation and productivity can lead to a genetically vulnerable crop. Improving the genetic resiliency of temperate maize depends upon the use of tropical germplasm, which harbors a rich source of natural allelic diversity. Here, the adaptation process was studied in a tropical maize population subjected to ten recurrent generations of directional selection for early flowering in a single temperate environment in Iowa, USA. We evaluated the response to this selection across a geographical range spanning from 43.05 (WI) to 18.00 (PR) latitude. The capacity for an all- tropical maize population to become adapted to a temperate environment was revealed in dramatic fashion: on average, families from generation 10 flowered 20 days earlier than families in generation 0, with a nine day separation between the latest generation 10 family and the earliest generation 0 family. Results suggest that adaptation was primarily due to selection on genetic main effects tailored to temperature-dependent plasticity in flowering time. Genotype-by-environment interactions represented a relatively small component of the phenotypic variation in flowering time, but were sufficient to produce a signature of localized adaptation that radiated latitudinally, in partial association with daylength and temperature, from the original location of selection. Furthermore, the original population exhibited a maladaptive syndrome including excessive ear and plant heights along with later flowering; this was dramatically reduced in frequency by selection for flowering time.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8f64f/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.69792","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.69792","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8f64f"}}