{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-11T15:17:04Z","author":["Skrede, Inger","Kauserud, Håvard","Maurice, Sundy"],"title":"Data from: Molecular characterization of sexual diversity in a population of Serpula lacrymans, a tetrapolar basidiomycete","host":"Skrede I, Maurice S, Kauserud H (2013) Molecular characterization of sexual diversity in a population of Serpula lacrymans, a tetrapolar basidiomycete. G3: Genes - Genomes - Genetics 3(2): 145-152.","keywords":["dry rot","tetrapolar","mating type","fungus","population diversity"],"description":"Different mating systems have evolved in the fungal kingdom, including a tetrapolar multiallelic mating system in many basidiomycetes. In tetrapolar species, the presence of different alleles at two mating loci (MAT A and MAT B) is necessary for mating to occur. The tetrapolar fungus Serpula lacrymans causes wood-decay in buildings in temperate regions worldwide and is present in Europe with a genetically homogeneous founder population. Using genome sequence data, we annotated the two mating type loci for S. lacrymans and found the expected synteny with other basidiomycetes, except for a retrotransposon being present in one locus (MAT A). We developed markers linked to the MAT A and MAT B regions and used these to investigate the mating type diversity in the European population. Moreover, we found a good match between the genetic markers and functional mating types as revealed by segregation and mating studies. A low diversity of mating types is present in the European S. lacrymans population caused by the founder event where a limited number of genotypes were introduced. This finding contrasts the situation in natural fungal populations where a high diversity of mating types is normally present. Although S. lacrymans has a large and viable population in Europe, we argue that the low mating type diversity restrains the dispersal and establishment of the fungus.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.gr6b8/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.gr6b8/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.gr6b8/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44542","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44542","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23390592","doi:10.1534/g3.112.003731"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gr6b8"}}