{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-10T18:30:25Z","author":["Kane, Emily A.","Higham, Timothy E."],"title":"Data from: Modelled three-dimensional suction accuracy predicts prey capture success in three species of centrarchid fishes","host":"Kane EA, Higham TE (2014) Modelled three-dimensional suction accuracy predicts prey capture success in three species of centrarchid fishes. Journal of the Royal Society Interface 11(95): 20140223.","keywords":["suction accuracy","ingested volume","performance","capture success","prey capture"],"description":"Prey capture is critical for survival, and differences in correctly positioning and timing a strike (accuracy) are likely related to variation in capture success. However, an ability to quantify accuracy under natural conditions, particularly for fishes, is lacking. We developed a predictive model of suction hydrodynamics and applied it to natural behaviours using three-dimensional kinematics of three centrarchid fishes capturing evasive and non-evasive prey. A spheroid ingested volume of water (IVW) with dimensions predicted by peak gape and ram speed was verified with known hydrodynamics for two species. Differences in capture success occurred primarily with evasive prey (64–96% success). Micropterus salmoides had the greatest ram and gape when capturing evasive prey, resulting in the largest and most elongate IVW. Accuracy predicted capture success, although other factors may also be important. The lower accuracy previously observed in M. salmoides was not replicated, but this is likely due to more natural conditions in our study. Additionally, we discuss the role of modulation and integrated behaviours in shaping the IVW and determining accuracy. With our model, accuracy is a more accessible performance measure for suction-feeding fishes, which can be used to explore macroevolutionary patterns of prey capture evolution.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.hf591/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.hf591/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.hf591/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.hf591/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61401","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61401","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rsif.2014.0223","PMID:24718455"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.hf591"}}