{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-18T14:22:21Z","author":["Taylor, Eric","Tonn, William","Bajno, Robert","Wiley, Simon","Howland, Kimberly","Chavarie, Louise","Harris, Les"],"title":"Data from: Evolution and origin of sympatric shallow-water morphotypes of Lake Trout, Salvelinus namaycush, in Canada's Great Bear Lake","keywords":["morphotypes","sympatric","post-glacial dispersal","allopatric","lake trout"],"description":"Range expansion in north-temperate fishes subsequent to the retreat of the Wisconsinan glaciers has resulted in the rapid colonization of previously unexploited, heterogeneous habitats and, in many situations, secondary contact among conspecific lineages that were once previously isolated. Such ecological opportunity coupled with reduced competition likely promoted morphological and genetic differentiation within and among post- glacial fish populations. Discrete morphological forms existing in sympatry, for example, have now been described in many species, yet few studies have directly assessed the association between morphological and genetic variation. Morphotypes of Lake Trout, Salvelinus namaycush, are found in several large-lake systems including Great Bear Lake (GBL), Northwest Territories, Canada, where several shallow-water forms are known. Here, we assess microsatellite and mtDNA variation among four morphotypes of Lake Trout from the five distinct arms of GBL, including locations from outside of this system to evaluate several hypotheses concerning the nature and origin of morphological variation in this species. Our data indicate that morphotypes of Lake Trout from GBL are genetically differentiated from one another, yet they are still more genetically similar to one another compared to those from outside of this system. Furthermore, our data suggest that Lake Trout colonized GBL following dispersal from a single refugium (the Mississippian) and support an intra-lake model of divergence. Overall, our study provides novel insights into the origins of morphological and genetic variation in post-glacial populations of fishes and provides benchmarks important for monitoring Lake Trout biodiversity in a region thought to be disproportionately affected by climate change.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1368p/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67908","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67908","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1368p"}}