{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-06T18:59:35Z","author":["Wetzel, Stefan","Hartmann, Nicole","Eichenberger, Juerg","Petersen, Frank","Frederiksen, Mathias","Movva, N. Rao","Cerino, Raffaele","Chang, Lena","Oakeley, Edward J.","Fishman, Mark C.","Petitjean, Virginie","Sadlish, Heather","Staedtler, Frank","Altorfer, Marc","Brachat, Sophie","Bhullar, Bhupinder","Hohendahl, Annika","Aust, Thomas","Filipuzzi, Ireos","Hoepfner, Dominic","Porter, Jeffrey A.","Abraham, Yann","Studer, Christian","Nigsch, Florian","Estoppey, David","Baeriswyl, Lukas","Plikat, Uwe","Riedl, Ralph","Schuierer, Sven","Melin, Nicolas","Tallarico, John A.","Schmitt, Esther K.","Krastel, Philipp","Knapp, Britta","Helliwell, Stephen B."],"title":"Data from: High-resolution chemical dissection of a model eukaryote reveals targets, pathways and gene functions","host":"Hoepfner D, Helliwell SB, Sadlish H, Schuierer S, Filipuzzi I, Brachat S, Bhullar B, Plikat U, Abraham Y, Altorfer M, Aust T, Baeriswyl L, Cerino R, Chang L, Estoppey D, Eichenberger J, Frederiksen M, Hartmann N, Hohendahl A, Knapp B, Krastel P, Melin N, Nigsch F, Oakeley EJ, Petitjean V, Petersen F, Riedl R, Schmitt EK, Staedtler F, Studer C, Tallarico JA, Wetzel S, Fishman MC, Porter JA, Movva NR (2013) High-resolution chemical dissection of a model eukaryote reveals targets, pathways and gene functions. Microbiological Research 169(2–3): 107–120.","keywords":["Mechanism of action","Bioactive molecules","Chemogenomic profiling","Target identification","HIP","HOP","Genomics","Yeast"],"description":"Due to evolutionary conservation of biology, experimental knowledge captured from genetic studies in eukaryotic model organisms provides insight into human cellular pathways and ultimately physiology. Yeast chemogenomic profiling is a powerful approach for annotating cellular responses to small molecules. Using an optimized platform, we provide the relative sensitivities of the heterozygous and homozygous deletion collections for nearly 1800 biologically active compounds. The data quality enables unique insights into pathways that are sensitive and resistant to a given perturbation, as demonstrated with both known and novel compounds. We present examples of novel compounds that inhibit the therapeutically relevant fatty acid synthase and desaturase (Ole1p and Fas1p), and demonstrate how the individual profiles facilitate hypothesis-driven experiments to delineate compound mechanism of action. Importantly, the scale and diversity of tested compounds yields a dataset where the number of modulated pathways approaches saturation. This resource can be used to map novel biological connections, and also identify functions for unannotated genes. We validated hypotheses generated by global 2-way hierarchical clustering of profiles for (i) novel compounds with a similar mechanism of action acting upon microtubules or vacuolar ATPases, and (ii) an un-annotated ORF, YIL060w, that plays a role in respiration in the mitochondria. Finally, we identify and characterize background mutations in the widely used yeast deletion collection which should improve the interpretation of past and future screens throughout the community. This comprehensive resource of cellular responses enables the expansion of our understanding of eukaryotic pathway biology.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56770","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56770","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24360837","doi:10.1016/j.micres.2013.11.004"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v5m8v"}}