{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-12T18:24:51Z","author":"Hartfield, Matthew","title":"Data from: A framework for estimating the fixation time of an advantageous allele in stepping-stone models","host":"Hartfield M (2012) A framework for estimating the fixation time of an advantageous allele in stepping-stone models. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 25(9): 1751-1764.","keywords":["Branching Process","Population genetics","Beneficial alleles","Population subdivision","Adaptation","Simulation","Torus model","Stepping-stone model","Fixation time","Theory"],"description":"Determining how population subdivision increases the fixation time of an advantageous allele is an important problem in evolutionary genetics as this influences many processes. Here, I lay out a framework for calculating the fixation time of a positively selected allele in a subdivided population, as a function of the number of demes present, the migration rate between them, and the manner in which they are connected. Using this framework it becomes clear that a beneficial allele's fixation time is significantly reduced through migration continuously introducing copies of the allele into a newly-colonised subpopulation, increasing its frequency within these demes. The effect that migration has on allele frequency needs to be explicitly taken into account to produce a realistic estimate of fixation time. This behaviour is most prominent when demes are arranged on a two-dimensional torus, in comparison to populations where demes are arranged in a circle. This is because each subpopulation is connected to several neighbours over a torus, so that there are multiple paths that an allele can take in order to fix. As a consequence, some demes experience a greater influx and efflux of migrants than others. Analytical results are found to be very accurate when compared to stochastic simulations, and are generally robust if there are a large number of demes, or if the allele is weakly selected for.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.407j1/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.39826","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.39826","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1420-9101.2012.02560.x","PMID:22805049"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.407j1"}}