{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-10-03T16:36:01Z","author":["Kiehart, Ryan","Berdan, Emma L.","Fuller, Rebecca C.","Rayburn, A. Lane","Ming, Ray","Kozak, Genevieve M."],"title":"Data from: Insight into genomic changes accompanying divergence: genetic linkage maps and synteny of Lucania goodei and L. parva reveal a Robertsonian fusion","host":"Berdan EL, Kozak GM, Ming R, Rayburn AL, Kiehart R, Fuller RC (2014) Insight into genomic changes accompanying divergence: genetic linkage maps and synteny of Lucania goodei and L. parva reveal a Robertsonian fusion. G3: Genes - Genomes - Genetics 4(8):1363-72.","keywords":["Speciation","Synteny","Linkage map","medaka","Robertsonian fusion","Chromosomal rearrangement","EST-based SNPs"],"description":"Linkage maps are important tools in evolutionary genetics and in studies of speciation. We performed a karyotyping study and constructed high-density linkage maps for two closely related killifish species, Lucania parva and Lucania goodei, that differ in salinity tolerance and still hybridize in their contact zone in Florida. Using SNPs from orthologous EST contigs, we compared synteny between the two species to determine how genomic architecture has shifted with divergence. Karyotyping revealed that L. goodei possesses 24 acrocentric chromosomes (1N) while L. parva possesses 23 chromosomes (1N), one of which is a large metacentric chromosome. Likewise, high-density SNP-based linkage maps indicated 24 linkage groups for L. goodei and 23 linkage groups for L. parva. Synteny mapping revealed two linkage groups in L. goodei that were highly syntenic with the largest linkage group in L. parva. Together, this evidence points to the largest linkage group in L. parva being the result of a chromosomal fusion. We further compared synteny between Lucania with the genome of a more distant teleost relative medaka (Oryzias latipes) and found good conservation of synteny at the chromosomal level. Each Lucania linkage group had a single best match with each medaka chromosome. These results provide the groundwork for future studies on the genetic architecture of reproductive isolation and salinity tolerance in Lucania and other Fundulidae.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.80822/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.80822/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.80822/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64825","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64825","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1534/g3.114.012096","PMID:24898707"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.80822"}}