{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-06-25T20:13:22Z","author":["Grande, Terry","Smith, William Leo","Borden, W. Calvin"],"title":"Data from: Limits and relationships of Paracanthopterygii: a molecular framework for evaluating past morphological hypotheses","host":"Grande T, Borden WC, Smith WL (2013) Limits and relationships of Paracanthopterygii: A molecular framework for evaluating past morphological hypotheses. Mesozoic Fishes 5: 385-418.","description":"Gadiforms and percopsiforms have historically been treated as prototypical or core paracanthopterygians. As such, they are the keys to unlocking the evolutionary history and limits of a revised Paracanthopterygii; therefore, we address the taxonomic compositions of gadiforms and percopsiforms and how they are related to each other and other putative basal acanthomorphs. We address these questions by first constructing a phylogenetic hypothesis based on multiple molecular sequences. Both maximum likelihood and parsimony criteria strongly support a Paracanthopterygii comprised of Percopsiformes + [Zeiformes + (Gadiformes + Stylephorus)]. Polymixiids are sister to this clade. Polymixiids + paracanthopterygians are in turn sister to the acanthopterygians (batrachoidiforms, beryciforms, lophiiforms, ophidioids, percomorphs) in the parsimony analysis but sister to Acanthopterygii  + Lampriformes (minus Stylephorus) in the likelihood analysis. A review of published morphological characters, putatively pertinent to paracanthopterygian systematics were evaluated by the direct examination of specimens. Results find high congruence between the molecular tree and character-state distributions for many of these internal relationships. New interpretations of homologies of published characters are proposed based on topological and phylogenetic data.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.k4m8t/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.41087","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.41087","isReferencedBy":"ISBN:978-3-89937-159-8","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.k4m8t"}}