{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-29T14:49:37Z","author":["Kölliker, Mathias","Stucki, Dimitri"],"title":"Data from: Coevolutionary feedbacks between family interactions and life history","host":"Stucki D, Kölliker M (2013) Coevolutionary feedbacks between family interactions and life history. Evolution 67(11): 3208–3220.","keywords":["begging origin","inter/intra-brood","conflict","co-adaptation","sensory bias","scramble competition"],"description":"Families with parental care show a parent–offspring conflict over the amount of parental investment. To date, the resolution of this conflict was modeled as being driven by either purely within-brood or between-brood competition. In reality the partitioning of parental resources within- versus between-broods is an evolving life history trait, which can be affected by parent–offspring interactions. This coevolutionary feedback between life history and family interactions may influence the evolutionary process and outcome of parent–offspring coadaptation. We used a genetic framework for a simulation model where we allowed parental parity to coevolve with traits that determine parental investment. The model included unlinked loci for clutch size, parental sensitivity, baseline provisioning, and offspring begging. The simulation showed that tight coadaptation of parent and offspring traits only occurred in iteroparous outcomes whereas semelparous outcomes were characterized by weak coadaptation. When genetic variation in clutch size was unrestricted in the ancestral population, semelparity and maximal begging with poor coadaptation evolved throughout. Conversely, when genetic variation was limited to iteroparous conditions, and/or when parental sensitivity was treated as an evolutionarily fixed sensory bias, coadapted outcomes were more likely. Our findings show the influence of a feedback between parity, coadaptation, and conflict on the evolution of parent–offspring interactions.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5j129/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.50359","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.50359","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12187","PMID:24152003"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5j129"}}