{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-07T14:42:16Z","author":["Beutel, Rolf","Holland, Barbara","Blanke, Alexander","Greve, Carola","Misof, Bernhard","Wipfler, Benjamin"],"title":"Data from: The identification of concerted convergence in insect heads corroborates Palaeoptera","host":"Blanke A, Greve C, Wipfler B, Beutel R, Holland B, Misof B (2012) The identification of concerted convergence in insect heads corroborates Palaeoptera. Systematic Biology 62(2): 250-263.","keywords":["homoplasy","character clique","mouthparts","convergent evolution"],"description":"The relationships of the three major clades of winged insects - Ephemeroptera, Odonata and Neoptera - are still unclear. Many morphologists favor a clade Metapterygota (Odonata+Neoptera), but Chiastomyaria (Ephemeroptera+Neoptera) or Palaeoptera (Ephemeroptera+Odonata) have also been supported in some older and more recent studies.\n\nA possible explanation for the difficulties in resolving these relationships is concerted convergence - the convergent evolution of entire character complexes under the same or similar selective pressures.\n\nIn this study we analyse possible instances of this phenomenon in the context of head structures of Ephemeroptera, Odonata and Neoptera. We apply a recently introduced formal approach to detect the occurrence of concerted convergence.\n\nWe found that characters of the tentorium and mandibles in particular, but also some other head structures, have apparently not evolved independently, and thus can cause artefacts in tree reconstruction. Our subsequent analyses, which exclude character sets that may be affected by concerted convergence, corroborate the Palaeoptera concept. We show that the analysis of homoplasy and its influence on tree inference can be formally improved with important consequences for the identification of incompatibilities between datasets. Our results suggest that modified weighting (or exclusion of characters) in cases of formally identified correlated cliques of characters may improve morphology based tree reconstruction.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40270","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40270","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23179601","doi:10.1093/sysbio/sys091"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1q3b6"}}