{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-16T18:49:18Z","author":["Liu, Fengxiang","Bodner, Melissa","Zhang, Junxia","Li, Daiqin","Xin, Xu","Liu, Qinqing","Maddison, Wayne P."],"title":"Data from: The deep phylogeny of jumping spiders (Araneae, Salticidae)","host":"Maddison WP, Li D, Bodner M, Zhang J, Xin X, Liu Q, Liu F (2014) The deep phylogeny of jumping spiders (Araneae, Salticidae). ZooKeys 440: 57-87.","keywords":["phylogeny","systematics","jumping spiders"],"description":"In order to resolve better the deep relationships among salticid spiders, we compiled and analyzed a molecular dataset of 169 salticid taxa (and 7 outgroups) and 8 gene regions. This dataset adds many new taxa to previous analyses, especially among the non-salticoid salticids, as well as two new genes – wingless and myosin heavy chain. Both of these genes, and especially the better sampled wingless, confirm many of the relationships indicated by other genes. The cocalodines are placed as sister to lapsiines, in a broader clade with the spartaeines. Cocalodines, lapsiines, and spartaeines are each supported as monophyletic, though the first two have no known morphological synapomorphies. The lyssomanines appear to be non-monophyletic, of three separate groups: (1) Lyssomanes plus Chinoscopus, (2) Onomastus, and (3) the remainder of Old World species. Several previously-inferred relationships continue to be supported: hisponines as sister to the Salticoida, Amycoida as sister to the remaining Salticoida, and Saltafresia as monophyletic. The relationship of Salticus with Philaeus and relatives is now considered well enough corroborated to move the latter into the subfamily Salticinae. A new clade consisting of the Plexippoida + Aelurilloida + Leptorchesteae + Salticinae is recognized. Nungia is found to be an astioid, and Echeclus, Gedea and Diplocanthopoda to be hasariines. The euophryines are corroborated as monophyletic. The agoriines Agorius and Synagelides are salticoids, within the sister group to amycoids, but their further placement is problematical, perhaps because of their nuclear ribosomal genes’ high GC bias, as also seen in the similarly problematic Eupoa.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v53h1/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66746","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66746","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.3897/zookeys.440.7891","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v53h1"}}