{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"280;1766;2013","keywords":["alternative prey","handling time","species abundances","per capita attack rate","predator-prey","species interactions","predator diet","feeding survey","food webs","interaction strengths"],"host":"Novak M (2013) Trophic omnivory across a productivity gradient: intraguild predation theory and the structure and strength of species interactions. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 280(1766): 20131415.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.6k144/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.6k144/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.6k144/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.6k144/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.58950","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2014-01-30T17:07:01Z","author":"Novak, Mark","title":"Data from: Trophic omnivory across a productivity gradient: intraguild predation theory and the structure and strength of species interactions","description":"Intraguild predation theory centres on two predictions: (i) for an omnivore and an intermediate predator (IG-prey) to coexist on shared resources, the IG-prey must be the superior resource competitor, and (ii) increasing resource productivity causes the IG-prey's equilibrium abundance to decline. I tested these predictions with a series of species-rich food webs along New Zealand's rocky shores, focusing on two predatory whelks, Haustrum haustorium, a trophic omnivore, and Haustrum scobina, the IG-prey. In contrast to theory, the IG-prey's abundance increased with productivity. Furthermore, feeding rates and allometric considerations indicate a competitive advantage for the omnivore when non-shared prey are considered, despite the IG-prey's superiority for shared prey. Nevertheless, clear and regular cross-gradient changes in network structure and interaction strengths were observed that challenge the assumptions of current theory. These insights suggest that the consideration of consumer-dependent functional responses, non-equilibrium dynamics, the dynamic nature of prey choice and non-trophic interactions among basal prey will be fruitful avenues for theoretical development.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.58950","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23864601","doi:10.1098/rspb.2013.1415"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6k144"}}