{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"10;112;2010","keywords":["genetics","UV-B","metabolic pathways","marker","QTL","cotyledon","signal transduction pathways","loci"],"host":"Conte M, de Simone S, Simmons SJ, Ballaré CL, Stapleton AE (2010) Chromosomal loci important for cotyledon opening under UV-B in Arabidopsis thaliana. BMC Plant Biology 10: 112.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1/6"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.41050","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2012-07-16T19:48:47Z","author":["Stapleton, Ann E.","Conte, Mariana","Simmons, Susan J.","de Simone, Silvia","Ballaré, Carlos L."],"title":"Data from: Chromosomal loci important for cotyledon opening under UV-B in Arabidopsis thaliana","description":"BACKGROUND: Understanding of the genetic architecture of plant UV-B responses allows extensive targeted testing of candidate genes or regions, along with combinations of those genes, for placement in metabolic or signal transduction pathways. RESULTS: Composite interval mapping and single-marker analysis methods were used to identify significant loci for cotyledon opening under UV-B in four sets of recombinant inbred lines. In addition, loci important for canalization (stability) of cotyledon opening were detected in two mapping populations. One candidate locus contained the gene HY5. Mutant analysis demonstrated that HY5 was required for UV-B-specific cotyledon opening. CONCLUSIONS: Structured mapping populations provide key information on the degree of complexity in the genetic control of UV-B-induced cotyledon opening in Arabidopsis. The loci identified using quantitative trait analysis methods are useful for follow-up testing of candidate genes.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.41050","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1186/1471-2229-10-112","PMID:20565708"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.83kd1"}}