{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-08T17:42:55Z","author":["Dolinar, Branko","Cox, Karen","Gyselings, Ralf","Božič, Gregor","Vanden Broeck, An","Van Landuyt, Wouter","Valentin, Bertille","Oostermeijer, Gerard","De Bruyn, Luc","Mergeay, Joachim","Illyés, Zoltán"],"title":"Data from: High levels of effective long-distance dispersal may blur ecotypic divergence in a rare terrestrial orchid","host":"Vanden Broeck A, Van Landuyt W, Cox K, De Bruyn L, Gyselings R, Oostermeijer G, Valentin B, Božič G, Dolinar B, Illyés Z, Mergeay J (2014) High levels of effective long-distance dispersal may blur ecotypic divergence in a rare terrestrial orchid. BMC Ecology 14: 20.","keywords":["ecotypic divergence","gene flow","long-distance seed dispersal","amplified fragment length polymorphism  (AFLP)"],"description":"Background: Gene flow and adaptive divergence are key aspects of metapopulation dynamics and ecological speciation. Long-distance dispersal is hard to detect and few studies estimate dispersal in combination with adaptive divergence. The aim of this study was to investigate effective long-distance dispersal and adaptive divergence in the fen orchid (Liparis loeselii (L.) Rich.). We used amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP)-based assignment tests to quantify effective long-distance dispersal at two different regions in Northwest Europe. In addition, genomic divergence between fen orchid populations occupying two distinguishable habitats, wet dune slacks and alkaline fens, was investigated by a genome scan approach at different spatial scales (continental, landscape and regional) and based on 451 AFLP loci. Results: We expected that different habitats would contribute to strong divergence and restricted gene flow resulting in isolation-by-adaptation. Instead, we found remarkably high levels of effective long-distance seed dispersal and low levels of adaptive divergence. At least 15% of the assigned individuals likely originated from among-population dispersal events with dispersal distances up to 220 km. Six (1.3%) ‘outlier’ loci, potentially reflecting local adaptation to habitat-type, were identified with high statistical support. Of these, only one (0.22%) was a replicated outlier in multiple independent dune-fen population comparisons and thus possibly reflecting truly parallel divergence. Signals of adaptation in response to habitat type were most evident at the scale of individual populations. Conclusions: The findings of this study suggest that the homogenizing effect of effective long-distance seed dispersal may overwhelm divergent selection associated to habitat type in fen orchids in Northwest Europe.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sb68v/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66168","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66168","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1186/1472-6785-14-20","PMID:24998243"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sb68v"}}