{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-27T19:03:16Z","author":["Hoerter, Andrew M.","Schabath, Mattthew B.","Hang, Gang","Eschrich, Steven","Morgan, Scott","Fenstermacher, David A.","Bhansali, Neera","Bloom, Gregory C."],"title":"Data from: Development and application of a novel metric to assess effectiveness of biomedical data","host":"Bloom GC, Eschrich S, Hang G, Schabath MB, Bhansali N, Hoerter AM, Morgan S, Fenstermacher DA (2013) Development and application of a novel metric to assess effectiveness of biomedical data. BMJ Open 3(8): e003220.","keywords":["Health informatics","Epidemiology","Oncology"],"description":"Objective: Design a metric to assess the comparative effectiveness of biomedical data elements within a study that incorporates their statistical relatedness to a given outcome variable as well as a measurement of the quality of their underlying data. Materials and methods: The cohort consisted of 874 patients with adenocarcinoma of the lung, each with 47 clinical data elements. The p value for each element was calculated using the Cox proportional hazard univariable regression model with overall survival as the endpoint. An attribute or A-score was calculated by quantification of an element's four quality attributes; Completeness, Comprehensiveness, Consistency and Overall-cost. An effectiveness or E-score was obtained by calculating the conditional probabilities of the p-value and A-score within the given data set with their product equaling the effectiveness score (E-score). Results: The E-score metric provided information about the utility of an element beyond an outcome-related p value ranking. E-scores for elements age-at-diagnosis, gender and tobacco-use showed utility above what their respective p values alone would indicate due to their relative ease of acquisition, that is, higher A-scores. Conversely, elements surgery-site, histologic-type and pathological-TNM stage were down-ranked in comparison to their p values based on lower A-scores caused by significantly higher acquisition costs. Conclusions: A novel metric termed E-score was developed which incorporates standard statistics with data quality metrics and was tested on elements from a large lung cohort. Results show that an element's underlying data quality is an important consideration in addition to p value correlation to outcome when determining the element's clinical or research utility in a study.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.54r13/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.52536","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.52536","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003220","PMID:23975264"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.54r13"}}