{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-14T17:24:04Z","author":["Hutchinson, John R.","Bates, Karl T.","Allen, Vivian","Li, Zhiheng"],"title":"Data from: Linking the evolution of body shape and locomotor biomechanics in bird-line archosaurs","host":"Allen V, Bates KT, Li Z, Hutchinson JR (2013) Linking the evolution of body shape and locomotor biomechanics in bird-line archosaurs. Nature 497(7447): 104–107.","keywords":["dinosaur","biomechanics","locomotion","evolution","palaeontology"],"description":"Locomotion in living birds (Neornithes) has two remarkable features: feather-assisted flight, and the use of unusually crouched hindlimbs for bipedal support and movement. When and how these defining functional traits evolved remains controversial. However, the advent of computer modelling approaches and the discoveries of exceptionally preserved key specimens now make it possible to use quantitative data on whole-body morphology to address the biomechanics underlying this issue. Here we use digital body reconstructions to quantify evolutionary trends in locomotor biomechanics (whole-body proportions and centre-of-mass position) across the clade Archosauria. We use three-dimensional digital reconstruction to estimate body shape from skeletal dimensions for 17 archosaurs along the ancestral bird line, including the exceptionally preserved, feathered taxa Microraptor, Archaeopteryx, Pengornis and Yixianornis, which represent key stages in the evolution of the avian body plan. Rather than a discrete transition from more-upright postures in the basal-most birds (Avialae) and their immediate outgroup deinonychosauria, our results support hypotheses of a gradual, stepwise acquisition of more-crouched limb postures across much of theropod evolution, although we find evidence of an accelerated change within the clade Maniraptora (birds and their closest relatives, such as deinonychosaurs). In addition, whereas reduction of the tail is widely accepted to be the primary morphological factor correlated with centre-of-mass position and, hence, evolution of hindlimb posture, we instead find that enlargement of the pectoral limb and several associated trends have a much stronger influence. Intriguingly, our support for the onset of accelerated morpho-functional trends within Maniraptora is closely correlated with the evolution of flight. Because we find that the evolution of enlarged forelimbs is strongly linked, via whole-body centre of mass, to hindlimb function during terrestrial locomotion, we suggest that the evolution of avian flight is linked to anatomical novelties in the pelvic limb as well as the pectoral.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.hh74n/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.hh74n/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.hh74n/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.hh74n/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.hh74n/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47161","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47161","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23615616","doi:10.1038/nature12059"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.hh74n"}}