{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-15T13:37:11Z","author":["Hahn, Thomas","Ghazoul, Jaboury","Hennig, Ernest I.","Pluess, Andrea R.","Kettle, Chris J."],"title":"Data from: Landscape composition has limited impact on local genetic structure in mountain clover, Trifolium montanum L.","host":"Hahn T, Kettle CJ, Ghazoul J, Hennig EI, Pluess AR (2013) Landscape composition has limited impact on local genetic structure in mountain clover, Trifolium montanum L. Journal of Heredity 104(6): 842-852.","keywords":["biodiversity","AFLP","fragmentation","gene flow","semi-dry grasslands","landscape genetics","Population structure and phylogeography","Conservation genetics"],"description":"Semi-dry grasslands in the European Alps have been increasingly fragmented over the last 150 years. Few studies have investigated the implications of landscape configuration for genetic structure and gene flow among remnant habitat patches. Conservation management of semi-dry grassland plants rarely accounts for possible effects of major landscape elements; such as forest patches, as barriers to gene flow and dispersal via seed and pollen, despite their potential importance for biodiversity conservation. Using 1,416 individuals from 61 sampling sites across two valleys in South-Eastern Switzerland and AFLP fingerprints we applied a spatial strip and a circle approach to determine the impact of different landscape elements on genetic differentiation in the semi-dry grassland herb Trifolium montanum (mountain clover). Overall genetic differentiation among sampling sites was low (overall FST = 0.044). Forest area had no effect on gene flow at the landscape scale but area of semi-dry grassland, the potential habitat of T. montanum, road area and altitude influenced genetic differentiation among sampling sites. The observed pattern of genetic differentiation suggests that a future increase in forest area, due to land use abandonment, at least in the short term, are unlikely to directly impact patterns of genetic variation in T. montanum.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.s0885/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.s0885/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53021","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53021","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24064981","doi:10.1093/jhered/est058"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s0885"}}