{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-12T17:50:45Z","author":["Messaoudi, Melina","Ebrahim, Naseem","Mueller, Beat","Giersdorf, Sven","Telles, Jean-Noel","Madhi, Shabir A.","Albrich, Werner C.","Adrian, Peter V.","Vernet, Guy","Klugman, Keith P.","Paranhos-Baccalà, Glaucia","van Niekerk, Nadia"],"title":"Data from: Pneumococcal colonisation density: a new marker for disease severity in HIV-infected adults with pneumonia","host":"Albrich WC, Madhi SA, Adrian PV, van Niekerk N, Telles J, Ebrahim N, Messaoudi M, Paranhos-Baccalà G, Giersdorf S, Vernet G, Mueller B, Klugman KP (2014) Pneumococcal colonisation density: a new marker for disease severity in HIV-infected adults with pneumonia. BMJ Open 4(8): e005953.","keywords":["Diagnostic microbiology","HIV & AIDS","Respiratory infections","biomarkers","Pneumococcal colonization density","prognosis"],"description":"Objective: A high genomic load of Pneumococcus from blood or cerebrospinal fluid has been associated with increased mortality. We aimed to analyse whether nasopharyngeal colonisation density in HIV-infected patients with community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) is associated with markers of disease severity or poor outcome. Methods: Quantitative lytA real-time PCR was performed on nasopharyngeal swabs in HIV-infected South African adults hospitalised for acute CAP at Chris Hani Baragwanath Hospital, Soweto, South Africa. Pneumonia aetiology was considered pneumococcal if any sputum culture or Gram stain, urinary pneumococcal C-polysaccharide-based antigen, blood culture or whole blood lytA real-time PCR revealed pneumococci. Results: There was a moderate correlation between the mean nasopharyngeal colonisation densities and increasing CURB65 scores among all-cause patients with pneumonia (Spearman correlation coefficient r=0.15, p=0.06) or with the Pitt bacteraemia score among patients with pneumococcal bacteraemia (p=0.63). In patients with pneumococcal pneumonia, nasopharyngeal pneumococcal colonisation density was higher among non-survivors than survivors (7.7 vs 6.1 log10 copies/mL, respectively, p=0.02) and among those who had pneumococci identified from blood cultures and/or by whole blood lytA real-time PCR than those with non-bacteraemic pneumococcal pneumonia (6.6 vs 5.6 log10 copies/mL, p=0.03). Nasopharyngeal colonisation density correlated positively with the biomarkers procalcitonin (Spearman correlation coefficient r=0.37, p<0.0001), proadrenomedullin (r=0.39, p=0.008) and copeptin (r=0.30, p=0.01). Conclusions: In addition to its previously reported role as a diagnostic tool for pneumococcal pneumonia, quantitative nasopharyngeal colonisation density also correlates with mortality and prognostic biomarkers. It may also be useful as a severity marker for pneumococcal pneumonia in HIV-infected adults.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rr42f/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68313","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68313","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25113557","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005953"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rr42f"}}