{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-17T14:54:43Z","author":["Beukeboom, Leo W.","de Haan, Ammerins","Pannebakker, Bart A.","Ferber, Steven","van de Zande, Louis","van Heerwaarden, Joost"],"title":"Data from: Development of a Nasonia vitripennis outbred laboratory population for genetic analysis","host":"van de Zande L, Ferber S, de Haan A, Beukeboom LW, van Heerwaarden J, Pannebakker BA (2013) Development of a Nasonia vitripennis outbred laboratory population for genetic analysis. Molecular Ecology Resources 14(3): 578–587.","keywords":["pooled resequencing","genetic variation","parasitoid wasp","laboratory strain","single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)","effective population size"],"description":"The parasitoid wasp genus Nasonia has rapidly become a genetic model system for developmental and evolutionary biology. The release of its genome sequence led to the development of high-resolution genomic tools, for both interspecific and intraspecific research, which has resulted in great advances in understanding Nasonia biology. To further advance the utility of Nasonia vitripennis as a genetic model system and to be able to fully exploit the advantages of its fully sequenced and annotated genome, we developed a genetically variable and well-characterized experimental population. In this study, we describe the establishment of the genetically diverse HVRx laboratory population from strains collected from the field in the Netherlands. We established a maintenance method that retains genetic variation over generations of culturing in the laboratory. As a characterization of its genetic composition, we provide data on the standing genetic variation and estimate the effective population size (Ne) by microsatellite analysis. A genome-wide description of polymorphism is provided through pooled resequencing, which yielded 417 331 high-quality SNPs spanning all five Nasonia chromosomes. The HVRx population and its characterization are freely available as a community resource for investigators seeking to elucidate the genetic basis of complex trait variation using the Nasonia model system.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.f2330/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.f2330/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.f2330/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.f2330/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.f2330/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55701","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55701","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/1755-0998.12201","PMID:24215457"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f2330"}}