{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-06T17:43:44Z","author":["Foitzik, Susanne","Job, Sylwester","Jongepier, Evelien","Kleeberg, Isabelle"],"title":"Data from: Collective defence portfolios of ant hosts shift with social parasite pressure","host":"Jongepier E, Kleeberg I, Job S, Foitzik S (2014) Collective defence portfolios of ant hosts shift with social parasite pressure. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1791): 20140225.","keywords":["brood parasites","host-parasite interactions","frontline defences","social insects","defence portfolios"],"description":"Host defences become increasingly costly as parasites breach successive lines of defence. Because selection favours hosts that successfully resist parasitism at the lowest possible cost, escalating coevolutionary arms races are likely to drive host defence portfolios towards ever more expensive strategies. We investigated the interplay between host defence portfolios and social parasite pressure by comparing 17 populations of two Temnothorax ant species. When successful, collective aggression not only prevents parasitation but also spares host colonies the cost of searching for and moving to a new nest site. However, once parasites breach the host's nest defence, host colonies should resort to flight as the more beneficial resistance strategy. We show that under low parasite pressure, host colonies more likely responded to an intruding Protomognathus americanus slavemaker with collective aggression, which prevented the slavemaker from escaping and potentially recruiting nest-mates. However, as parasite pressure increased, ant colonies of both host species became more likely to flee rather than to fight. We conclude that host defence portfolios shift consistently with social parasite pressure, which is in accordance with the degeneration of frontline defences and the evolution of subsequent anti-parasite strategies often invoked in hosts of brood parasites.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6st80/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.65360","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.65360","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.0225","PMID:25100690"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6st80"}}