{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-25T15:18:31Z","author":["McDermott, Shannon R.","Noor, Mohamed A. F."],"title":"Data from: Mapping of within-species segregation distortion in D. persimilis and hybrid sterility between D. persimilis and D. pseudoobscura","host":"McDermott SR, Noor MAF (2012) Mapping of within-species segregation distortion in D. persimilis and hybrid sterility between D. persimilis and D. pseudoobscura. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 25(10): 2023-2032.","keywords":["Speciation","Hybrid Incompatibility","Reproductive Isolation","Meiotic Drive"],"description":"In contrast to the prevailing dogma in the 1990s, recent studies have suggested that an evolutionary history of segregation distortion within species may contribute to sterility in species hybrids. However, this recent work identified segregation distortion exclusively in species hybrids which may never have had an evolutionary history of segregation distortion in either parent species. We expand on previous work by using a strain of Drosophila persimilis exhibiting segregation distortion within species to generate QTL maps for segregation distortion and hybrid sterility in crosses between D. persimilis and D. pseudoobscura. The maps localize regions along the XR contributing to both phenotypes, and they indicate one region of overlap between the two maps. This overlap could provide preliminary evidence for an association between segregation distortion within species and hybrid sterility, but the localizations are currently too broad to have confidence in this conclusion. This work is a first step towards possibly supporting a genetic conflict model of speciation in this system.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.c744j/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.c744j/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.c744j/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.c744j/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.c744j/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40610","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40610","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22966762","doi:10.1111/j.1420-9101.2012.02581.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.c744j"}}