{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-16T18:55:25Z","author":["Nistelberger, Heidi M.","Llorens, Tanya M.","Yates, Colin J.","Byrne, Margaret","Coates, David J."],"title":"Data from: Evaluating the influence of different aspects of habitat fragmentation on mating patterns and pollen dispersal in the bird-pollinated Banksia sphaerocarpa var. caesia","host":"Llorens TM, Byrne M, Yates CJ, Nistelberger HM, Coates DJ (2011) Evaluating the influence of different aspects of habitat fragmentation on mating patterns and pollen dispersal in the bird-pollinated Banksia sphaerocarpa var. caesia. Molecular Ecology 21(2): 314-328.","keywords":["mating system","fragmentation","pollen dispersal","population shape"],"description":"Habitat fragmentation can significantly affect mating and pollen dispersal patterns in plant populations, although the differential effects of the various aspects of fragmentation are poorly understood. In this study we used paternity assignment with eight microsatellite loci to investigate the effect of fragmentation on the mating system and pollen dispersal within one large and eight small population remnants of Banksia sphaerocarpa var. caesia, a bird-pollinated shrub in the southern agricultural region of Western Australia. The large population had a much larger neighbourhood size and lower selfing rate, maternal pollen pool differentiation and within-plot mean pollen dispersal distance than the small populations. Outcrossing was consistently high and ranged from 89% ± 0.8 to 98.5% ± 0.3, and mating patterns suggested nearest-neighbour pollination. Pollen immigration into small populations ranged from 6% ± 0.6 to 15% ± 0.6. Using the small populations, we tested for correlations between various fragmentation variables and mating system and pollen dispersal parameters. We found significant positive linear relationships between population size and number of different fathers per seed crop and between population shape and pollen pool differentiation. There were significant negative linear relationships between population isolation and outcrossing rate; population shape and neighbourhood size; and conspecific density and mean pollen dispersal distance. Our results suggest that birds may use a series of fragmented populations as a vegetation corridor while foraging across the landscape and that population connectivity is a critical determinant of pollinator visitation. Our results also suggest that the effect of a linear population shape on the mating system and pollen dispersal is routinely underestimated.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.pm251177/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.pm251177/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35521","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35521","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22151648","doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05396.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pm251177"}}