{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-14T16:57:06Z","author":["Logan, Corina J.","Ostojić, Ljerka","Clayton, Nicola S."],"title":"Data from: Rook, but not jackdaw, post-conflict third-party affiliation reduces aggression for aggressors","host":"Logan CJ, Ostojić L, Clayton NS (2013) Rook, but not jackdaw, post-conflict third-party affiliation reduces aggression for aggressors. Ethology 119(5): 427–435.","keywords":["Third-party affiliation","Corvid","Post-conflict affiliation","Reduces aggression"],"description":"Post-conflict (PC) affiliation refers to positive social interactions that occur after fights. Although this behavior has been widely studied, its functions are rarely tested. We examine a potential function of PC third-party affiliation (affiliation between former opponents and bystanders) in rooks and jackdaws by investigating the hypothesis that conflicts lead to further aggression and that PC third-party affiliation increases to reduce such aggression. The results show that PC affiliation reduces PC aggression for rook aggressors who were less likely to receive aggression after conflicts when they were affiliating with another vs. when they were alone. The opposite result was found for victims of both species who received more aggression after conflicts, and this aggression was not reduced by the act of affiliating. Finally, for jackdaw aggressors, the amount of aggression received after conflicts was not influenced by whether the individual was affiliating or alone, indicating that PC third-party affiliation may serve a function that we did not examine. These findings highlight the importance of investigating functional differences in PC affiliative behavior according to the role played in the conflict.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46516","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46516","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/eth.12078","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.r4jq1"}}