{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-03T06:30:03Z","author":["Mueller, Jakob C","Olano-Marin, Juanita","Kempenaers, Bart"],"title":"Data from: Correlations between heterozygosity and reproductive success in the blue tit (Cyanistes caeruleus): an analysis of inbreeding and single locus effects","host":"Olano-Marin J, Mueller JC, Kempenaers B (2011) Correlations between heterozygosity and reproductive success in the blue tit (Cyanistes caeruleus): an analysis of inbreeding and single locus effects. Evolution 65(11): 3175-3194.","keywords":["Population Genetics","Fitness","Genetic Variation","Inbreeding"],"description":"In order to understand the mechanisms behind heterozygosity-fitness correlations (HFC), it is necessary to employ large numbers of markers with known function and to independently estimate the variation in inbreeding in the population. Here we genotyped 794 blue tits with 79 microsatellites that were distributed across 25 chromosomes and that were classified either as \"functional\" (N = 58) or \"neutral\" (N = 21). We found a positive effect of individual heterozygosity at multiple loci on clutch size, on the number of eggs sired by males, and on the number of recruits produced by males and females. We documented the occurrence of some consanguineous matings and found evidence for a particular type of population structure that can contribute to the occurrence of inbreeding. As the set of \"neutral\" loci provided more power to detect HFC and identity disequilibrium, we argue that \"neutral\" markers are better predictors of the effects of inbreeding. The number of significant effects at single loci did not exceed the expected number of false positives and no strong effects were associated with heterozygosity at \"functional\" markers. Thus, the HFC found here cannot be attributed to strong effects of the loci under study.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.rk280/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.rk280/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.rk280/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.rk280/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.33775","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.33775","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22023584","doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2011.01369.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rk280"}}