{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-10-03T01:07:38Z","author":["Nystrand, Magdalena","Dowling, Damian K."],"title":"Data from: Transgenerational interactions involving parental age and immune status affect female reproductive success in Drosophila melanogaster","host":"Nystrand M, Dowling DK (2014) Transgenerational interactions involving parental age and immune status affect female reproductive success in Drosophila melanogaster. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1794): 20141242.","keywords":["immune elicitor","immune transfer","heat-killed bacteria","maternal effects","paternal effects","life-history"],"description":"It is well established that the parental phenotype can influence offspring phenotypic expression, independent of the effects of the offspring's own genotype. Nonetheless, the evolutionary implications of such parental effects remain unclear, partly because previous studies have generally overlooked the potential for interactions between parental sources of non-genetic variance to influence patterns of offspring phenotypic expression. We tested for such interactions, subjecting male and female Drosophila melanogaster of two different age classes to an immune activation challenge or a control treatment. Flies were then crossed in all age and immune status combinations, and the reproductive success of their immune- and control-treated daughters measured. We found that daughters produced by two younger parents exhibited reduced reproductive success relative to those of other parental age combinations. Furthermore, immune-challenged daughters exhibited higher reproductive success when produced by immune-challenged relative to control-treated mothers, a pattern consistent with transgenerational immune priming. Finally, a complex interplay between paternal age and parental immune statuses influenced daughter's reproductive success. These findings demonstrate the dynamic nature of age- and immune-mediated parental effects, traceable to both parents, and regulated by interactions between parents and between parents and offspring.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7cf02/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68904","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68904","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25253454","doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.1242"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7cf02"}}