{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-06T21:52:44Z","author":["Agren, Jon","Akiyama, Reiko"],"title":"Data from: Conflicting selection on the timing of germination in a natural population of Arabidopsis thaliana","host":"Akiyama R, Agren J (2013) Conflicting selection on the timing of germination in a natural population of Arabidopsis thaliana. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 27(1): 193–199.","keywords":["Trade-offs","Life history evolution","Plants","Ecological genetics","Natural selection"],"description":"The timing of germination is a key life-history trait that may strongly influence plant fitness and that sets the stage for selection on traits expressed later in the life cycle. In seasonal environments, the period favourable for germination and the total length of the growing season are limited. The optimal timing of germination may therefore be governed by conflicting selection through survival and fecundity. We conducted a field experiment to examine the effects of timing of germination on survival, fecundity and overall fitness in a natural population of the annual herb Arabidopsis thaliana in north-central Sweden. Seedlings were transplanted at three different times in late summer and in autumn covering the period of seed germination in the study population. Early germination was associated with low seedling survival, but also with high survival and fecundity among established plants. The advantages of germinating early more than balanced the disadvantage and selection favoured early germination. The results suggest that low survival among early germinating seeds is the main force opposing the evolution of earlier germination and that the optimal timing of germination should vary in space and time as a function of the direction and strength of selection acting during different life-history stages.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.82mf4/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56268","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56268","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/jeb.12293","PMID:24329869"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.82mf4"}}