{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-03-14T18:58:50Z","author":["Lutzoni, François","Gottel, Neil R.","Schadt, Christopher W.","Hodkinson, Brendan P."],"title":"Data from: Photoautotrophic symbiont and geography are major factors affecting highly structured and diverse bacterial communities in the lichen microbiome","host":"Hodkinson BP, Gottel NR, Schadt CW, Lutzoni F (2011) Photoautotrophic symbiont and geography are major factors affecting highly structured and diverse bacterial communities in the lichen microbiome. Environmental Microbiology 14(1): 147-161.","keywords":["Titanium series reagents","pyrosequencing","clone libraries","454 sequencing","lichens","16S rRNA gene","bacterial communities","microbial ecology"],"description":"Although common knowledge dictates that the lichen thallus is formed solely by a fungus (mycobiont) that develops a symbiotic relationship with an alga and/or cyanobacterium (photobiont), the non-photoautotrophic bacteria found in lichen microbiomes are increasingly regarded as integral components of lichen thalli. For this study, comparative analyses were conducted on lichen-associated bacterial communities to test for effects of photobiont-types (i.e., green algal vs. cyanobacterial), mycobiont-types, and large-scale spatial distances (from tropical to arctic latitudes). Amplicons of the 16S (SSU) rRNA gene were examined using both Sanger sequencing of cloned fragments and barcoded pyrosequencing. Rhizobiales is typically the most abundant and taxonomically diverse order in lichen microbiomes; however, overall bacterial diversity in lichens is shown to be much higher than previously reported. Members of Acidobacteriaceae, Acetobacteraceae, Brucellaceae, and sequence group LAR1 are the most commonly found groups across the phylogenetically and geographically broad array of lichens examined here. Major bacterial community trends are significantly correlated with differences in large-scale geography, photobiont-type, and mycobiont-type. The lichen as a microcosm represents a structured, unique microbial habitat with greater ecological complexity and bacterial diversity than previously appreciated and can serve as a model system for studying larger ecological and evolutionary principles.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.t99b1/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34223","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34223","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1462-2920.2011.02560.x","PMID:21906220"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.t99b1"}}