{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-23T16:45:50Z","author":["Núñez-Acuña, Gustavo","Chávez-Mardones, Jacqueline","Gallardo-Escárate, Cristian","Valenzuela-Muñoz, Valentina","Maldonado-Aguayo, Waleska"],"title":"Data from: Concholepas concholepas Ferritin H-like subunit (CcFer): molecular characterization and single nucleotide polymorphism associated to innate immune response","host":"Chávez-Mardones J,  Valenzuela-Muñoz V, Núñez-Acuña G, Maldonado-Aguayo W, Gallardo-Escárate C (2013) Concholepas concholepas Ferritin H-like subunit (CcFer): molecular characterization and single nucleotide polymorphism associated to innate immune response. Fish & Shellfish Immunology 35(3): 910–917.","keywords":["Ferritine-like","SNP"],"description":"Ferritin has been shown as the principal protein of iron storage and iron detoxification, playing a pivotal role for the cellular homeostasis in living organisms. However, recent studies in marine invertebrates have suggested its association with innate immune system. In the present study, one Ferritin subunit was identified from the gastropod Concholepas concholepas (CcFer), which was fully characterized by Rapid Amplification of cDNA Ends technique. Simultaneously, a challenge test was performed to evaluate the immune response against Vibrio anguillarum. The full length of cDNA Ccfer was 1,030 bp, containing 513 bp of open reading frame that encodes 170 amino acid peptides, which was similar to the Ferritin-H subunit described in vertebrates. Untranslated Regions (UTRs) were identified with a 5'UTR of 244 bp that contains iron responsive element (IRE), and a 3'UTR of 273 pb. The predicted molecular mass of deduced amino acid of CcFer was 19.66 kDa and isoelectric point of 4.92. Gene transcription analysis revealed that CcFer increases against infections with V. anguillarum, showing a peak expression at 6 hours post-infection. Moreover, a single nucleotide polymorphism was detected at -64 downstream 5'UTR sequence (SNP-64). Quantitative real time analysis showed that homozygous mutant allele (TT) was significantly associated with higher expression levels of the challenged group compared to wild (CC) and heterozygous (CT) variants. Our findings suggest that CcFer is associated to innate immune response in C. concholepas and that the presence of SNPs may involve differential transcriptional expression of CcFer.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mf00q/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49679","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49679","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23838046","doi:10.1016/j.fsi.2013.06.028"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mf00q"}}