{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-24T20:18:03Z","author":["Rouger, Romuald","Jump, Alistair S."],"title":"Data from: A seascape genetic analysis reveals strong biogeographical structuring driven by contrasting processes in the polyploid saltmarsh species Puccinellia maritima and Triglochin maritima.","host":"Rouger R, Jump AS (2014) A seascape genetic analysis reveals strong biogeographical structuring driven by contrasting processes in the polyploid saltmarsh species Puccinellia maritima and Triglochin maritima. Molecular Ecology 23(13): 3158–3170.","keywords":["Polyploidy","Isolation by resistance","Saltmarsh","DAPC"],"description":"Little is known about the processes shaping population structure in saltmarshes. It is expected that the sea should act as a powerful agent of dispersal. Yet, in contrast, import of external propagules into a saltmarsh is thought to be small. To determine the level of connectivity between saltmarsh ecosystems at a macro-geographical scale, we characterised and compared the population structure of two polyploid saltmarsh species, Puccinellia maritima and Triglochin maritima based on a seascape genetics approach. A discriminant analysis of principal components highlighted a genetic structure for both species arranged according to a regional pattern. Subsequent analysis based on isolation by distance and isolation by resistance frameworks indicated a strong role of coastal sediment transport processes in delimiting regional structure in P. maritima while additional overland propagule dispersal was indicated for T. maritima. The identification and comparison of regional genetic structure and likely determining factors presented here allows us to understand the biogeographical units along the UK coast, between which barriers to connectivity occur not only at the species level but at the ecosystem scale. This information is valuable in plant conservation and community ecology and in the management and restoration of saltmarsh ecosystems.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/23","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/24","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/21","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/22","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/20","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n/11"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64282","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64282","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24862943","doi:10.1111/mec.12802"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.dc56n"}}