{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-03-19T20:52:04Z","author":["Dean, Sarah L.","Farrer, Emily C.","Taylor, D. Lee","Sinsabaugh, Robert L.","Porras-Alfaro, Andrea","Suding, Katharine N."],"title":"Data from: Nitrogen deposition alters plant–fungal relationships: linking belowground dynamics to aboveground vegetation change","host":"Dean SL, Farrer EC, Taylor DL, Porras-Alfaro A, Suding KN, Sinsabaugh RL (2013) Nitrogen deposition alters plant–fungal relationships: linking belowground dynamics to aboveground vegetation change. Molecular Ecology 23(6): 1364–1378.","keywords":["root fungi","Helotiales","nitrogen deposition","ITS","454 pyrosequencing"],"description":"Nitrogen (N) deposition rates are increasing globally due to anthropogenic activities. Plant community responses to N are often attributed to altered competitive interactions between plants, but may also be a result of microbial responses to N, particularly root-associated fungi (RAF), which are known to affect plant fitness. In response to N, Deschampsia cespitosa, a codominant plant in the alpine tundra at Niwot Ridge (CO), increases in abundance, while Geum rossii, its principal competitor, declines. Importantly, G. rossii declines with N even in the absence of its competitor. We examined whether contrasting host responses to N are associated with altered plant–fungal symbioses, and whether the effects of N are distinct from effects of altered plant competition on RAF, using 454 pyrosequencing. Host RAF communities were distinct (only 9.4% of OTUs overlapped). N increased RAF diversity in G. rossii, but decreased it in D. cespitosa. D. cespitosa RAF communities were more responsive to N than G. rossii RAF communities, perhaps indicating a flexible microbial community aids host adaptation to nutrient enrichment. Effects of removing D. cespitosa were distinct from effects of N on G. rossii RAF, and D. cespitosa presence reversed RAF diversity response to N. The most dominant G. rossii RAF order, Helotiales, was the most affected by N, declining from 83% to 60% of sequences, perhaps indicating a loss of mutualists under N enrichment. These results highlight the potential importance of belowground microbial dynamics in plant responses to N deposition.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/41","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/40","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/42","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/43","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/29","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/28","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/23","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/22","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/21","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/20","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/30","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/27","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/26","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/25","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/24","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/33","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/34","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/31","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/32","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/37","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/38","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/35","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/36","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f/39"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.52417","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.52417","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24112704","doi:10.1111/mec.12541"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sv33f"}}