{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-04-09T18:54:12Z","author":["Whiting, Martin J.","Carazo, Pau","Noble, Daniel W. A."],"title":"Data from: Learning outdoors: Male lizards show flexible spatial learning under semi-natural conditions","host":"Noble DWA, Carazo P, Whiting MJ (2012) Learning outdoors: Male lizards show flexible spatial learning under semi-natural conditions. Biology Letters 8(6): 946-948.","keywords":["reptile","cognition","spatial learning","associative learning"],"description":"Spatial cognition is predicted to be a fundamental component of fitness in many lizard species, and yet some studies suggest that it is relatively slow and inflexible. However, such claims are based on work conducted using experimental designs or in artificial contexts that may underestimate their cognitive abilities. We used a biologically realistic experimental procedure (using simulated predatory attacks) to study spatial learning and its flexibility in the lizard Eulamprus quoyii in semi-natural outdoor enclosures under similar conditions to those experienced by lizards in the wild. To evaluate the flexibility of spatial learning, we conducted a reversal spatial-learning task in which positive and negative reinforcements of learnt spatial stimuli were switched. Nineteen (32%) male lizards learnt both tasks within 10 days (spatial task mean: 8.16 ± 0.69 (s.e.) and reversal spatial task mean: 10.74 ± 0.98 (s.e.) trials). We demonstrate that E. quoyii are capable of flexible spatial learning and suggest that future studies focus on a range of lizard species which differ in phylogeny and/or ecology, using biologically relevant cognitive tasks, in an effort to bridge the cognitive divide between ecto- and endotherms.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n5b32/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42675","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42675","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23075525","doi:10.1098/rsbl.2012.0813"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n5b32"}}