{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"The American Naturalist","keywords":["clade diversification","speciation","macroevolution","extinction","phylogenetic rates"],"host":"McPeek, M. A. 2008. The ecological dynamics of clade diversification and community assembly. American Naturalist 172:E270-E284.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.355/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.355","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T20:29:29Z","author":"McPeek, Mark A.","title":"Data from: The ecological dynamics of clade diversification and community assembly","description":"Clades diversify in an ecological context, but most macroevolutionary\nmodels do not directly encapsulate ecological mechanisms that influence speciation and extinction. A data set of 245 chordate, arthropod, mollusk, and magnoliophyte phylogenies had\na majority of clades that showed rapid lineage accumulation early\nwith a slowing more recently, whereas a small but significantminority\nshowed accelerated lineage accumulation in their recent histories.\nPrevious analyses have demonstrated that macroevolutionary birthdeath\nmodels can replicate the pattern of slowing lineage accumulation\nonly by a strong decrease in speciation rate with increasing\nspecies richness and extinction rate held extremely low or absent. In\ncontrast, the metacommunity model presented here could generate\nthe full range of patterns seen in the real phylogenies by simply\nmanipulating the degree of ecological differentiation of new species\nat the time of speciation. Specifically, the metacommunity model\npredicts that clades showing decelerating lineage accumulation rates are those that have diversified by ecological modes of speciation, whereas clades showing accelerating lineage accumulation rates are those that have diversified primarily by modes of speciation that generate little or no ecological diversification. A number of testable predictions that integrate data from molecular systematics, community ecology, and biogeography are also discussed.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.355","isReferencedBy":["PMID:18851684","doi:10.1086/593137"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.355"}}