{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-03T16:03:29Z","author":["Mazé-Guilmo, Elise","Lefèvre, Thierry","Blanchet, Simon","Loot, Géraldine","Páez, David James"],"title":"Data from: Heritable variation in host tolerance and resistance inferred from a wild host– parasite system","host":"Mazé-Guilmo E, Loot G, Páez DJ, Lefèvre T, Blanchet S (2014) Heritable variation in host tolerance and resistance inferred from a wild host– parasite system. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1779): 20132567.","keywords":["host–parasite interaction","quantitative genetics","genetic correlation","long-term survey","molecular-based pedigree"],"description":"Hosts have evolved two distinct defence strategies against parasites: resistance (which prevents infection or limit parasite growth) and tolerance (which alleviates the fitness consequences of infection). However, heritable variation in resistance and tolerance and the genetic correlation between these two traits have rarely been characterized in wild host populations. Here, we estimate these parameters for both traits in Leuciscus burdigalensis, a freshwater fish parasitized by Tracheliastes polycolpus. We used a genetic database to construct a full-sib pedigree in a wild L. burdigalensis population. We then used univariate animal models to estimate inclusive heritability (i.e. all forms of genetic and non-genetic inheritance) in resistance and tolerance. Finally, we assessed the genetic correlation between these two traits using a bivariate animal model. We found significant heritability for resistance (H = 17.6%; 95% CI: 7.2–32.2%) and tolerance (H = 18.8%; 95% CI: 4.4–36.1%), whereas we found no evidence for the existence of a genetic correlation between these traits. Furthermore, we confirm that resistance and tolerance are strongly affected by environmental effects. Our results demonstrate that (i) heritable variation exists for parasite resistance and tolerance in wild host populations, and (ii) these traits can evolve independently in populations.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.s3k34/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.s3k34/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.58622","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.58622","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24478295","doi:10.1098/rspb.2013.2567"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s3k34"}}