{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"41;8;2011","keywords":["nematode","expressed sequence tag","PartiGene","transcriptome","genome","database"],"host":"Elsworth B, Wasmuth J, Blaxter M (2011) NEMBASE4: the nematode transcriptome resource. International Journal for Parasitology 41(8): 881-894.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b22430s2/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35766","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-10-31T18:33:54Z","author":["Elsworth, Benjamin","Wasmuth, James","Blaxter, Mark L"],"title":"Data from: NEMBASE4: the nematode transcriptome resource","description":"Nematode parasites are of major importance in human health and agriculture, and free-living species deliver essential ecosystem services. The genomics revolution has resulted in the production of many datasets of expressed sequence tags (ESTs) from a phylogenetically wide range of nematode species, but these are not easily compared. NEMBASE4 presents a single portal onto extensively functionally annotated, EST-derived transcriptomes from over sixty species of nematodes, including plant and animal parasites and free-living taxa. Using the PartiGene suite of tools, we have assembled the ESTs publicly available for each species into a high-quality set of putative transcripts. These transcripts have been translated to produce a protein sequence resource, and each annotated with functional information derived from comparison to well-studied nematode species such as Caenorhabditis elegans and also other non-nematode resources. By cross-comparing the sequences within NEMBASE4, we have also generated a protein family assignment for each translation. The data are presented in an openly-accessible, interactive database. To demonstrate the utility of NEMBASE4, we have used the database to examine the uniqueness of the transcriptomes of major clades of parasitic nematodes, identifying lineage-restricted genes that may underpin particular parasitic phenotypes, possible viral pathogens of nematodes, and nematode-unique protein families that may be developed as drug targets.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35766","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21550347","doi:10.1016/j.ijpara.2011.03.009"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b22430s2"}}