{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-20T17:27:30Z","author":["Tam, Sheh May","Olsen, Kenneth M.","Song, Beng-Kah","Chuah, Tse-Seng"],"title":"Data from: Malaysian weedy rice shows its true stripes: wild Oryza and elite rice cultivars shape agricultural weed evolution in Southeast Asia","host":"Song B, Chuah T, Tam SM, Olsen KM (2014) Malaysian weedy rice shows its true stripes: wild Oryza and elite rice cultivars shape agricultural weed evolution in Southeast Asia. Molecular Ecology, online in advance of print.","keywords":["wild crop relatives","agricultural weeds","genetic introgression","hull color","shattering","red rice"],"description":"Weedy rice is a close relative of domesticated rice (Oryza sativa) that competes aggressively with the crop and limits rice productivity worldwide. Most genetic studies of weedy rice have focused on populations in regions where no reproductively compatible wild Oryza species occur (North America, Europe, northern Asia). Here we examined the population genetics of weedy rice in Malaysia, where wild rice (O. rufipogon) can be found growing in close proximity to cultivated and weedy rice. Using 375 accessions and a combined analysis of 24 neutral SSR loci and two rice domestication genes (sh4, controlling seed shattering, and Bh4, controlling hull color), we addressed the following questions: 1) What is the relationship of Malaysian weedy rice to domesticated and wild rice, and to weedy rice strains in the US? 2) To what extent does the presence of O. rufipogon influence the genetic and phenotypic diversity of Malaysian weeds? 3) What do the distributions of sh4 and Bh4 alleles and associated phenotypes reveal about the origin and contemporary evolution of Malaysian weedy rice? Our results reveal: independent evolutionary origins for Malaysian weeds and US strains, despite their very close phenotypic resemblance; wild-to-weed gene flow in Malaysian weed populations, including apparent adaptive introgression of seed-shattering alleles; and a prominent role for modern Malaysian cultivars in the origin and recent proliferation of Malaysian weeds. These findings suggest that the genetic complexity and adaptability of weedy crop relatives can be profoundly influenced by proximity to reproductively compatible wild and domesticated populations.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.1m9q8/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.1m9q8/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.1m9q8/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.69960","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.69960","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25231087","doi:10.1111/mec.12922"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1m9q8"}}