{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-10-08T19:50:51Z","author":["Becker, C. Guilherme","Corrêa, Décio T.","Toledo, Luís Felipe","Rodriguez, David","Longo, Ana V.","Zamudio, Kelly R.","Leite, Domingos S.","Haddad, Célio F. B.","Lambertini, Carolina"],"title":"Data from: Partitioning the net effect of host diversity on an emerging amphibian pathogen","host":"Becker CG, Rodriguez D, Toledo LF, Longo AV, Lambertini C, Corrêa DT, Leite DS, Haddad CFB, Zamudio KR (2014) Partitioning the net effect of host diversity on an emerging amphibian pathogen. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1795): 20141796.","keywords":["biodiversity","diversity-disease relationship","dilution effect"],"description":"The ‘dilution effect’ (DE) hypothesis predicts that diverse host communities will show reduced disease. The underlying causes of pathogen dilution are complex, because they involve non-additive (driven by host interactions and differential habitat use) and additive (controlled by host species composition) mechanisms. Here, we used measures of complementarity and selection traditionally employed in the field of biodiversity–ecosystem function (BEF) to quantify the net effect of host diversity on disease dynamics of the amphibian-killing fungus Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis (Bd). Complementarity occurs when average infection load in diverse host assemblages departs from that of each component species in uniform populations. Selection measures the disproportionate impact of a particular species in diverse assemblages compared with its performance in uniform populations, and therefore has strong additive and non-additive properties. We experimentally infected tropical amphibian species of varying life histories, in single- and multi-host treatments, and measured individual Bd infection loads. Host diversity reduced Bd infection in amphibians through a mechanism analogous to complementarity (sensu BEF), potentially by reducing shared habitat use and transmission among hosts. Additionally, the selection component indicated that one particular terrestrial species showed reduced infection loads in diverse assemblages at the expense of neighbouring aquatic hosts becoming heavily infected. By partitioning components of diversity, our findings underscore the importance of additive and non-additive mechanisms underlying the DE.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s4h7h/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.69817","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.69817","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.1796","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s4h7h"}}