{"properties":{"genre":"Book","timestamp":"2013-06-18T16:32:04Z","author":"Fairbairn, Daphne J.","title":"Data from: Odd couples: extraordinary differences between the sexes in the animal kingdom.","host":"Fairbairn DJ (2013) Odd couples: extraordinary differences between the sexes in the animal kingdom. Princeton: Princeton University Press.","keywords":["vertebrates","sex","sexual selection","life history","sexual dimorphism","body size","dioecy","reproduction","invertebrates","adaptation"],"description":"Introducing readers to important discoveries in animal behavior and evolution, Odd Couples explores some of the most extraordinary sexual differences in the animal world and shows how all can be understood through the common conceptual framework of evolutionary biology. The book uncovers the unique and bizarre characteristics—in size, behavior, ecology, and life history—that exist in these remarkable species and the special strategies they use to maximize reproductive success. Eight chapters highlight individual species with exceptional sexual dimorphisms, including elephant seals (Mirounga sp.), great bustards (Otis tarda), shell-carrying cichlids (Lamprologus callipterus), deep-sea anglerfishes (Ceratias holboelli), garden spiders (Argiope aurantia), bone-eating worms (Osedax sp.), blanket octopuses (Tremoctopus sp.) and burrowing barnacles (Trypetesa lampas). In addition, two synthesis chapters use data from all known animal phyla and classes to discern overall trends and patterns of sexual differences, providing the first broad-scale, quantitative analysis of sexual dimorphisms across the entire Animal Kingdom.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.n48cm/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.n48cm/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.n48cm/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.n48cm/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42982","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42982","isReferencedBy":"http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/820118780","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n48cm"}}