{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-20T14:42:12Z","author":["Gómez, José María","Perfectti, Francisco","Muñoz-Pajares, Antonio Jesús","Abdelaziz Mohamed, Mohamed","Berbel, Modesto"],"title":"Data from: Association between inbreeding depression and floral traits in a generalist-pollinated plant","keywords":["heterozygosity","geitonogamy","biparental inbreeding","microsatellite markers","self-pollination","corolla diameter","purging","outcrossing"],"description":"Individual variation in the magnitude of inbreeding depression (ID) in plants and its association with phenotypic traits may have important consequences for mating system evolution. This association has been investigated only scarcely, and always considering traits functionally related to autogamy. Here we explore the association between individual variation in ID and plant traits associated to pollinator attractiveness (related to plant size, corolla size and corolla shape) in two populations of Erysimum mediohispanicum (Brassicaceae). ID was calculated along the entire life cycle of the plant. In addition, we also explored the relationship between phenotypic traits and the individual levels of heterozygosity. We found significant associations between ID and corolla diameter and stalk height, being taller plants with larger corollas those undergoing a lower intensity of ID. Furthermore, we found a negative relationship between corolla diameter and heterozygosity, suggesting that plants with large flowers have purged their genetic load. Finally, we found a significant effect of corolla diameter on the intra-population genetic structure. All these findings suggest that plants with large flowers have secularly suffered frequent inbreeding in the study populations. Because corolla diameter is a trait frequently selected by pollinators in E. mediohispanicum, we believe that the observed relationship between this trait and ID could be mediated by pollinators, probably throughout an increasing in biparental inbreeding, geitonogamy or autogamy.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.p1s20/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.p1s20/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.71144","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.71144","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.p1s20"}}