{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-01T19:47:24Z","author":["Boshoff, Helena I.","Chakraborty, Sumit","Rhee, Kyu Y.","Barry III, Clifton E.","Gruber, Todd"],"title":"Data from: Para-aminosalicylic acid acts as an alternative substrate of folate metabolism in Mycobacterium tuberculosis","host":"Chakraborty S, Gruber T, Barry III CE, Boshoff HI, Rhee KY (2012) Para-aminosalicylic acid acts as an alternative substrate of folate metabolism in Mycobacterium tuberculosis. Science 339(6115): 88-91.","description":"Folate biosynthesis is an established anti-infective target, and the antifolate para-aminosalicylic acid (PAS) was one of the first anti-infectives introduced into clinical practice on the basis of target-based drug discovery. Fifty years later, PAS continues to be used to treat tuberculosis. PAS is assumed to inhibit dihydropteroate synthase (DHPS) in Mycobacterium tuberculosis by mimicking the substrate p-aminobenzoate (PABA). However, we found that sulfonamide inhibitors of DHPS inhibited growth of M. tuberculosis only weakly because of their intracellular metabolism. In contrast, PAS served as a replacement substrate for DHPS. Products of PAS metabolism at this and subsequent steps in folate metabolism inhibited those enzymes, competing with their substrates. PAS is thus a prodrug that blocks growth of M. tuberculosis when its active forms are generated by enzymes in the pathway they poison.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.43496","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.43496","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23118010","doi:10.1126/science.1228980"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.vh36n"}}