{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-12-10T17:01:06Z","author":["Keriö, Susanna","Kovalchuk, Andriy","Chen, Hongxin","Asiegbu, Fred O."],"title":"Data from: Distribution and bioinformatic analysis of the cerato-platanin protein family in Dikarya","host":"Chen H, Kovalchuk A, Keriö S, Asiegbu FO (2013) Distribution and bioinformatic analysis of the cerato-platanin protein family in Dikarya. Mycologia 105(6): 1479-1488.","keywords":["cerato-platanin","phylogenetic analysis"],"description":"The cerato-platanin family is a group of small cysteine-rich fungal proteins new to science. They usually are abundantly secreted extracellularly and are involved in fungus-host interactions. With the advance of available fungal genome sequences, we performed a genomewide study of the distribution of this family in fungi and analyzed the common characteristics of the protein sequences. A total of 55 fungal genomes, including 27 from Ascomycota and 28 from Basidiomycota, were used. A total of 130 cerato-platanin homolog protein sequences were obtained and analyzed. Our results showed that cerato-platanin homologs existed in both Ascomycota and Basidiomycota but were lost in early branches of jelly fungi as well as in some groups with yeast or yeast-like forms in their life cycle. Homolog numbers varied considerably between Ascomycota and Basidiomycota. Phylogenetic analysis suggested that the ancestor of the Dikarya possessed multiple copies of cerato-platanins, which sorted differently in Ascomycota and Basidiomycota, and that this gene family might have expanded in the Basidiomycota. Almost all homologs contained signal peptide sequences, and the length of mature proteins were mainly 105-134 amino acids. Four cysteines involved in forming two disulfide bridges and signature sequences (CSD or CSN) were highly conserved in most homologs. These results indicated a higher diversity of the cerato-platanin family in Basidiomycota than Ascomycota.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.g12k7/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.g12k7/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.g12k7/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.g12k7/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.g12k7/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.g12k7/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49668","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49668","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.3852/13-115","PMID:23928425"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g12k7"}}