{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-14T16:38:57Z","author":["Templin, William D.","Seeb, James E.","Ackerman, Michael W.","Seeb, Lisa W."],"title":"Data from: Landscape heterogeneity and local adaptation define the spatial genetic structure of Pacific salmon in a pristine environment","host":"Ackerman MW, Templin WD, Seeb JE, Seeb LW (2012) Landscape heterogeneity and local adaptation define the spatial genetic structure of Pacific salmon in a pristine environment. Conservation Genetics 14(2): 483-498.","keywords":["demography","SNPs","landscape genetics","sockeye salmon","adaptation"],"description":"Identifying the spatial distribution of genetic variation across the landscape is an essential step in informing species conservation. Comparison of closely related and geographically overlapping species can be particularly useful in cases where landscape may similarly influence genetic structure. Congruent patterns among species highlight the importance that landscape heterogeneity plays in determining genetic structure whereas contrasting patterns emphasize differences in species-specific ecology and life-history or the importance of species-specific adaptation to local environments. We examined the interacting roles of demography and adaptation in determining spatial genetic structure in two closely related and geographically overlapping species in a pristine environment. Using single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) loci exhibiting both neutral and putative adaptive variation, we evaluated the genetic structure of sockeye salmon in the Copper River, Alaska; these data were compared to existing data for Chinook salmon from the same region. Overall, both species exhibited patterns of isolation by distance; the spatial distribution of populations largely determined the distribution of genetic variation across the landscape. Further, both species exhibited largely congruent patterns of within- and among-population genetic diversity, highlighting the role that landscape heterogeneity and historical processes play in determining spatial genetic structure. Potential adaptive differences among geographically proximate sockeye salmon populations were observed when high FST outlier SNPs were evaluated in a landscape genetics context. Results were evaluated in the context of conservation efforts with an emphasis on reproductive isolation, historical processes, and local adaptation.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ng93k/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42393","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42393","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1007/s10592-012-0401-7","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ng93k"}}