{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-11-18T19:51:04Z","author":"Oaks, Jamie R","title":"Data from: A time-calibrated species tree of Crocodylia reveals a recent radiation of the true crocodiles","host":"Oaks JR (2011) A time-calibrated species tree of Crocodylia reveals a recent radiation of the true crocodiles. Evolution 65(11): 3285-3297.","keywords":["Biogeography","species tree","multi-species coalescent","Phylogenetics"],"description":"True crocodiles (Crocodylus) are the most broadly distributed, ecologically diverse, and species-rich crocodylian genus, comprising about half of extant crocodylian diversity and exhibiting a circumtropical distribution. Crocodylus traditionally has been viewed as an ancient group of morphologically conserved species that originated in Africa prior to continental breakup. In this study, these long-held notions about the temporal and geographic origin of Crocodylus are tested using DNA sequence data of 10 loci from 76 individuals representing all 23 crocodylian species. I infer a time-calibrated species tree of all Crocodylia and estimate the spatial pattern of diversification within Crocodylus. For the first time, a fully resolved phylogenetic estimate of all Crocodylia is well-supported. The results overturn traditional views of the evolution of Crocodylus by demonstrating that the true crocodiles are not \"living-fossils\" that originated in Africa. Rather, Crocodylus originated from an ancestor in the tropics of the Late Miocene Indo-Pacific, and rapidly radiated and dispersed around the globe during a period marked by mass extinctions of fellow crocodylians. The findings also reveal more diversity within the genus than is recognized by current taxonomy.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5k9s0/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.33833","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.33833","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2011.01373.x","PMID:22023592"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5k9s0"}}