{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-11T16:36:29Z","author":["Igić, Boris","Raduski, Andrew R.","Haney, Elizabeth B."],"title":"Data from: The expression of self-incompatibility in angiosperms is bimodal","host":"Raduski AR, Haney EB, Igić B (2011)  The expression of self-incompatibility in angiosperms is bimodal. Evolution 66(4): 1275-1283.","keywords":["breeding systems","levels of selection","mating systems","self-compatibility","outcrossing rate"],"description":"Self-incompatibility is expressed by nearly one half of all angiosperms. A large proportion of the remaining species are self-compatible, and they either outcross using various contrivances or self-fertilize to some extent. Because of the common occurrence of populations and individuals with intermediate levels of self-incompatibility, categorization of the expression of self-incompatibility as an approximately binary trait has become controversial. We collect a widely reported index (ISI) used to asses the strength and variation of self-incompatibility from over 1200 angiosperm taxa. Its distribution is bimodal and positively associated with outcrossing rate, albeit with a weak relationship within self-compatible taxa. A substantial fraction of species have intermediate mean values of ISI. Their occurrence can be caused by segregating ephemeral self-compatible mutations, averaging artifacts, and experimental biases, in addition to the often invoked stabilizing selection acting on the expression of self-incompatibility. Selection may also generally favor taxa with high ISI values through increased lineage birth and death rates, and it may counter lower-level selection advantages within taxa expressing intermediate and low values of ISI. Such a null hypothesis is nearly universally overlooked, despite the fact that it could adequately explain the observed distribution of mating and breeding systems.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qt3m8jv7/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35637","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35637","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2011.01505.x","PMID:22486704"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qt3m8jv7"}}