{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-10-03T19:05:09Z","author":["Gowachirapant, Sueppong","Gray, Andrew R.","Houghton, Lisa A.","Harper, Michelle J.","Pongcharoen, Tippawan","Gibson, Rosalind S.","Winichagoon, Pattanee"],"title":"Data from: Vitamin D status among Thai school children and the association with 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D and parathyroid hormone levels","host":"Houghton LA, Gray AR, Harper MJ, Winichagoon P, Pongcharoen T, Gowachirapant S, Gibson RS (2014) Vitamin D status among Thai school children and the association with 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D and parathyroid hormone levels. PLoS ONE 9(8): e104825.","keywords":["children","vitamin D"],"description":"In several low latitude countries, vitamin D deficiency is emerging as a public health issue. Adequate vitamin D is essential for bone health in rapidly growing children. In the Thai population, little is known about serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D [25(OH)D] status of infants and children. Moreover, the association between 25(OH)D and the biological active form of 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D [1,25(OH)]2D is not clear. The specific aims of this study were to characterize circulating serum 25(OH)D, 1,25(OH)2D and their determinants including parathyroid hormone (PTH), age, sex, height and body mass index (BMI) in 529 school-aged Thai children aged 6–14 y. Adjusted linear regression analysis was performed to examine the impact of age and BMI, and its interaction with sex, on serum 25(OH)D concentrations and 1,25(OH)2D concentrations. Serum 25(OH)D, 1,25(OH)2D and PTH concentrations (geometric mean ± geometric SD) were 72.7±1.2 nmol/L, 199.1±1.3 pmol/L and 35.0±1.5 ng/L, respectively. Only 4% (21 of 529) participants had a serum 25(OH)D level below 50 nmol/L. There was statistically significant evidence for an interaction between sex and age with regard to 25(OH)D concentrations. Specifically, 25(OH)D concentrations were 19% higher in males. Moreover, females experienced a statistically significant 4% decline in serum 25(OH)D levels for each increasing year of age (P = 0.001); no decline was seen in male participants with increasing age (P = 0.93). When BMI, age, sex, height and serum 25(OH)D were individually regressed on 1,25(OH)2D, height and sex were associated with 1,25(OH)2D with females exhibiting statistically significantly higher serum 1,25(OH)2D levels compared with males (P<0.001). Serum 1,25(OH)2D among our sample of children exhibiting fairly sufficient vitamin D status were higher than previous reports suggesting an adaptive mechanism to maximize calcium absorption.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7763s/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67489","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67489","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0104825","PMID:25111832"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7763s"}}