{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-03-19T20:39:02Z","author":["Streiff, Réjane","Bourguet, Denis","Meusnier, Serge","Courtois, Brigitte"],"title":"Data from: Genetic mapping of two components of reproductive isolation between two sibling species of moths, Ostrinia nubilalis and O. scapulalis","host":"Streiff R, Courtois B, Meusnier S, Bourguet D (2013) Genetic mapping of two components of reproductive isolation between two sibling species of moths, Ostrinia nubilalis and O. scapulalis. Heredity 112(4): 370-381.","description":"We report the quantitative trait loci (QTL) mapping of reproductive isolation traits between Ostrinia nubilalis (the European corn borer) and its sibling species O. scapulalis (the Adzuki bean borer), focusing on two traits: mating isolation (mi) and pheromone production (Pher). Four genetic maps were generated from two backcross families, with two maps (one chromosomal map and one linkage map) per backcross. We located 165–323 AFLP markers on these four maps, resulting in the identification of 27–31 linkage groups, depending on the map considered. No-choice mating experiments with the offspring of each backcross led to the detection of at least two QTLs for mi in different linkage groups. QTLs underlying Pher were located in a third linkage group. The Z heterochromosome was identified by a specific marker (Tpi) and did not carry any of these QTLs. Finally, we considered the global divergence between the two sibling species, distortions of segregation throughout the genome, and the location and effect of mi and Pher QTLs in light of the known candidate genes for reproductive isolation within the genus Ostrinia and, more broadly, in phytophagous insects.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qr3t2/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54989","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54989","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24220089","doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.113"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qr3t2"}}