{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-19T19:39:38Z","author":["König, Barbara","Lindholm, Anna K.","Manser, Andri","Bagheri, Homayoun C."],"title":"Data from: Polyandry and the decrease of a selfish genetic element in a wild house mouse population","host":"Manser A, Lindholm AK, König B, Bagheri HC (2011) Polyandry and the decrease of a selfish genetic element in a wild house mouse population. Evolution 65(9): 2435-2447.","keywords":["t frequency paradox","generation time","intragenomic conflict","overdominance","t haplotype"],"description":"Despite deleterious effects on individuals, the t haplotype is a selfish genetic element present in many house mouse populations. By distorting the transmission ratio, +/t males transmit the t haplotype to up to 90% of their offspring. However, t/t individuals perish in utero. Theoretical models based on these properties predict a much higher t frequency than observed, leading to the t paradox. Here, we use empirical field data and theoretical approaches to investigate whether polyandry is a female counterstrategy against the negative fitness consequences of such distorters. We found a significant decrease of the t frequency over a period of 5.5 years that cannot be explained by the effect of transmission ratio distortion and recessive lethals, despite significantly higher life expectancy of +/t females compared to +/+ females. We quantified life history data and homozygous and heterozygous fitness effects. Population subdivision and inbreeding were excluded as evolutionary force influencing the t system. The possible influence of polyandry on the t system was then investigated by applying a stochastic model to this situation. Simulations show that polyandry can explain the observed t dynamics, making it a biologically plausible explanation for low t frequencies in natural populations in general.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.9069/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.9069/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.9069/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.9069/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.9069/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.9069/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.9069/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.9069","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.9069","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2011.01336.x","PMID:21884047"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9069"}}