{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-12T20:41:32Z","author":["Yun, Li","Agrawal, Aneil F."],"title":"Data from: Variation in the strength of inbreeding depression across environments: effects of stress and density dependence","host":"Yun L, Agrawal AF (2014) Variation in the strength of inbreeding depression across environments: effects of stress and density dependence. Evolution, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Fitness","Mutations","Mating Systems","Inbreeding","Competition"],"description":"In what types of environments should we expect to find strong inbreeding depression? Previous studies indicate that inbreeding depression, δ, is positively correlated with the stressfulness of the environment in which it is measured. However, it remains unclear why stress, per se, should increase δ. To our knowledge, only “competitive stress” has a logical connection to δ. Through competition for resources, better quality (outbred) individuals make the environment worse for lower quality (inbred) individuals, accentuating the differences between them. For this reason, we expect inbreeding depression to be stronger in environments where the fitness of individuals is more sensitive to the presence of conspecifics (i.e., where fitness is more density dependent). Indeed, some studies suggest a role for competition within environments but this idea has not been tested in the context of understanding variation in δ across environments. Using Drosophila melanogaster, we estimated δ for viability in 22 different environments. These environments were simultaneously characterized for (i) stressfulness and (ii) density dependence. Though stress and density dependence are moderately correlated with each other, inbreeding depression is much more strongly correlated with density dependence. These results suggest that mean selection across the genome is stronger in environments where competition is intense, rather than in environments that are stressful for other reasons.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.95pp7/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70308","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70308","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25213285","doi:10.1111/evo.12527"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.95pp7"}}