{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-04T20:40:21Z","author":["Sawa, Yoshiki","Yoshikawa, Yasushi","Miyagawa, Shigeru","Kuratani, Toru","Saito, Shunsuke","Sakaguchi, Taichi","Nishi, Hiroyuki","Fukushima, Satsuki","Ueno, Takayoshi"],"title":"Data from: Impact of microRNA expression in human atrial tissue in patients with atrial fibrillation undergoing cardiac surgery","host":"Nishi H, Sakaguchi T, Miyagawa S, Yoshikawa Y, Fukushima S, Saito S, Ueno T, Kuratani T, Sawa Y (2013) Impact of microRNA expression in human atrial tissue in patients with atrial fibrillation undergoing cardiac surgery. PLoS ONE 8(9): e73397.","keywords":["atrial fibrillation","cardiac surgery","microRNA","fibrosis"],"description":"Background: Although microRNA (miRNA) regulates initiation and/or progression of atrial fibrillation (AF) in canine AF models, the underlying mechanism in humans remains unclear. We speculated that certain miRNAs in atrial tissue are related to AF, and evaluated the relationship of miRNA expression in human atrial tissue in cardiac surgery patients. Methods: Right atrial tissues from 29 patients undergoing cardiovascular surgery were divided into 3 groups [A: chronic AF or unsuccessful maze, n=6; B: successful maze, n=10; C: sinus rhythm (SR) n=13]. miRNA expression was determined using high density microarrays and with Reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). Fibrosis was examined using Masson trichrome staining. Results: miRNA microarray analysis showed elevated miRNA-21, miRNA-23b, miRNA-199b, and miRNA-208b in AF as compared to SR groups. RT-PCR showed elevated miRNA-21 (1.9-fold) and miRNA-208b (4.2-fold) in AF as compared to the SR groups. miRNA-21 expression increased from Group C to A (A: 2.1-fold, B: 1.8-fold, C: 1.0-fold). Fibrosis increased from C to A (A: 43.0±12.9%, B: 21.3±6.1%, C: 11.9±3.1%). Percent fibrosis and miRNA-21 expression were correlated (r=0.508, p<0.05). The plasma levels of miRNA-21 in AF patients was significantly decreased as compared to the healthy volunteers (p<0.05). Conclusion: The expression of miRNA-21 in human atrial tissue was found to be related to atrial fibrosis and might affect AF occurrence, indicating its usefulness as a biomarker for cardiac surgery management.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8p1t6/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51951","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51951","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24069193","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0073397"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8p1t6"}}