{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-30T18:31:41Z","author":["Gruenthal, Kristen M.","Drawbridge, Mark A."],"title":"Data from: Toward responsible stock enhancement: broadcast spawning dynamics and adaptive genetic management in white seabass aquaculture","host":"Gruenthal KM, Drawbridge MA (2011) Toward responsible stock enhancement: broadcast spawning dynamics and adaptive genetic management in white seabass aquaculture. Evolutionary Applications 5(4): 405-417.","keywords":["Fisheries Management","Population Genetics - Empirical","Conservation Genetics","Captive Populations","Aquaculture"],"description":"The evolutionary effects captive-bred individuals can have on wild conspecifics are necessary considerations for stock enhancement programs, but breeding protocols are often developed without knowledge of realized reproductive behavior. To help fill that gap, parentage was assigned to offspring produced by a freely-mating group of 50 white seabass (Atractoscion nobilis), a representative broadcast spawning marine finfish cultured for conservation. Similar to the well-known and closely-related red drum (Sciaenops ocellatus), A. nobilis exhibited large variation in reproductive success. More males contributed and contributed more equally than females within and among spawns in a mating system best described as lottery polygyny. Two females produced 27% of the seasonal offspring pool and female breeding effective size averaged 1.85 per spawn and 12.38 seasonally, whereas male breeding effective size was higher (6.42 and 20.87, respectively), with every male contributing 1-7% of offspring. Further, females batch spawned every 1-5 weeks, while males displayed continuous reproductive readiness. Sex-specific mating strategies resulted in multiple successful mate pairings and a breeding effective to census size ratio of ≥ 0.62. Understanding a depleted species’ mating system allowed management to more effectively utilize parental genetic variability for culture, but the fitness consequences of long-term stocking can be difficult to address.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6n391t06/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36649","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36649","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/j.1752-4571.2011.00234.x","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6n391t06"}}