{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-09T01:19:18Z","author":["Contreras, Marinela","Grubhoffer, Libor","Estrada-Peña, Agustin","de la Fuente, Jose","Tobes, Raquel"],"title":"Data from: \"Transcriptome sequence identity between Lyme disease tick vectors, Ixodes scapularis and Ixodes ricinus\" in Genomic Resources Notes accepted 1 April 2014 to 31 May 2014","host":"Genomic Resources Development Consortium, Contreras M, de la Fuente J, Estrada-Peña A, Grubhoffer L and Tobes R (2014), Genomic Resources Notes accepted 1 April 2014 – 31 May 2014. Molecular Ecology Resources, 14(5): 1095.","keywords":["Agriculture","Transcriptomics","Parasitology","Invertebrates"],"description":"Ixodes scapularis and I. ricinus transmit the Lyme disease agent Borrelia burgdorferi in the U.S. and Europe, respectively. The only tick genome sequence available is that of I. scapularis, which constitutes a limitation for tick research. Recent evidences suggest that I. ricinus and I. scapularis transcriptomes share some degree of sequence identity. However, only the global transcriptome comparison reported here demonstrated that I. ricinus and I. scapularis share a 99.232±0.005 percent sequence identity with a very low frequency of INDELs. However, due to limitations of the current I. scapularis genome assembly, the number of aligned reads was only 26-27%. These results support the use of I. scapularis genome sequence as a reference for the analysis of I. ricinus transcriptomics and proteomics data, but addressing the limitations associated with the I. scapularis genome assembly.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.63882","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.63882","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/1755-0998.12298","PMID:24976445"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9js92"}}