{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-25T16:19:19Z","author":["Jones, Daniel","Dale, Trine","Smith, Craig","Sweetman, Andrew"],"title":"Data from: Rapid scavenging of jellyfish carcasses reveals the importance of gelatinous material to deep-sea food webs","keywords":["Metazoans","Scavenging","Deep sea","Jellyfish carcasses","Biological pump"],"description":"Jellyfish blooms are common in many oceans, and anthropogenic changes appear to have increased their magnitude in some regions. Although mass falls of jellyfish carcasses have been observed recently at the deep seafloor, the dense necrophage aggregations and rapid consumption rates typical for vertebrate carrion have not been documented. This has led to a paradigm of limited energy transfer to higher trophic levels at jelly falls relative to vertebrate organic falls. We show from baited camera deployments in the Norwegian deep sea that dense aggregations of deep-sea scavengers (>1000 animals at peak densities) can rapidly form at jellyfish baits and consume entire jellyfish carcasses in 2.5 hours. We also show that scavenging rates on jellyfish are not significantly different from fish carrion of similar mass, and reveal that scavenging communities typical for the NE Atlantic bathyal zone consume both types of carcasses, including the Atlantic hagfish, galatheid crabs, decapod shrimp and lysianassid amphipods. These rapid jellyfish carrion consumption rates suggest that the contribution of gelatinous material to organic fluxes maybe seriously underestimated in some regions because jelly falls may disappear much more rapidly than previously thought. Our results also demonstrate the energy contained in gelatinous carrion can be efficiently incorporated into large numbers of deep-sea scavengers and food webs, lessening the expected impacts of enhanced jellyfish production on pelagic-benthic coupling.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.90kt3/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.71089","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.71089","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.90kt3"}}