{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-31T16:50:24Z","author":["Wang, Yanhui","Xie, Qiang","Yu, Shasha","Bu, Wenjun","Rédei, Dávid"],"title":"Data from: Secondary structure models of 18S and 28S rRNAs of the true bugs based on complete rDNA sequences of Eurydema maracandica Oshanin, 1871 (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae)","host":"Yu S, Wang Y, Rédei D, Xie Q, Bu W (2013) Secondary structure models of 18S and 28S rRNAs of the true bugs based on complete rDNA sequences of Eurydema maracandica Oshanin, 1871 (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae). ZooKeys 319: 363–377.","keywords":["rRNA","molecular synapomorphy","secondary structure"],"description":"The sequences of 18S and 28S rDNAs have been used as molecular markers to resolve phylogenetic relationships of Heteroptera for two decades. The complete sequences of 18S rDNAs have been used in many studies, while in most studies only partial sequences of 28S rDNAs have been used due to technical difficulties of amplifying the complete lengths. In this study, we amplified the complete 18S and 28S rDNA sequences of Eurydema maracandica Oshanin, 1871, and reconstructed the secondary structure models of the corresponding rRNAs. In addition, and more importantly, all of the length variable regions of 18S rRNA were compared among 37 families of Heteroptera based on 140 sequences, and the D3 region of 28S rRNA was compared among 51 families based on 84 sequences. It was found that 8 length variable regions could potentially serve as molecular synapomorphies for some monophyletic groups. Therefore discoveries of more molecular synapomorphies for specific clades can be anticipated from amplification of complete 18S and 28S rDNAs of more representatives of Heteroptera.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.j8kp5/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.j8kp5/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.j8kp5/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.j8kp5/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.j8kp5/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.45357","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.45357","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24039531","doi:10.3897/zookeys.319.4178"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.j8kp5"}}