{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-09-02T20:01:42Z","author":["Cammen, Kristina","Knapp, Leslie A","Hoffman, Joe I","Amos, William","Harwood, John"],"title":"Data from: Geographic variation of the major histocompatibility complex in Eastern Atlantic grey seals (Halichoerus grypus)","host":"Cammen K, Hoffman JI, Knapp LA, Harwood J, Amos W (2010) Geographic variation of the major histocompatibility complex in Eastern Atlantic grey seals (Halichoerus grypus). Molecular Ecology 20(4): 740-752.","keywords":["isolation-by-distance","grey seal","microsatellites","selection","major histocompatibility complex"],"description":"Pathogen-driven balancing selection maintains high genetic diversity in many vertebrates, particularly in the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) immune \nsystem gene family, which is often associated with disease susceptibility. In large natural populations where subpopulations face different pathogen pressures, the MHC \nshould show greater genetic differentiation within a species than neutral markers. We examined genetic diversity at the MHC-DQB locus and nine putatively neutral \nmicrosatellite markers in grey seals (Halichoerus grypus) from eight United Kingdom colonies, the Faeroe Islands and Sable Island, Canada. Five DQB alleles were \nidentified in grey seals, which varied in prevalence across the grey seal range. Among the seal colonies, significant differences in DQB allele and haplotype \nfrequencies and in average DQB heterozygosity were observed. Additionally, the DQB gene exhibited greater differentiation among colonies compared with neutral markers, \nyet a weaker pattern of isolation-by-distance. After correcting for the underlying isolation-by-distance pattern, subpopulations breeding in similar habitats were more \nsimilar to one another in DQB allele frequencies than populations breeding in different habitats, but the same did not hold true for microsatellites, suggesting that \nhabitat-specific pathogen pressure influences MHC evolution. Overall, the data are consistent with selection at MHC-DQB loci in grey seals with both varying selective \npressures and geographic population structure appearing to influence the DQB genetic composition of breeding colonies.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8175/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8175","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8175","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21199032","doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2010.04975.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8175"}}