{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-13T13:40:20Z","author":["Nagamitsu, Teruyoshi","Tsumura, Yoshihiko","Shuri, Kato","Mukai, Yuzuru","Iwata, Hiroyoshi"],"title":"Data from: Impact of negative frequency-dependent selection on mating pattern and genetic structure: a comparative analysis of the S-locus and nuclear SSR loci in Prunus lannesiana var. speciosa","host":"Shuri K, Saika K, Junko K, Michiharu K, Nagamitsu T, Iwata H, Tsumura Y, Mukai Y (2012) Impact of negative frequency-dependent selection on mating pattern and genetic structure: a comparative analysis of the S-locus and nuclear SSR loci in Prunus lannesiana var. speciosa. Heredity 109: 188-198.","keywords":["paternity","negative frequency-dependent selection","self-incompatibility","SSR","S-alleles"],"description":"Mating processes of local demes and spatial genetic structure of island populations at the self-incompatibility (S-) locus under negative frequency-dependent selection (NFDS) were evaluated in Prunus lannesiana var. speciosa in comparison with nuclear simple sequence repeat (SSR) loci that seemed to be evolutionarily neutral. Our observations of local mating patterns indicated that male-female pair fecundity was influenced by not only self-incompatibility, but also various factors such as kinship, pollen production and flowering synchrony. In spite of the mating bias caused by these factors, the NFDS effect on changes in allele frequencies from potential mates to mating pollen was detected at the S-locus but not at the SSR loci although the changes from adult to juvenile cohorts were not apparent at any loci. Genetic differentiation and isolation-by-distance over various spatial scales were smaller at the S-locus than at the SSR loci, as expected under the NFDS. All ele sharing distributions among the populations also had a unimodal pattern at the S-locus, indicating the NFDS effect except for alleles unique to individual populations probably due to isolation among islands, although this pattern was not exhibited by the SSR loci. Our results suggest that the NFDS at the S-locus has an impact on both the mating patterns and the genetic structure in the P. lannesiana populations studied.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7c425/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.39132","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.39132","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2012.29","PMID:22669074"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7c425"}}