{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-19T20:00:47Z","author":["Soria-Carrasco, Victor","Johnston, J. Spencer","Egan, Scott P.","Bast, Jens","Crespi, Bernard J.","Farkas, Timothy E.","Schwander, Tanja","Buerkle, C. Alex","Comeault, Aaron A.","Parchman, Thomas L.","Feder, Jeffrey L.","Gompert, Zachariah","Nosil, Patrik"],"title":"Data from: Stick insect genomes reveal natural selection's role in parallel speciation","host":"Soria-Carrasco V, Gompert Z, Comeault AA, Farkas TE, Parchman TL, Johnston JS, Buerkle CA, Feder JL, Bast J, Schwander T, Egan SP, Crespi BJ, Nosil P (2014) Stick insect genomes reveal natural selection's role in parallel speciation. Science 344 (6185): 738-742.","description":"Natural selection can drive the repeated evolution of reproductive isolation, but the genomic basis of parallel speciation remains poorly understood. We analyzed whole-genome divergence between replicate pairs of stick insect populations that are adapted to different host plants and undergoing parallel speciation. We found thousands of modest-sized genomic regions of accentuated divergence between populations, most of which are unique to individual population pairs. We also detected parallel genomic divergence across population pairs involving an excess of coding genes with specific molecular functions. Regions of parallel genomic divergence in nature exhibited exceptional allele frequency changes between hosts in a field transplant experiment. The results advance understanding of biological diversification by providing convergent observational and experimental evidence for selection’s role in driving repeatable genomic divergence.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.74j06/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.74j06/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.74j06/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.74j06/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.63765","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.63765","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24833390","doi:10.1126/science.1252136"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.74j06"}}