{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-20T19:20:05Z","author":["Thompson, M","Heneghan, C","Cohen, D","Billingsley, M"],"title":"Data from: Medical-device recalls in the UK and the device-regulation process: retrospective review of safety notices and alerts","host":"Heneghan C, Thompson M, Billingsley M, Cohen D (2011) Medical-device recalls in the UK and the device-regulation process: retrospective review of safety notices and alerts. BMJ Open 1(1): e000155.","keywords":["clinical data","Medical-device","device-regulation"],"description":"Background: Medical devices are used widely for virtually every disease and condition. Although devices are subject to regulation, the number of recalls, the\nclinical data requirements for regulation and the impact on patient safety are poorly understood. Methods: The authors defined a device using\nEuropean directives and used publicly available information on the Medicines and Health Regulatory\nAuthority website to determine the number of devices recalled from January 2006 to December 2010. Two\nreviewers independently assessed Field Safety Notices and Medical Device Alerts. The authors wrote to\nmanufacturers to obtain further information and clinical data, and summarised data by year, Conformité Européenne classification, indication, and Food and Drug Administration recall system of severity. Results: In total, 2124 field safety notices were issued\nover the 5-year period, an increase of 1220% (62 in\n2006 to 757 in 2010). 447 Medical Device Alerts were issued in the same period, and 44% were assessed as a reasonable probability of causing serious adverse\nhealth consequences or death. The authors wrote to 192 manufacturers of withdrawn devices and received\n101 (53%) replies; only four (2.1%) provided the clinical data the authors requested. A lack of available transparent data prevented full analyses of the safety impact. Of the highest-risk recalled devices, more than\nhalf were related to the cardiovascular system (25%)\nor musculoskeletal system (33%), and 88% (95% CI 80% to 97%) were assessed as a reasonable\nprobability of causing serious adverse health consequences or death. For low-risk devices, the\nfigure was 34% (95% CI 26% to 42%). Conclusion: The number of medical devices subject to\nrecalls or warnings in the UK has risen dramatically. A substantial number of these devices may have caused serious adverse effects in patients and contributed to\nhealthcare costs. Significant problems exist in the UK with a lack of access to transparent data and a registry of the highest-risk devices.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.585t4/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.585t4/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.33846","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.33846","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2011-000155","PMID:22021778"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.585t4"}}