{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-30T18:09:17Z","author":["Leimar, Olof","Løvlie, Hanne","Favati, Anna"],"title":"Data from: Personality predicts social dominance in male domestic fowl","host":"Favati A, Leimar O, Løvlie H (2014) Personality predicts social dominance in male domestic fowl. PLoS ONE 9(7): e103535.","keywords":["social status","chicken","aggression","intra-sexual selection","social hierarchy","behavioural syndrome","personality","vigilance","exploration"],"description":"Individuals in social species commonly form dominance relationships, where dominant individuals enjoy greater access to resources compared to subordinates. A range of factors such as sex, age, body size and prior experiences has to varying degrees been observed to affect the social status an individual obtains. Recent work on animal personality (i.e. consistent variation in behavioural responses of individuals) demonstrates that personality can co-vary with social status, suggesting that also behavioural variation can play an important role in establishment of status. We investigated whether personality could predict the outcome of duels between pairs of morphologically matched male domestic fowl (Gallus gallus domesticus), a species where individuals readily form social hierarchies. We found that males that more quickly explored a novel arena, or remained vigilant for a longer period following the playback of a warning call were more likely to obtain a dominant position. These traits were uncorrelated to each other and were also uncorrelated to aggression during the initial part of the dominance-determining duel. Our results indicate that several behavioural traits independently play a role in the establishment of social status, which in turn can have implications for the reproductive success of different personality types.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.885g3/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67457","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67457","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25072296","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0103535"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.885g3"}}