{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"64;9;2010","keywords":["sexual selection","function-valued trait","condition-dependence","female choice"],"host":"Delcourt M, Blows MW, Rundle HD (2010) Quantitative genetics of female mate preferences in an ancestral and a novel environment. Evolution 64(9): 2758-2766.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8bq71011/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.37155","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2012-01-10T18:41:34Z","author":["Blows, Mark W.","Delcourt, Matthieu","Rundle, Howard D."],"title":"Data from: Quantitative genetics of female mate preferences in an ancestral and a novel environment","description":"A female’s mate preference is a potentially complex function relating variation in multiple male phenotypes with her probability of accepting individual males as a mate. Estimating the quantitative genetic basis of preference functions within a population is empirically challenging yet key to understanding preference evolution. We employed a recently described approach that uses random-coefficient mixed models in the analysis of function-valued traits. Using a half-sibling breeding design in a laboratory-adapted Drosophila serrata population, we estimated the genetic (co)variance function of female preference for male sexual displays composed of nine contact pheromones. The breeding design was performed across two environments: the food to which the population was well adapted and a novel food that reduced average female productivity by 35%. Significant genetic variance in female preference was detected and the majority (64.2%) was attributable to a single genetic dimension (eigenfunction), suggesting that preferences for different pheromones are not genetically independent. The second eigenfunction, accounting for 24% of the total genetic variance, approached significance in a conservative test, suggesting the existence of a second, independent genetic dimension. There was no evidence that the genetic basis of female preference differed between the two environments, suggesting the absence of genotype-by-environment interactions and hence a lack of condition-dependent preference expression.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.37155","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01031.x","PMID:20482612"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8bq71011"}}