{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-06-12T17:05:59Z","author":["Neubert, Eike","Baur, Hannes","Reichenbach, Fabian"],"title":"Data from: Sexual dimorphism in shells of Cochlostoma septemspirale (Caenogastropoda, Cyclophoroidea, Diplommatinidae, Cochlostomatinae)","host":"Reichenbach F, Baur H, Neubert E (2012) Sexual dimorphism in shells of Cochlostoma septemspirale (Caenogastropoda, Cyclophoroidea, Diplommatinidae, Cochlostomatinae). ZooKeys 208: 1-16.","keywords":["Sexual dimorphism","shell features","PCA ratio spectrum","LDA ratio extractor","allometry ratio spectrum"],"description":"Sexual dimorphisms in shell-bearing snails expressed by characteristic traits of their respective shells would offer the possibility for a lot of studies about gender distribution in populations, species, etc. In this study, the seven main shell characters of the snail Cochlostoma septemspirale were measured in both sexes: (1) height and (2) width of the shell, (3) height and (4) width of the aperture, (5) width of the last whorl, (6) rib density on the last whorl, and (7) intensity of the reddish or brown pigments forming three bands over the shell. The variation of size and shape was explored with statistical methods adapted to principal components analysis (PCA) and linear discriminant analysis (LDA). In particular, we applied some multivariate morphometric tools for the analysis of ratios that have been developed only recently, that is, the PCA ratio spectrum, allometry ratio spectrum, and LDA ratio extractor. The overall separation of the two sexes was tested with LDA cross validation. The results show that there is a sexual dimorphism in the size and shape of shells. Females are more slender than males and are characterised by larger size, a slightly reduced aperture height but larger shell height and whorl width. Therefore they have a considerable larger shell volume (about one fifth) in the part above the aperture. Furthermore, the last whorl of females is slightly less strongly pigmented and mean rib density slightly higher. All characters overlap quite considerably between sexes. However, by using cross validation based on the 5 continuous shell characters more than 90% of the shells can be correctly assigned to each sex.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ns7v7/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40767","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40767","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22859868","doi:10.3897/zookeys.208.2869"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ns7v7"}}