{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-13T17:38:38Z","author":["Hutchings, Jeffrey A.","Debes, Paul V."],"title":"Data from: Effects of domestication on parr maturity, growth, and vulnerability to predation in Atlantic salmon","host":"Debes PV, Hutchings JA (2014) Effects of domestication on parr maturity, growth, and vulnerability to predation in Atlantic salmon. Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences, online in advance of print.","keywords":["domestication","predation","aquaculture","stress","male parr maturation","growth"],"description":"Domestication can change fitness-related traits. We investigated domestication-induced changes in fitness-related traits in Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar) under naturally enriched laboratory conditions with and without threat of predation. Selection in two strains for rapid growth for 3 and 5 generations resulted in 2 and 3 times larger sizes of under-yearling parr relative to their wild ancestor. An initially larger size and ability to outgrow prey size more rapidly resulted in lower size-selective predation mortality for domesticated individuals. Growth under threat of predation was only reduced for wild individuals, suggesting that domestication co-selects for predator-related stress resistance. Size-adjusted male parr maturation probability was 34% in the wild strain, but significantly reduced to 10% and 7% after 3 and 5 generations of domestication, respectively. Together, freshwater-stage specific survival for individuals with a domesticated background relative to individuals with a wild genetic background might be higher in the presence of gape-limited predators preferring small individuals, but male reproductive success might be lower for domesticated individuals as their reproduction potential during the freshwater phase is reduced.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.3v670/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.3v670/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64746","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64746","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1139/cjfas-2013-0618","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3v670"}}