{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-19T21:26:08Z","author":["Palacios, Julia A.","Bryson Jr., Robert W.","Minin, Vladimir N.","Leaché, Adam D."],"title":"Data from: Phylogeography of the Trans-Volcanic bunchgrass lizard (Sceloporus bicanthalis) across the highlands of southeastern Mexico","host":"Leaché AD, Palacios JA, Minin VN, Bryson Jr RW (2013) Phylogeography of the Trans-Volcanic bunchgrass lizard (Sceloporus bicanthalis) across the highlands of southeastern Mexico. Biological Journal of the Linnean Society 110(4): 852–865.","keywords":["divergence","gene flow","skyline plot","Phrynosomatidae","Pleistocene","coalescence","biogeography","species delimitation"],"description":"We quantify the population divergence processes that shaped population genetic structure in the Trans-Volcanic bunchgrass lizard (Sceloporus bicanthalis) across the highlands of south-eastern Mexico. Multilocus genetic data from nine nuclear loci and mitochondrial (mt)DNA were used to estimate the population divergence history for 47 samples of S. bicanthalis. Bayesian clustering methods partitioned S. bicanthalis into three populations: (1) a southern population in Oaxaca and southern Puebla; (2) a population in western Puebla; and (3) a northern population with a broad distribution across Hidalgo, Puebla, and Veracruz. The multilocus nuclear data and mtDNA both supported a Late Pleistocene increase in effective population size, and the nuclear data revealed low levels of unidirectional gene flow from the widespread northern population into the southern and western populations. Populations of S. bicanthalis experienced different demographic histories during the Pleistocene, and phylogeographical patterns were similar to those observed in many co-distributed highland taxa. Although we recommend continuing to recognize S. bicanthalis as a single species, future research on the evolution of viviparity could gain novel insights by contrasting physiological and genomic patterns among the different populations located across the highlands of south-eastern Mexico.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51675","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51675","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/bij.12172","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7nv16"}}