{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-02T14:10:38Z","author":["Hamberg-van Reenen, Heleen H.","de Wit, G. Ardine","van den Berg, Matthijs","Engelfriet, Peter M.","Over, Eelco A. B.","van Gils, Paul F."],"title":"Data from: The polypill in the primary prevention of cardiovascular disease: cost-effectiveness in the Dutch population","host":"van Gils PF, Over EAB, Hamberg-van Reenen HH, de Wit GA, van den Berg M, Schuit AJ, Engelfriet PM (2011) The polypill in the primary prevention of cardiovascular disease: cost-effectiveness in the Dutch population. BMJ Open 1(2): e000363.","keywords":["Health economics","Stroke","Myocardial infarction","Public health"],"description":"OBJECTIVES: The aim of the present study was to estimate the cost-effectiveness of the polypill in the primary prevention of cardiovascular disease. DESIGN: A health economic modeling study. SETTING: Primary health care in the Netherlands. PARTICIPANTS: Simulated individuals from the general Dutch population, aged 45-75 years of age. INTERVENTIONS: Opportunistic screening followed by prescription of the polypill to eligible individuals. Eligibility was defined as having a minimum 10-year risk of cardiovascular death as assessed with the SCORE function of alternatively 5%, 7.5%, or 10%. Different versions of the polypill were considered, depending on composition: 1) the Indian polycap, with three different types of blood pressure lowering drugs, a statin, and aspirin; 2) as 1) but without aspirin; 3) as 2) but with a double statin dose. In addition, a scenario of (targeted) separate antihypertensive and/or statin medication was simulated. PRIMARY OUTCOME MEASURES: Cases of acute myocardial infarction or stroke prevented, QALYs gained, and the costs per QALY gained. All interventions were compared with usual care. RESULTS: All scenarios were cost-effective with an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio between €7,900-12,300 per QALY compared with usual care. Most health gains were achieved with the polypill without aspirin and containing a double dose of statins. With a 10-year risk of 7.5% as threshold, this pill would prevent approximately 3.5% of all cardiovascular events. CONCLUSIONS: Opportunistic screening based on global cardiovascular risk assessment followed by polypill prescription to those with increased risk offers a cost-effective strategy. Most health gain is achieved by the polypill without aspirin and a double statin dose.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qg54c627/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36114","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36114","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2011-000363","PMID:22189351"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qg54c627"}}