{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-20T17:19:32Z","author":["Osuna, María Dolores","Balas, Francisco Carlos","Pérez-Gragera, Fernando","López-Corrales, Margarita","Domínguez, Guadalupe"],"title":"Data from: Ex situ conservation of underutilised fruit tree species: establishment of a core collection for Ficus carica L. using microsatellite markers (SSRs)","host":"Balas FC, Osuna MD, Domínguez G, Pérez-Gragera F, López-Corrales M (2014) Ex situ conservation of underutilised fruit tree species: establishment of a core collection for Ficus carica L. using microsatellite markers (SSRs). Tree Genetics & Genomes 10(3): 703-710.","keywords":["Fig tree","Core collection","Plant genetic resources","Germplasm bank","Ex situ conservation","SSRs"],"description":"Ex situ germ plasm collections of woody crops are necessary to ensure the optimal use of plant genetic resources. The fig tree (Ficus carica L.) germ plasm bank, consisting of 229 accessions, is located in Centro de Investigación ‘La Orden’. Despite great progress in conservation, ex situ collections face size and organization problems. Core collections obtained from structured samples of bigger collections are a useful tool to improve germ plasm management. In this work, we used simple sequence repeat (SSR) markers to establish a core collection in this underutilised Mediterranean fruit tree species. Four approaches have been carried out (random sampling, maximization, simulated annealing and stepwise clustering) to determine the best method to develop a core collection in this woody plant. The genetic diversity obtained with each subset was compared with that of the complete collection. It was found that the most efficient way to achieve the maximum diversity was the maximization strategy, which, with 30 accessions, recovers all the SSR alleles and does not show significant differences in allele frequency distribution in any of the loci or in the variability parameters (H O, H E) between the whole and core collections. Thus, this core collection, a representative of most fig diversity conserved in the germ plasm bank, could be used as a basis for plant material exchange among researchers and breeders.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2r107/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.48446","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.48446","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1007/s11295-014-0715-3","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2r107"}}