{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-06-12T20:51:41Z","author":["Ying, Yanling","Chen, Nanying","Tao, Sudan","Zhu, Faming","Han, Zhedong","He, Junjun","He, Ji","He, Yanmin","Lv, Hangjun","Zhang, Wei","Wang, Wei"],"title":"Data from: Distribution of MICB diversity in the Zhejiang Han population: PCR sequence-based typing for exons 2–6 and identification of five novel MICB alleles","host":"Ying Y, He Y, Tao S, Han Z, Wang W, Chen N, He J, Zhang W, He J, Zhu F, Lv H (2013) Distribution of MICB diversity in the Zhejiang Han population: PCR sequence-based typing for exons 2–6 and identification of five novel MICB alleles. Immunogenetics 65(7): 485-492.","keywords":["major histocompatibility complex class I chain-related gene B","HLA-B"],"description":"The polymorphism of major histocompatibility complex class I chain-related gene B (MICB) and variations in MICB alleles in a variety of populations have been characterized using several genotyping approaches. In the present study, a novel polymerase chain reaction sequence-based typing (PCR-SBT) method was established for the genotyping of MICB exons 2–6, and the allelic frequency of MICB in the Zhejiang Han population was investigated. Among 400 unrelated healthy Han individuals from Zhejiang Province, China, a total of 20 MICB alleles were identified, of which MICB*005:02:01, MICB*002:01:01, and MICB*004:01:01 were the most predominant alleles, with frequencies of 0.57375, 0.1225, and 0.08375, respectively. Nine MICB alleles were detected on only one occasion, giving a frequency of 0.00125. Of the 118 distinct MICB ∼ HLA-B haplotypes identified, 42 showed significant linkage disequilibrium (P < 0.05). Haplotypes MICB*005:02:01 ∼ B*46:01, MICB*005:02:01 ∼ B*40:01, and MICB*008 ∼ B*58:01 were the most common haplotypes, with frequencies of 0.0978, 0.0761, and 0.0616, respectively. Five novel alleles, MICB*005:07, MICB*005:08, MICB*027, MICB*028, and MICB*029 were identified. Compared with the MICB*005:02:01 sequence, a G > A substitution was observed at nucleotide position 210 in MICB*005:07, and a 1,134 T > C substitution in MICB*005:08 and an 862 G > A substitution in MICB*027 were detected. In addition, it appears that MICB*028 probably arose from MICB*004:01:01 with an A to G substitution at position 1,147 in exon 6. MICB*029 had a G > T transversion at nucleotide position 730 in exon 4, compared with that of MICB*002:01:01. On the basis of the new PCR-SBT assay, these observed results demonstrated MICB allelic variations in the Zhejiang Han population.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.dc14n/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46382","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46382","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1007/s00251-013-0699-4","PMID:23549730"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.dc14n"}}