{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-04T16:06:52Z","author":["Coltman, David W.","Malenfant, René M.","Davis, Corey S."],"title":"Data from: Design of a 9K SNP chip for polar bears (Ursus maritimus) from RAD and transcriptome sequencing","host":"Malenfant RM, Coltman DW, Davis CS (2014) Design of a 9K SNP chip for polar bears (Ursus maritimus) from RAD and transcriptome sequencing. Molecular Ecology Resources, online in advance of print.","keywords":["next-generation sequencing","population genetics","Infinium BeadChip","single-nucleotide polymorphism","polar bear"],"description":"Single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) offer numerous advantages over anonymous markers such as microsatellites, including improved estimation of population parameters, finer-scale resolution of population structure, and more precise genomic dissection of quantitative traits. However, many SNPs are needed to equal the resolution of a single microsatellite, and reliable large-scale genotyping of SNPs remains a challenge in non-model species. Here, we document the creation of a 9K Illumina Infinium BeadChip for polar bears (Ursus maritimus), which will be used to investigate: 1) the fine-scale population structure among Canadian polar bears, and 2) the genomic architecture of phenotypic traits in the Western Hudson Bay subpopulation. To this end, we used restriction-site associated DNA (RAD) sequencing from 38 bears across their circumpolar range, as well as blood/fat transcriptome sequencing of 10 individuals from Western Hudson Bay. 6000 RAD SNPs and 3000 transcriptomic SNPs were selected for the chip, based primarily on genomic spacing and gene function respectively. Of the 9000 SNPs ordered from Illumina, 8042 were successfully printed, and—after genotyping 1450 polar bears—5441 of these SNPs were found to be well clustered and polymorphic. Using this array, we show rapid linkage disequilibrium decay among polar bears, we demonstrate that in a subsample of 78 individuals, our SNPs detect known genetic structure more clearly than 24 microsatellites genotyped for the same individuals, and that these results are not driven by the SNP ascertainment scheme. Here we present one of the first large-scale genotyping resources designed for a threatened species.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b35td/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66139","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66139","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/1755-0998.12327","PMID:25187336"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b35td"}}