{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-15T20:48:47Z","author":["Cavalieri, Duccio","Velasco, Riccardo","Goremykin, Vadim","Nikiforova, Svetlana V."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenetic analysis of 47 chloroplast genomes clarifies the contribution of wild species to the domesticated apple maternal line","host":"Nikiforova SV, Cavalieri D, Velasco R, Goremykin V (2013) Phylogenetic analysis of 47 chloroplast genomes clarifies the contribution of wild species to the domesticated apple maternal line. Molecular Biology and Evolution 30(8): 1751-1760.","keywords":["apples","chloroplast genome phylogeny"],"description":"Both the origin of domesticated apple and the overall phylogeny of the genus Malus are still not completely resolved. Having this as a target, we built a 134,553 position long alignment including two previously published cpDNAs and 45 de novo sequenced, fully co-linear chloroplast genomes from cultivated apple varieties and wild apple species. The data produced are free from compositional heterogeneity and from substitutional saturation, which can adversely affect phylogeny reconstruction. Phylogenetic analyses based on this alignment recovered a branch, having the maximum bootstrap support, subtending a large group of the cultivated apple sorts together with all analyzed European wild apple (Malus sylvestris) accessions. One apple cultivar was embedded in a monophylum comprising wild M. sieversii accessions and other Asian apple species. The data demonstrate that M. sylvestris has contributed chloroplast genome to a substantial fraction of domesticated apple varieties, supporting the conclusion that different wild species should have contributed the organelle and nuclear genomes to domesticated apple.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.33817/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49758","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49758","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23676769","doi:10.1093/molbev/mst092"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.33817"}}