{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-12T19:30:02Z","author":["Jacobs, Chris G. C.","Lee-Yaw, Julie A.","Irwin, Darren E."],"title":"Data from: Individual performance in relation to cytonuclear discordance in a northern contact zone between long-toed salamander (Ambystoma macrodactylum) lineages","host":"Lee-Yaw JA, Jacobs CGC, Irwin DE (2014) Individual performance in relation to cytonuclear discordance in a northern contact zone between long-toed salamander (Ambystoma macrodactylum) lineages. Molecular Ecology 23(18): 4590-4602.","keywords":["mitochondria","cytonuclear incompatibilities","amphibian","adaptive introgression","hybrid zone"],"description":"Cytonuclear discordance in contact zones between related lineages is common, with mitochondrial clines often being displaced from clines in nuclear allele frequency. Proposed explanations for such a pattern include adaptive introgression of mtDNA or a neutral wake of mtDNA being left behind following hybrid zone movement. However, studies investigating these hypotheses are rare. Our previous survey of genetic variation in the long-toed salamander (Ambystoma macrodactylum) highlighted a potential case of cytonuclear discordance between two lineages in western Canada. Here, we use additional markers and samples to clarify the extent of this discordance. We simultaneously assess the feeding performance of individuals in a common environment to test for an association between mitotype and individual performance. The genetic results confirm a general pattern of cytonuclear discordance in the focal region. However, we also observed more limited introgression of a diagnostic nuclear marker. Intriguingly, although there were differences in individual performance associated with the transition between mitotypes, these differences were not fully explained by mitotype. Instead, the lowest performance was observed in individuals demonstrating the greatest mismatch between mtDNA and all nuclear markers, suggesting the potential for cytonuclear incompatibilities to be acting. These results highlight the complexity of understanding the causes and consequences of mtDNA introgression and cytonuclear discordance in contact zones.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.q8473/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67579","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67579","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12878","PMID:25088666"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.q8473"}}