{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-17T17:43:18Z","author":["Brekke, Thomas David","Good, Jeffrey"],"title":"Data from: Parent-of-origin growth effects and the evolution of hybrid inviability in dwarf hamsters","keywords":["Speciation","genetic imprinting","Haldane's rule","Reproductive Isolation"],"description":"Mammalian hybrids often show abnormal growth, indicating that developmental inviability may play an important role in mammalian speciation. Yet it is unclear if this recurrent phenotype reflects a common genetic basis. Here we describe extreme parent-of-origin dependent growth in hybrids from crosses between two species of dwarf hamsters, Phodopus campbelli and P. sungorus. One cross type results in massive placental and embryonic overgrowth, severe developmental defects, and maternal death. Embryos from the reciprocal cross are viable and normal sized but adult hybrid males are relatively small. These effects are strikingly similar to patterns from several other mammalian hybrids. Using comparative sequence data from dwarf hamsters and several other hybridizing mammals, we argue that extreme hybrid growth can contribute to reproductive isolation during the early stages of species divergence. We next test if abnormal growth in hybrid hamsters is associated with disrupted genomic imprinting. We find no association between imprinting status at several candidate genes and hybrid growth, though two interacting genes involved in embryonic growth do show reduced expression in overgrown hybrids. Collectively, our study indicates that growth-related hybrid inviability may play an important role in mammalian speciation but that the genetic underpinnings of these phenotypes remain unresolved.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.sd931/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.sd931/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.sd931/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.sd931/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.sd931/5"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67838","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67838","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sd931"}}