{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-07T18:41:19Z","author":["Wyllie-Echeverria, Sandy","Ort, Brian S.","Boyer, Katharyn E.","Cohen, C. Sarah"],"title":"Data from: Population structure and genetic diversity among eelgrass (Zostera marina) beds and depths in San Francisco Bay","host":"Ort BS, Cohen CS, Boyer KE, Wyllie-Echeverria S (2012) Population structure and genetic diversity among eelgrass (Zostera marina) beds and depths in San Francisco Bay. Journal of Heredity 103(4): 533-546.","keywords":["gene flow","seagrass","restoration genetics","natural selection","marine population genetics"],"description":"The seagrass Zostera marina is widely distributed in coastal regions throughout much of the northern hemisphere, forms the foundation of an important ecological habitat, and is suffering population declines. Studies in the Atlantic and Pacific oceans indicate the degree of population genetic differentiation is location-dependent. San Francisco Bay, California, USA, is a high-current, high-wind environment where rafting of seed-bearing shoots has the potential to enhance genetic connectivity among Z. marina populations. We tested Z. marina from six locations, including one annual population, within the bay to assess population differentiation and to compare levels of within-population genetic diversity. Using seven microsatellite loci, we found significant differentiation among all populations. The annual population had significantly higher clonal diversity than the others but showed no detectible differences in heterozygosity or allelic richness. There appears to be sufficient input of genetic variation through sexual reproduction or immigration into the perennial populations to prevent significant declines in the number and frequency of alleles. In additional depth comparisons, we found differentiation among deep and shallow portions in one of three beds evaluated. Genetic drift, sweepstakes recruitment, dispersal limitation, and possibly natural selection may have combined to produce genetic differentiation over a spatial scale of 3 – 30 km in Z. marina. This implies the scale of genetic differentiation may be smaller than expected for seagrasses in other locations, too. We suggest that populations in close proximity may not be interchangeable for use as restoration material.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8gv43s53/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38372","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38372","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/jhered/ess022","PMID:22577191"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8gv43s53"}}