{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-12-18T20:26:53Z","author":["Bewick, Emily R.","White, Brooke E.","Sztepanacz, Jacqueline L.","Dyer, Kelly A.","Rundle, Howard D."],"title":"Data from: Reproductive character displacement of epicuticular compounds and their contribution to mate choice in Drosophila subqinaria and D. recens","host":"Dyer KA, White BE, Sztepanacz JL, Bewick ER, Rundle HD (2013) Reproductive character displacement of epicuticular compounds and their contribution to mate choice in Drosophila subqinaria and D. recens. Evolution, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Speciation","Reproductive Isolation","Signaling/Courtship"],"description":"Interactions between species can alter selection on sexual displays used in mate choice within species. Here we study the epicuticular pheromones of two Drosophila species that overlap partially in geographic range and are incompletely reproductively isolated. D. subquinaria shows a pattern of reproductive character displacement against D. recens, and partial behavioral isolation between conspecific sympatric vs. allopatric populations, whereas D. recens shows no such variation in mate choice. First, using manipulative perfuming experiments, we show that females use pheromones as signals for mate discrimination both between species and among populations of D. subquinaria. Second, we show that patterns of variation in epicuticular compounds, both across populations and between species, are consistent with those previously shown for mating probabilities: pheromone compositions differ between populations of D. subquinaria that are allopatric vs. sympatric with D. recens, but are similar across populations of D. recens regardless of overlap with D. subquinaria. We also identify differences in pheromone composition among allopatric regions of D. subquinaria. In sum, our results suggest that epicuticular compounds are key signals used by females during mate recognition, and that these traits have diverged among D. subquinaria populations in response to reinforcing selection generated by the presence of D. recens.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.17sr0/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.17sr0/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.17sr0/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.57586","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.57586","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12335","PMID:24351014"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.17sr0"}}