{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-13T17:22:13Z","author":["McDonald, Megan C.","Razavi, Mohammad","Friesen, Timothy L.","McDonald, Bruce A.","Brunner, Patrick C."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenetic and population genetic analyses of Phaeosphaeria nodorum and its close relatives indicate cryptic species and an origin in the Fertile Crescent","host":"McDonald MC, Razavi M, Friesen TL, Brunner PC, McDonald BA (2012) Phylogenetic and population genetic analyses of Phaeosphaeria nodorum and its close relatives indicate cryptic species and an origin in the Fertile Crescent. Fungal Genetics and Biology, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Species complex","Coalescent","Hybridization","Evolution"],"description":"The origin of the fungal wheat pathogen Phaeosphaeria nodorum remains unclear despite earlier intensive global population genetic and phylogeographical studies. We sequenced 1,683 bp distributed across three loci in 355 globally distributed Phaeosphaeria isolates, including 74 collected in Iran near the center of origin of wheat. We identified nine phylogenetically distinct clades, including two previously unknown species tentatively named P1 and P2 collected in Iran. Coalescent analysis indicates that P1 and P2 are sister species of P. nodorum and the other Phaeosphaeria species identified in our analysis. Two species, P. nodorum and P. avenaria f. sp. tritici 1 (Pat1), comprised ∼85% of the sampled isolates, making them the dominant wheat-infecting pathogens within the species complex. We designed a PCR-RFLP assay to distinguish P. nodorum from Pat1. Approximately 4% of P. nodorum and Pat1 isolates showed evidence of hybridization. Measures of private allelic richness at SSR and sequence loci suggest that the center of origin of P. nodorum coincides with its host in the Fertile Crescent. We hypothesize that the origin of this species complex is also in the Fertile Crescent, with four species out of nine found exclusively in the Iranian collections.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cg32n/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42369","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42369","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1016/j.fgb.2012.08.001","PMID:22922546"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cg32n"}}