{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-01-15T17:37:22Z","author":["Vignes-Lebbe, Régine","Ung, Visotheary","Burguiere, Thomas","Causse, Florian"],"title":"Data from: IKey+: a new single-access key generation web service","host":"Burguiere T, Causse F, Ung V, Vignes-Lebbe R (2012) IKey+: a new single-access key generation web service. Systematic Biology 62(1): 157-161.","keywords":["Biodiversity informatics","Single-access key","Taxonomy","Web service","Systematics"],"description":"Single-access keys are a major tool for biologists who need to identify specimens. The construction process of these keys is particularly complex (especially if the input dataset is large) so having an automatic single-access key generation tool is essential. As part of the European project ViBRANT, our aim was to develop such a tool as a web service, thus allowing end-users to integrate it directly into their workflow. IKey+generates single-access keys on demand, for single users or research institutions. It receives user input data (using the standard SDD format), accepts several key-generation parameters (affecting the key topology and representation), and supports several output formats. IKey+ is freely available (sources and binary packages) at www.identificationkey.fr. Furthermore, it is deployed on our server and can be queried (for testing purposes) via a simple web client also available at www.identificationkey.fr. Finally a client plugin will be integrated to the Scratchpads biodiversity networking tool (scratchpads.eu).","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.41188","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.41188","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22863681","doi:10.1093/sysbio/sys069"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3ft19"}}