{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-20T18:46:45Z","author":["Alberici da Barbiano, Laura","Gabor, Caitlin R.","Aspbury, Andrea S.","Nice, Chris C.","Gompert, Zachariah"],"title":"Data from: Population genomics reveals a possible history of backcrossing and recombination in the gynogenetic fish Poecilia formosa","host":"Alberici da Barbiano L, Gompert Z, Aspbury AS, Gabor CR, Nice CC (2013) Population genomics reveals a possible history of backcrossing and recombination in the gynogenetic fish Poecilia formosa. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 110(34): 13797-13802.","keywords":["Gynogenesis","Mixed mating complex"],"description":"Unisexual sperm-dependent vertebrates are of hybrid origins, rare, and predicted to be short-lived as a result of several challenges arising from their mode of reproduction. In particular, because of a lack of recombination, clonal species are predicted to have a low potential to respond to natural selection. However, many unisexual sperm-dependent species persist, and assessing the genetic diversity present in these species is fundamental to understanding how they avoid extinction. We used population genomic methods to assess genotypic variation within the unisexual fish Poecilia formosa. Measures of admixture and population differentiation, as well as clustering analyses, indicate that the genomes of individuals of P. formosa are admixed and intermediate between Poecilia latipinna and Poecilia mexicana, consistent with the hypothesis of their hybrid origins. Bayesian genomic cline analyses indicate that about 12% of sampled loci exhibit patterns consistent with inheritance from only one parent. The estimation of observed heterozygosity clearly suggests that P. formosa is not comprised of direct descendants of a single nonrecombining asexual F1 hybrid individual. Additionally, the estimation of observed heterozygosity provides support for the hypothesis that the history of this unisexual species has included backcrossing with the parent species before the onset of gynogenesis. We also document high levels of variation among asexual individuals, which is attributable to recombination (historical or ongoing) and the accumulation of mutations. The high genetic variation suggests that this unisexual vertebrate has more potential to respond to natural selection than if they were frozen F1 hybrids.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35/12"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51993","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51993","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1073/pnas.1303730110","PMID:23918384"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h6p35"}}