{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-08-16T16:22:29Z","author":["Lepais, Olivier","Bacles, Cecile F. E."],"title":"Data from: De novo discovery and multiplexed amplification of microsatellite markers for black alder (Alnus glutinosa) and related species using SSR-enriched shotgun pyrosequencing.","host":"Lepais O and Bacles CFE (2011) De novo discovery and multiplexed amplification of microsatellite markers for black alder (Alnus glutinosa) and related species using SSR-enriched shotgun pyrosequencing. Journal of Heredity 102(5): 627-632.","keywords":["next-generation sequencing","high throughput genotyping","common alder","454 GS-FLX Titanium","short sequence repeats"],"description":"Recent developments in sequencing technologies and bioinformatics analyses provide an unprecedented opportunity for cost and time effective high quality microsatellite marker discovery in non-model organisms for which no genomic information is available. Here, we use shotgun pyrosequencing of a microsatellite-enriched library to develop, for the first time, microsatellite markers for Alnus glutinosa, a keystone tree species of European riparian woodland communities. From a total of 17,855 short sequences, we identified 590 perfect microsatellites from which 392 had designed primers. A subset of 48 loci were tested for amplification, twelve of which were polymorphic in A. glutinosa. These twelve loci were successfully co-amplified in a single multiplex PCR experiment and validated for population genetics applications. In addition, ten and eight of these microsatellites were found to be transferable to the related A. incana and A. cordata species. The developed multiplex of 12 microsatellite markers therefore provides new opportunities for experimental evolutionary and forest genetics research in Alnus.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gg0jm/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.33842","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.33842","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/jhered/esr062","PMID:21705491"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gg0jm"}}