{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-01-15T18:51:33Z","author":["Rowell, David M.","Young, Andrew G.","Pickup, Melinda","Field, David L."],"title":"Data from: Predicting local adaptation in fragmented plant populations: implications for restoration genetics","host":"Pickup M, Field D, Rowell D, Young A (2012) Predicting local adaptation in fragmented plant populations: implications for restoration genetics. Evolutionary Applications 5(8): 913-924.","keywords":["QST","environmental heterogeneity","Adaptive differentiation","FST","population size"],"description":"Understanding patterns and correlates of local adaptation in heterogeneous landscapes can provide important information in the selection of appropriate seed sources for restoration. We assessed the extent of local adaptation of fitness components in 12 population pairs of the perennial herb Rutidosis leptorrhynchoides (Asteraceae) and examined if spatial scale (0.7 – 600km), environmental distance, quantitative Q_ST and neutral genetic differentiation F_ST, and size of the local and foreign populations could predict patterns of adaptive differentiation. Local adaptation varied among populations and fitness components. Including all population pairs, local adaptation was observed for seedling survival, but not for biomass, while foreign genotype advantage was observed for reproduction (number of inflorescences). Among population pairs, local adaptation increased with Q_ST and local population size for biomass. Q_ST was associated with environmental distance, suggesting ecological selection for phenotypic divergence. However, low F_ST and variation in population structure in small populations demonstrates the interaction of gene flow and drift in constraining local adaptation in R. leptorrhynchoides. Our study indicates that for species in heterogeneous landscapes, collecting seed from large populations from similar environments to candidate sites is likely to provide the most appropriate seed sources for restoration.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1qp8v/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40335","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40335","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1752-4571.2012.00284.x","PMID:23346235"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1qp8v"}}