{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-09-09T16:11:48Z","author":["Boag, Peter T.","Weber, Diana S.","Atkinson, Stephen N.","Saunders, Brenda L.","Van Coeverden de Groot, Peter J.","Lougheed, Stephen C.","Campagna, Leonardo","Dyck, Markus G."],"title":"Data from: Extensive sampling of polar bears (Ursus maritimus) in the Northwest Passage (Canadian Arctic Archipelago) reveals population differentiation across multiple spatial and temporal scales","host":"Campagna L, Van Coeverden de Groot PJ, Saunders BL, Atkinson SN, Weber DS, Dyck MG, Boag PT, Lougheed SC (2013) Extensive sampling of polar bears (Ursus maritimus) in the Northwest Passage (Canadian Arctic Archipelago) reveals population differentiation across multiple spatial and temporal scales. Ecology and Evolution 3(9): 3152–3165.","keywords":["Mark-recapture","Mitochondrial DNA","Species at risk","DNA microsatellites","Marine mammals","Conservation genetics"],"description":"As global warming accelerates the melting of Arctic sea ice, polar bears (Ursus maritimus) must adapt to a rapidly changing landscape. This process will necessarily alter the species distribution together with population dynamics and structure. Detailed knowledge of these changes is crucial to delineating conservation priorities. Here, we sampled 361 polar bears from across the center of the Canadian Arctic Archipelago spanning the Gulf of Boothia (GB) and M'Clintock Channel (MC). We use DNA microsatellites and mitochondrial control region sequences to quantify genetic differentiation, estimate gene flow, and infer population history. Two populations, roughly coincident with GB and MC, are significantly differentiated at both nuclear (FST = 0.01) and mitochondrial (ΦST = 0.47; FST = 0.29) loci, allowing Bayesian clustering analyses to assign individuals to either group. Our data imply that the causes of the mitochondrial and nuclear genetic patterns differ. Analysis of mtDNA reveals the matrilineal structure dates at least to the Holocene, and is common to individuals throughout the species’ range. These mtDNA differences probably reflect both genetic drift and historical colonization dynamics. In contrast, the differentiation inferred from microsatellites is only on the scale of hundreds of years, possibly reflecting contemporary impediments to gene flow. Taken together, our data suggest that gene flow is insufficient to homogenize the GB and MC populations and support the designation of GB and MC as separate polar bear conservation units. Our study also provide a striking example of how nuclear DNA and mtDNA capture different aspects of a species demographic history.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h1v63/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.50428","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.50428","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1002/ece3.662","PMID:24102001"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h1v63"}}