{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-26T20:35:24Z","author":["Russello, Michael A.","Jensen, Evelyn L.","Morbey, Yolanda E."],"title":"Data from: Time scale matters: genetic analysis does not support adaptation-by-time as the mechanism for adaptive seasonal declines in kokanee reproductive lifespan","host":"Morbey YE, Jensen EL, Russello MA (2014) Time scale matters: genetic analysis does not support adaptation-by-time as the mechanism for adaptive seasonal declines in kokanee reproductive lifespan. Ecology and Evolution 4(18): 3714-3722.","description":"Seasonal declines of fitness-related traits are often attributed to environmental effects or individual-level decisions about reproductive timing and effort, but genetic variation may also play a role. In populations of Pacific salmon (Oncorhynchus spp.), seasonal declines in reproductive life span have been attributed to adaptation-by-time, in which divergent selection for different traits occurs among reproductively isolated temporal components of a population. We evaluated this hypothesis in kokanee (freshwater obligate Oncorhynchus nerka) by testing for temporal genetic structure in neutral and circadian-linked loci. We detected no genetic differences in presumably neutral loci among kokanee with different arrival and maturation dates within a spawning season. Similarly, we detected no temporal genetic structure in OtsClock1b, Omy1009uw, or OmyFbxw11, candidate loci associated with circadian function. The genetic evidence from this study and others indicates a lack of support for adaptation-by-time as an important evolutionary mechanism underlying seasonal declines in reproductive life span and a need for greater consideration of other mechanisms such as time-dependent, adaptive adjustment of reproductive effort.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.98c48/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68720","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68720","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1002/ece3.1214","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.98c48"}}