{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-28T18:41:32Z","author":["Angert, Amy L.","Venable, D. Lawrence","Peterson, Megan","Huxman, Travis E.","Kimball, Sarah"],"title":"Data from: Phenotypic constraints and community structure: linking trade-offs within and among species","host":"Angert AL, Kimball S, Peterson M, Huxman TE, Venable DL (2014) Phenotypic constraints and community structure: linking trade-offs within and among species. Evolution, online in advance of print.","keywords":["winter annual plants","community assembly","genetic correlation","G-matrix","stress tolerance","growth rate"],"description":"Trade-offs are central to many topics in biology, from the evolution of life histories to ecological mechanisms of species coexistence. Trade-offs observed among species may reflect pervasive constraints on phenotypes that are achievable given biophysical and resource limitations. If so, then among-species trade-offs should be consistent with trade-offs within species. Alternatively, trait variation among co-occurring species may reflect historical contingencies during community assembly rather than within-species constraints. Here, we test whether a key trade-off between relative growth rate (RGR) and water-use efficiency (WUE) among Sonoran Desert winter annual plants is apparent within four species representing different strategies in the system. We grew progeny of maternal families from multiple populations in a greenhouse common garden. One species, Pectocarya recurvata, displayed the expected RGR – WUE trade-off among families within populations. For other species, although RGR and WUE often varied clinally among populations, among-family variation within populations was lacking, implicating a role for past selection on these traits. Our results suggest that a combination of limited genetic variation in single traits and negative trait correlations could pose constraints on the evolution of a high-RGR and high-WUE phenotype within species, providing a microevolutionary explanation for phenotypes that influence community-level patterns of abundance and coexistence.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gv682/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.69392","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.69392","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25163352","doi:10.1111/evo.12514"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gv682"}}