{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-21T17:17:44Z","author":["Duval, Thomas","Thébaud, Christophe","Milá, Borja","Delahaie, Boris","Cornuault, Josselin","García-Jiménez, Ricardo","Bertrand, Joris A. M.","Pujol, Benoit","Bourgeois, Yann X. C.","Heeb, Philipp"],"title":"Data from: Extremely reduced dispersal and gene flow in an island bird","host":"Bertrand JAM, Bourgeois YXC, Delahaie B, Duval T, García-Jiménez R, Cornuault J, Heeb P, Milá B, Pujol B, Thébaud C (2013) Extremely reduced dispersal and gene flow in an island bird. Heredity 112(2): 190–196.","keywords":["population differentiation","passerine","birds","microsatellites","White-eye"],"description":"The Réunion grey white-eye, Zosterops borbonicus, a passerine bird endemic to Réunion Island in the Mascarene archipelago, represents an extreme case of microgeographical plumage colour variation in birds, with four distinct colour forms occupying different parts of this small island (2512 km2). To understand whether such population differentiation may reflect low levels of dispersal and gene flow at a very small spatial scale, we examined population structure and gene flow by analysing variation at 11 microsatellite loci among four geographically close localities (<26 km apart) sampled within the distribution range of one of the colour forms, the brown-headed brown form. Our results revealed levels of genetic differentiation that are exceptionally high for birds at such a small spatial scale. This strong population structure appears to reflect low levels of historical and contemporary gene flow among populations, unless very close geographically (<10 km). Thus, we suggest that the Réunion grey white-eye shows an extremely reduced propensity to disperse, which is likely to be related to behavioural processes.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1652m/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53112","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53112","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24084644","doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.91"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1652m"}}