{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-26T17:06:26Z","author":"Patten, Manus","title":"Data from: Meiotic drive influences the outcome of sexually antagonistic selection at a linked locus","keywords":["Population genetics","Sexual selection & conflicts","Natural selection","Theory"],"description":"Most meiotic drivers, such as the t-haplotype in Mus and the segregation distorter (SD) in Drosophila, act in a sex-specific manner, gaining a transmission advantage through one sex while suffering only the fitness costs associated with the driver in the other. Their inheritance is thus more likely through one of the two sexes, a property they share with sexually antagonistic alleles. Previous theory has shown that pairs of linked loci segregating for sexually antagonistic alleles are more likely to remain polymorphic and that linkage disequilibrium accrues between them. I probe this similarity between drive and sexual antagonism and examine the evolution of chromosomes experiencing these selection pressures simultaneously. Reminiscent of previous theory, I find that: the opportunity for polymorphism increases for a sexually antagonistic locus that is physically linked to a driving locus; the opportunity for polymorphism at a driving locus also increases when linked to a sexually antagonistic locus; and stable linkage disequilibrium accompanies any polymorphic equilibrium. Additionally, I find that drive at a linked locus favours the fixation of sexually antagonistic alleles that benefit the sex in which drive occurs. Further, I show that under certain conditions reduced recombination between these two loci is selectively favoured. These theoretical results provide clear, testable predictions about the nature of sexually antagonistic variation on driving chromosomes and have implications for the evolution of genomic architecture.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7q577/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.69758","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.69758","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7q577"}}