{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-13T18:11:29Z","author":["Roy, Pranab","Chandradev, Sharma K.","Bhardwaj, Pardeep Kumar","Waikhom, Sayanika Devi","Singh, Mohendro Wakambam","Talukdar, Narayan Chandra","Bengyella, Louis"],"title":"Data from: Invasion of Solanum tuberosum L. by Aspergillus terreus: a microscopic and proteomics insight on pathogenicity","host":"Bengyella L, Waikhom SD, Roy P, Bhardwaj PK, Singh MW, Chandradev SK, Talukdar NC (2014) Invasion of Solanum tuberosum L. by Aspergillus terreus: a microscopic and proteomics insight on pathogenicity. BMC Research Notes 7: 350.","keywords":["phylogeny","maximum likelihood method","pathogenicity","Cadmodulin locus"],"description":"Background: Aspergillus terreus is one of the most harmful filamentous fungal pathogen of humans, animals and plants. Recently, researchers have discovered that A. terreus can cause foliar blight disease in potato (Solanum tuberosum L.). We used light and scanning electron microscopy, and performed proteomics analysis in an attempt to dissect the invasion process of A. terreus in this important crop. Results: Microscopic study revealed that invasion of leaf tissue is marked by rapid germination of A. terreus phialidic conidia (PC) by 4 h after inoculation. By 8 h after inoculation, primary germ tubes from PC differentiated into irregular protuberance, often displayed stomata atropism, and failed to penetrate via the epidermal cells. Colonization of leaf tissues was associated with high rate of production of accessory conidia (AC). These analyses showed the occurrence of a unique opposing pattern of AC, tissue-specific and produced on melanized colonizing hyphae during the infection of leaf tissue. A significant proteome change hallmarked by differential expression of class I patatin, lipoxygenase, catalase-peroxidase complex, and cysteine proteinase inhibitor were observed during tuber colonization. These proteins are often involved in signal transduction pathways and crosstalk in pathogenic responses. Conclusion: A. terreus abundantly produced AC and multipolar germinating PC to invade potato leaf tissue. Additionally, A. terreus differentially induced enzymes in potato tuber during colonization which facilitates rapid disease development.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.590j0/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.590j0/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64373","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64373","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1186/1756-0500-7-350","PMID:24917207"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.590j0"}}