{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-26T19:04:11Z","author":["Searle, Jeremy B.","Mathias, Maria da Luz","Britton-Davidian, Janice","Förster, Daniel W."],"title":"Data from: Origin of the chromosomal radiation of Madeiran house mice: a microsatellite analysis of metacentric chromosomes","host":"Mathias MdL, Britton-Davidian J, Searle JB, Förster DW (2012) Origin of the chromosomal radiation of Madeiran house mice: a microsatellite analysis of metacentric chromosomes. Heredity 110(4): 380–388.","keywords":["phylogeography","chromosomal rearrangements","colonization"],"description":"Chromosome races of Mus musculus domesticus are characterised by particular sets of metacentric chromosomes formed by Robertsonian fusions and whole-arm reciprocal translocations. The Atlantic island of Madeira is inhabited by six chromosome races of house mice with 6–9 pairs of metacentric chromosomes. Three of these races are characterised by the metacentric 3.8 also found elsewhere in the distribution of M. m. domesticus, including Denmark and Spain. We investigated the possibility that metacentric 3.8 was introduced to Madeira during the initial colonisation, as this could have ‘seeded’ the cascade of chromosomal mutation that is the basis of the extraordinary chromosomal radiation observed on the island. Variation at 24 microsatellite loci mapping to three different chromosomal regions (proximal, interstitial and distal) of mouse chromosomes 3 and 8 was investigated in 179 mice from Madeira, Denmark, Portugal, Spain, Italy and Scotland. Analyses of microsatellite loci closely linked to the centromeres of these chromosomes (‘proximal loci’) do not support a common evolutionary origin of metacentric 3.8 among Madeiran, Danish and Spanish mouse populations. Our results suggest that Madeiran mice are genetically more similar to standard karyotype mice from Portugal than to metacentric mice from elsewhere. There is expected to be an interruption to gene flow between hybridising metacentric races on Madeira, particularly in the chromosomal regions close to the rearrangement breakpoints. Consistent with this, relating to differentiation involving chromosomes 3 and 8 on Madeira, we found greater genetic structure among races for proximal than interstitial or distal loci.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jv2hd/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44056","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44056","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2012.107","PMID:23232832"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jv2hd"}}