{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-28T22:08:01Z","author":["Bilde, Trine","Lubin, Yael","Tuni, Cristina","Smith, Debroah","Berger-Tal, Reut"],"title":"Data from: Fitness consequences of outcrossing in a social spider with an inbreeding mating system","host":"Berger-Tal R, Tuni C, Lubin Y, Smith D, Bilde T (2013) Fitness consequences of outcrossing in a social spider with an inbreeding mating system. Evolution 68(2): 343–351.","keywords":["Genetic Drift","Gene Flow","Sociality","Mating Systems","Adaptation","Inbreeding"],"description":"Inbreeding mating systems are uncommon because of inbreeding depression. Mating among close relatives can evolve, however, when outcrossing is constrained. Social spiders show obligatory mating among siblings. In combination with a female-biased sex ratio, sib-mating results in small effective populations. In such a system high genetic homozygosity is expected, and drift may cause population divergence. We tested the effect of outcrossing in the social spider Stegodyphus dumicola. Females were mated to sib-males, to a non-nestmate within the population, or to a male from a distant population, and fitness traits of F1s were compared. We found reduced hatching success of broods from between-population crosses, suggesting the presence of population divergence at a large geographical scale that may result in population incompatibility. However, a lack of a difference in offspring performance between inbred and outbred crosses indicates little genetic variation between populations, and could suggest recent colonisation by a common ancestor. This is consistent with population dynamics of frequent colonisations by single sib-mated females of common origin, and extinctions of populations after few generations. While drift or single mutations can lead to population divergence at a relatively short time scale, it is possible that dynamic population processes homogenize these effects at longer time scales.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.c8qq7/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53078","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53078","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12264","PMID:24111606"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.c8qq7"}}