{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-22T13:02:49Z","author":["Iacovelli, Stephanie R.","Finseth, Findley R.","Harrison, Richard G.","Adkins-Regan, Elizabeth K."],"title":"Data from: A nonsemen copulatory fluid influences the outcome of sperm competition in Japanese quail.","host":"Finseth FR, Iacovelli SR, Harrison RG, Adkins-Regan EK (2013) A nonsemen copulatory fluid influences the outcome of sperm competition in Japanese quail. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 26(9): 1875–1889.","keywords":["sperm competition","seminal fluid proteins","foam gland","post-copulatory sexual selection","Japanese quail","ejaculate evolution"],"description":"Sperm competition is a powerful and widespread evolutionary force that drives the divergence of behavioral, physiological, and morphological traits. Elucidating the mechanisms governing differential fertilization success is a fundamental question of sperm competition. Both sperm and non-sperm ejaculate components can influence sperm competition outcomes. Here, we investigate the role of a non-semen copulatory fluid in sperm competition. Male Japanese quail possess a gland that makes meringue-like foam. Males produce and store foam independent of sperm and seminal fluid, yet transfer foam to females during copulation. We tested whether foam influenced the outcome of sperm competition by varying foam state and mating order in competitive matings. We found that the presence of foam from one male decreased the relative fertilization success of a rival, and that foam from a given male increased the probability he obtained any fertilizations. Mating order also affected competitive success. Males mated first fertilized proportionally more eggs in a clutch and had more matings with any fertilizations than subsequent males. We conclude that the function of foam in sperm competition is mediated through the positive interaction of foam with a male’s sperm, and we speculate whether the benefit is achieved through improving sperm storage, fertilizing efficiency, or retention. Our results suggest males can evolve complex strategies to gain fertilizations at the expense of rivals as foam, a copulatory fluid not required for fertilization, nevertheless has important effects on reproductive performance under competition.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mf587/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49124","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49124","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23890178","doi:10.1111/jeb.12189"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mf587"}}