{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-18T16:33:47Z","author":["Toews, David","Irwin, Darren","Brelsford, Alan"],"title":"Data from: Isotopic variation ccross the Audubon’s-myrtle warbler hybrid zone","keywords":["migration","Speciation","isotopes","hybrid zones","Birds","hybridization","migratory divide"],"description":"Differences in seasonal migratory behaviours are thought to be an important component of reproductive isolation in many organisms. Stable isotopes have been used with success to estimate the location and qualities of disjunct breeding and wintering areas. However, few studies have used isotope data to estimate the movements of hybrid offspring in species that form hybrid zones. Here we use stable hydrogen to estimate the wintering locations and migratory patterns of two common and widespread migratory birds, Audubon’s (Setophaga auduboni) and myrtle (S. coronata) warblers, as well as their hybrids. These two species form a narrow hybrid zone with extensive interbreeding in the Rocky Mountains of British Columbia and Alberta, Canada, which has been studied for over four decades. Isotopes in feathers grown on the wintering grounds or early on migration reveal three important patterns: 1) Audubon’s and myrtle warblers from allopatric breeding populations winter in isotopically different environments, consistent with band recovery data and suggesting that there is a narrow migratory transition between the two species, 2) most hybrids appear to over-winter in the southeast, similar to where myrtle warblers are known to winter and 3) some hybrid individuals, particularly those along the western edge of the hybrid zone, show Audubon’s-like isotopic patterns. These data suggest there is a migratory divide between these two species, but that it is not directly coincident with the center of the hybrid zone in the breeding range. We interpret these findings and discuss them within the context of previous research on hybrid zones, speciation and migratory divides.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h1j51/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.62960","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.62960","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h1j51"}}