{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-05T16:21:00Z","author":["Schwarzer, Julia","Mayer, Christoph","Dambach, Johannes","Raupach, Michael J.","Leese, Florian"],"title":"Data from: Isolation and characterization of nine polymorphic microsatellite markers for the deep-sea shrimp Nematocarcinus lanceopes (Crustacea: Decapoda: Caridea)","host":"Dambach J, Raupach MJ, Mayer C, Schwarzer J, Leese F (2013) Isolation and characterization of nine polymorphic microsatellite markers for the deep-sea shrimp Nematocarcinus lanceopes (Crustacea: Decapoda: Caridea). BMC Research Notes 6: 75.","keywords":["Southern Ocean","deep sea","Antarctic","microsatellites"],"description":"BACKGROUND: The shrimp Nematocarcinus lanceopes Bate, 1888 is found in the deep sea around Antarctica and sub-Antarctic islands. Previous studies on mitochondrial data and species distribution models provided evidence for a homogenous circum-Antarctic population of N. lanceopes. However, to analyze the fine-scale population genetic structure and to examine influences of abiotic environmental conditions on population composition and genetic diversity, a set of fast evolving nuclear microsatellite markers is required. FINDINGS: We report the isolation and characterization of nine polymorphic microsatellite markers from the Antarctic deep-sea shrimp species Nematocarcinus lanceopes (Crustacea: Decapoda: Caridea). Microsatellite markers were screened in 55 individuals from different locations around the Antarctic continent. All markers were polymorphic with 9 to 25 alleles per locus. The observed heterozygosity ranged from 0.545 to 0.927 and the expected heterozygosity from 0.549 to 0.934. CONCLUSIONS: The reported markers provide a novel tool to study genetic structure and diversity in Nematocarcinus lanceopes populations in the Southern Ocean and monitor effects of ongoing climate change in the region on the populations inhabiting these.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gg3rn/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46414","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46414","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23448502","doi:10.1186/1756-0500-6-75"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gg3rn"}}