{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-05T19:56:33Z","author":["von Wehrden, Henrik","Hirsch, Heidi","Hensen, Isabell","Wypior, Catherina","Renison, Daniel","Wesche, Karsten"],"title":"Data from: Germination performance of native and non-native Ulmus pumila populations","host":"Hirsch H, Wypior C, von Wehrden H, Wesche K, Renison D, Hensen I (2012) Germination performance of native and non-native Ulmus pumila populations. NeoBiota 15: 53–68.","keywords":["survival analysis","biological invasion","climatic influence"],"description":"Germination is a crucial step for invasive plants to extend their distribution under different environmental conditions in a new range. Therefore, information on germination characteristics of invasive plant species provides invaluable knowledge about the factors which might contribute to the invasion success. Moreover, intra-specific comparisons under controlled conditions will show if different responses between non-native and native populations are caused by evolutionary changes or by phenotypic plasticity towards different environmental influences. This paper focuses on the germination of native and non-native Ulmus pumila populations. We expected that non-native populations would be characterized by their higher final germination percentage and enhanced germination rate, which might indicate an influence due to corresponding climatic conditions. Germination experiments with a moderate and a warm temperature treatment did not reveal significant differences in final germination percentage. However, seeds from the North American non-native range germinated significantly faster than native seeds (p < 0.001). Additionally, mean time to germination in both ranges was significantly negatively correlated with annual precipitation (p = 0.022). At the same time, this relationship is stronger in the native range whereas mean time to germination in non-native populations seems to be less influenced by climatic conditions. Different germination responses of the North American populations could be caused by a fast evolutionary change mediating a higher tolerance to current climatic conditions in the non-native range. However, our findings could also be caused by artificial selection during the introduction process and extensive planting of Ulmus pumila in its non-native range. Nevertheless, we assume that the faster germination rate of non-native populations is one potential explanation for the invasion success of Ulmus pumila in its new range since it might provide a competitive advantage during colonization of new sites.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.fk376/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44740","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44740","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.fk376"}}