{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-03T19:02:02Z","author":["Thuiller, Wilfried","Lavergne, Sébastien","Roquet, Cristina"],"title":"Data from: One tree to link them all: a phylogenetic dataset for the European Tetrapoda","host":"Roquet C, Lavergne S, Thuiller W (2014) One tree to link them all: a phylogenetic dataset for the European Tetrapoda. PLoS Currents: Tree of Life 1.","keywords":["phylogenetic uncertainty","chronogram","phylogeny"],"description":"Since the ever-increasing availability of phylogenetic informative data, the last decade has seen an upsurge of ecological studies incorporating information on evolutionary relationships among species. However, detailed species-level phylogenies are still lacking for many large groups and regions, which are necessary for comprehensive large-scale eco-phylogenetic analyses. Here, we provide a dataset of 100 dated phylogenetic trees for all European tetrapods based on a mixture of supermatrix and supertree approaches. Phylogenetic inference was performed separately for each of the main Tetrapoda groups of Europe except mammals (i.e. amphibians, birds, squamates and turtles) by means of maximum likelihood (ML) analyses of supermatrix applying a tree constraint at the family (amphibians and squamates) or order (birds and turtles) levels based on consensus knowledge. For each group, we inferred 100 ML trees to be able to provide a phylogenetic dataset that accounts for phylogenetic uncertainty, and assessed node support with bootstrap analyses. Each tree was dated using penalized-likelihood and fossil calibration. The trees obtained were well-supported by existing knowledge and previous phylogenetic studies. For mammals, we modified the most complete supertree dataset available on the literature to include a recent update of the Carnivora clade. As a final step, we merged the phylogenetic trees of all groups to obtain a set of 100 phylogenetic trees for all European Tetrapoda species for which data was available (91%). We provide this phylogenetic dataset (100 chronograms) for the purpose of comparative analyses, macro-ecological or community ecology studies aiming to incorporate phylogenetic information while accounting for phylogenetic uncertainty.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.11609/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.11609/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.11609/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.11609/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.11609/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70059","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70059","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1371/currents.tol.5102670fff8aa5c918e78f5592790e48","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.11609"}}