{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-07T13:37:13Z","author":["Prado, Cynthia P. A.","Zamudio, Kelly R.","Haddad, Célio F. B.","Nali, Renato C."],"title":"Data from: Size-dependent selective mechanisms on males and females and the evolution of sexual size dimorphism in frogs","keywords":["Sexual dimorphism","Phylogenetics: comparative","Life history: ecology","Mating systems","Macroevolution","Life history: evolution","Behavior: reproductive","Anurans (frogs and toads)"],"description":"Sexual size dimorphism (SSD) varies in animals from male-biased to female-biased. The evolution of SSD is potentially influenced by a number of factors, such as territoriality, fecundity, and temporal breeding patterns (explosive vs. prolonged). In general, frogs show female-biased SSD with broad variance among species. Using comparative methods, we examine how different selective forces affect male and female sizes, and test hypotheses about size-dependent mechanisms shaping SSD in frogs. Male size was weakly associated with SSD in all size classes, and we found no significant association among SSD, male size, temporal breeding pattern, and male territoriality. In contrast, female size best explained SSD variation across all size classes, but especially for small-bodied species. We found a stronger evolutionary association between female body size and fecundity, and this fecundity advantage was highest in explosively-breeding species. Our data indicate that the fecundity-advantage associated with female body size may not be linear, such that intermediate and large females benefit less with body size increases. Therefore, size-dependent selection in females associated with fecundity and breeding patterns are important mechanisms driving SSD evolution in frogs. Our study underscores that lineage-specific ecology and behavior should be incorporated in comparative analyses of animal SSD.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.270sf/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68934","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68934","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.270sf"}}