{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-12-27T19:55:06Z","author":["Mitchell-Olds, Thomas","Lee, Cheng-Ruei","Anderson, Jill Theresa"],"title":"Data from: Strong selection genome-wide enhances fitness trade-offs across environments and episodes of selection","host":"Anderson JT, Lee C, Mitchell-Olds T (2013) Strong selection genome-wide enhances fitness trade-offs across environments and episodes of selection. Evolution 68(1): 16–31.","keywords":["evolutionary constraints","antagonistic pleiotropy","conditional neutrality","local adaptation","ecological genetics","fitness components"],"description":"Fitness trade-offs across episodes of selection and environments influence life-history evolution and adaptive population divergence. Documenting these trade-offs remains challenging as selection can vary in magnitude and direction through time and space. Here, we evaluate fitness trade-offs at the levels of the whole organism and the quantitative trait locus (QTL) in a multiyear field study of Boechera stricta (Brassicaceae), a genetically tractable mustard native to the Rocky Mountains. Reciprocal local adaptation was pronounced for viability, but not for reproductive components of fitness. Instead, local genomes had a fecundity advantage only in the high latitude garden. By estimating realized selection coefficients from individual-level data on viability and reproductive success and permuting the data to infer significance, we examined the genetic basis of fitness trade-offs. This analytical approach (Conditional Neutrality-Antagonistic Pleiotropy, CNAP) identified genetic trade-offs at a flowering phenology QTL (costs of adaptation) and revealed genetic trade-offs across fitness components (costs of reproduction). These patterns would not have emerged from traditional ANOVA-based QTL mapping. Our analytical framework can be applied to other systems to investigate fitness trade-offs. This task is becoming increasingly important as climate change may alter fitness landscapes, potentially disrupting fitness trade-offs that took many generations to evolve.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rp3pc/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53139","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53139","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12259","PMID:24102539"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rp3pc"}}