{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-01-04T17:42:55Z","author":["Lendemer, James C.","Hodkinson, Brendan P."],"series":"7;;2010","title":"Data from: The Wisdom of Fools: new molecular and morphological insights into the North American apodetiate species of Cladonia","host":"Lendemer JC, Hodkinson BP (2009) The Wisdom of Fools: new molecular and morphological insights into the North American apodetiate species of Cladonia. Opuscula Philolichenum 7: 79-100.","keywords":["podetia","taxonomy","species concepts","macrolichens","biogeography"],"description":"The taxonomy of the North American apodetiate and superficially apodetiate species of Cladonia with persistent, primarily squamulose thalli (viz., C. apodocarpa, C. caespiticia, and C. petrophila) is revised using morphological, chemical, and ecological data in combination with molecular phylogenetic analyses of ITS1, 5.8S, and ITS2 sequence data. The results of this approach confirm some established taxonomic concepts in the group and raise doubts about others. The taxon known as C. apodocarpa is well supported by likelihood- and parsimony-based molecular phylogenetic inferences as well as morphology, chemistry, and ecology. However, molecular evidence gives an equivocal answer to the question of whether C. petrophila is a distinct monophyletic entity or if C. apodocarpa is nested within it. In addition, no phylogenetic structure is detected for the chemical races of C. petrophila with and without fumarprotocetraric acid, based on the markers used in these analyses. However, C. petrophila does remain well supported as a taxon by chemistry (i.e., the presence of sphaerophorin), morphology, and ecology. A morphologically and ecologically distinct new taxon is described as C. stipitata. We confirm the distant relationship of these taxa (C. apodocarpa, C. petrophila, and C. stipitata) to C. caespiticia, a species with stipitate or pseudopodetiate (vs. sessile) apothecia. A treatment of the North American apodetiate species of Cladonia including distribution maps, cited specimens, and illustrations is presented. A key to the taxa that includes unrelated, frequently sterile species of Cladonia found in eastern North America is also provided.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.nv1sv92n/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36977","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36977","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.nv1sv92n"}}