{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-08-22T20:56:45Z","author":["Schwabl, I.","Versteegh, Maaike A.","Tieleman, B. Irene","Jacqier, Sophie"],"title":"Data from: Do immunological, endocrine and metabolic traits fall on a single Pace-of-Life axis? Covariation and constraints among physiological systems","host":"Versteegh MA, Schwabl I, Jacqier S, Tieleman BI (2012) Do immunological, endocrine and metabolic traits fall on a single Pace-of-Life axis? Covariation and constraints among physiological systems. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 25(9): 1864-1876.","keywords":["Comparative studies","Life history evolution","Adaptation","Evolutionary physiology","Birds"],"description":"Variation in demographic and physiological attributes of life-history is thought to fall on one single axis, a phenomenon termed the Pace-of-Life. A slow Pace-of-Life is characterized by low annual reproduction, long life span and low metabolic rate, a fast Pace-of-Life by the opposite characteristics. The existence of a single axis has been attributed to constraints among physiological mechanisms that are thought to restrict evolutionary potential. In that case, physiological traits should covary in the same fashion at the levels of individual organisms and species. We examined covariation at the levels of individual and subspecies in three physiological systems (metabolic, endocrine and immune) using four stonechat subspecies with distinct life-history strategies in a common garden set-up. We measured basal metabolic rate, corticosterone as endocrine measure, and six measures of constitutive immunity. Metabolic rate covaried with two indices of immunity at the individual level, and with corticosterone concentrations and one index of immunity at the subspecies level, but not with other measures. The different patterns of covariation among individuals and among subspecies demonstrate that links among physiological traits are loose and suggest that these traits can evolve independent of each other.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.kf320/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40922","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40922","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22817634","doi:10.1111/j.1420-9101.2012.02574.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.kf320"}}