{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-14T16:44:40Z","author":["Serret, Julien","Verhaegen, Daniel","Papineau, Christian","Pain, Anthony","Vaillant, Alexandre","Gâteblé, Gildas","Assoumane, Aichatou","Bouvet, Jean-Marc","Tassin, Jacques","Favreau, Bénédicte","Noe, Sandrine","Maggia, Laurent"],"title":"Data from: Structure and genetic diversity of Ixora margaretae an endangered species: a baseline study for conservation and restoration of natural dry forest of New Caledonia","host":"Verhaegen D, Assoumane A, Serret J, Noe S, Favreau B, Vaillant A, Gâteblé G, Pain A, Papineau C, Maggia L, Tassin J, Bouvet J (2012) Structure and genetic diversity of Ixora margaretae an endangered species: a baseline study for conservation and restoration of natural dry forest of New Caledonia. Tree Genetics & Genomes 9(2) 511-524.","keywords":["gene flow","genetic drift","sclerophyll forests","Biodiversity hotspot","ecology","SSR","endemism"],"description":"The dry forests of New Caledonia are an excep- tional ecosystem because of their numerous endemic botan- ical species and their highly diversified fauna of insects, mollusks, reptiles and birds. Unfortunately, the area of the dry forests has been significantly reduced, mainly by human activities. Ecological, phenological and genetic analysis of Ixora margaretae, a symbolic species of the sclerophyll forest, has revealed contrasting traits among natural stands. The division of the natural range and then the separation of forest islands has greatly reduced the existing genetic vari- ability of this species. The genetic diversity is strongly structured in genetic clusters which correspond well to spe- cific ecotypes according to the environmental conditions and the forest types. Furthermore, genetic analysis of the reproductive and non-reproductive trees as well the half- sib families obtained by complete protection of mother trees has revealed substantial genetic drift which has resulted in increased loss of allelic variability. The total consumption of seeds by mainly rats confirms the ob- served absence of natural regeneration. All these results show that measures taken to protect the stands of dry forests will not be enough to maintain sufficient genetic variability of I. margaretae populations in the long term. Assisted regeneration with control of the increase in var- iability will be necessary to maintain the biodiversity of the species. The results obtained for I. margaretae must be confirmed with other symbolic species in order to take the necessary measures for the effective preservation of the dry forests in New Caledonia.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.76nv3/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.76nv3/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42774","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42774","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1007/s11295-012-0575-7","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.76nv3"}}