{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-02T14:59:26Z","author":["Mills, Cynthia J.","Karoly, Keith","Conner, Jeffrey K.","Koelling, Vanessa A."],"title":"Data from: Artificial selection on anther exsertion in wild radish, Raphanus raphanistrum","host":"Conner JK, Mills CJ, Koelling VA, Karoly K (2014) Artificial selection on anther exsertion in wild radish, Raphanus raphanistrum. Scientific Data 1: 140027","keywords":["floral traits","quantitative genetics","evolutionary genetics","plants"],"description":"To study the genetic architecture of anther exsertion, a trait under stabilizing selection in wild radish, artificial selection on anther exsertion was applied for 11 generations. Two replicate lines each of increased and decreased exsertion plus two randomly-mated controls were included. Full pedigree information is available from generation five. To estimate correlated responses to selection, 571 plants from all lines and matrilines were grown in the greenhouse and a number of floral, growth, and phenology traits were measured. To create an outbred F2 mapping population, all possible crosses among the two high and two low exsertion lines were made, using a multiple-family design to capture the genetic variance still present after 11 generations of selection. Six floral traits were measured on 40 parents, 240 F1, and 4,868 F2 offspring. Opportunities for reuse of these data include traits not previously analyzed, other analyses, especially using the pedigree and fitness data, and seeds from all generations and photos of flowers in the later generations are available.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.6cq0n/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.6cq0n/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.6cq0n/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.6cq0n/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.6cq0n/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.6cq0n/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.63007","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.63007","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1038/sdata.2014.27","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6cq0n"}}