{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-24T14:42:38Z","author":["Gomez-Zurita, Jesus","Montelongo, Tinguaro"],"title":"Data from: Non-random patterns of genetic admixture expose the complex historical hybrid origin of unisexual leaf beetle species in the genus Calligrapha","keywords":["Reproduction: strategies","Phylogeny","Life history: evolution","Biodiversity","beetles","Hybridization"],"description":"Many unisexual animal lineages supposedly arose from hybridization. However, support for these putative hybrid origins mostly comes from indirect methodologies, which are rarely confirmatory. Here, we provide compelling data showing that tetraploid unisexual Calligrapha are true genetic mosaics by analyzing mtDNA, and allelic variation and coalescent times for three single copy nuclear genes (CPS, HARS and Wg) in five out of six unisexual Calligrapha and a representative sample of bisexual species. Nuclear allelic diversity in unisexuals consistently segregates in the gene pools of at least two, but up to three divergent bisexual species, interpreted as putative parentals of interspecific hybridization crosses. Interestingly, their mtDNA diversity derives from an additional, yet undiscovered older evolutionary lineage, possibly the same for all independently originated unisexual species. One possibly extinct species transferred its mtDNA to several evolutionary lineages in a wave of hybridization events during the Pliocene, whereby descendant species retained a polymorphic mtDNA constitution. Recent hybridizations, in the Pleistocene, always involving females with the old introgressed mtDNA seemingly occurred in the lineages leading to unisexual species, decoupling mtDNA introgression (and inferences derived from these data, such as timing and parentage) from subsequent acquisition of the new reproductive mode. These results illuminate an unexpected complexity for possible routes to animal unisexuality, including the interpretation of 'ancient' unisexuality. If the origin of unisexuality requires a mechanism where (1) hybridization is a necessary but not sufficient condition and (2) multiple bouts of hybridization involving more than two divergent lineages are required, the origin of several classical unisexual systems may have to be reassessed.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.b8h1n/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.b8h1n/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.b8h1n/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.b8h1n/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68221","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68221","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b8h1n"}}