{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-12T20:12:04Z","author":["Ruiz-Trillo, Iñaki","Medina-Chacón, Luis A.","Marshall, Wyth","Suga, Hiroshi","Paps, Jordi"],"title":"Data from: Molecular phylogeny of unikonts: new insights into the position of apusomonads and ancyromonads and the internal relationships of Opisthokontsí","host":"Paps J, Medina-Chacón LA, Marshall W, Suga H, Ruiz-Trillo I (2012) Molecular phylogeny of unikonts: new insights into the position of apusomonads and ancyromonads and the internal relationships of Opisthokontsí. Protist 164(1): 2–12.","keywords":["eukaryotes","cilia","opisthokonts"],"description":"The eukaryotic supergroup known as the Opisthokonta includes animals (Metazoa), fungi, choanoflagellates, as well as some poorly-studied unicellular eukaryotes, such as the Nucleariidea, Fonticula alba, the Ichthyosporea, the Filasterea and Corallochytrium limacisporum. Whereas the evolutionary positions of the well-known opisthokont lineages are mostly resolved, the specific phylogenetic relationships among those neglected opisthokont lineages is unsettled. Moreover, it remains unclear whether Amoebozoa or Apusozoa are the sister group to opisthokonts. Aiming at elucidating the evolutionary tree of the opisthokonts, we have produced a dataset with a large sampling of both organisms and number of genes, including representatives from all known opisthokont lineages. Moreover, we have generated new molecular data from an additional ichthyosporean (Creolimax fragrantissima) and a choanoflagellate (Codosiga botrytis). Our analyses show the Apusozoa as a paraphyletic assemblage with the Apusomonadida as sister group to Opisthokonta. Within the the Holozoa, the Ichthyosporea are shown as the first splitting group, followed by C. limacisporum, the Filasterea, the Choanoflagellata, and the Metazoa. With this taxon-rich opisthokont tree, it is possible to pinpoint the origin and evolution of morphological characters. As an example, we discuss cilia evolution under the evolutionary scenario here presented.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v3p3j/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40739","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40739","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1016/j.protis.2012.09.002","PMID:23083534"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v3p3j"}}