{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-05T20:11:12Z","author":["Clement, Wendy L.","Edwards, Erika J.","Chatelet, David S.","Sack, Lawren","Donoghue, Michael J."],"title":"Data from: The evolution of photosynthetic anatomy in Viburnum (Adoxaceae)","host":"Chatelet DS, Clement WL, Sack L, Donoghue MJ, Edwards EJ (2013) The evolution of photosynthetic anatomy in Viburnum (Adoxaceae). International Journal of Plant Sciences 174(9): 1277-1291.","keywords":["photosynthesis","mesophyll","H-cell","palisade","evolution"],"description":"Premise of research: Leaf mesophyll is often differentiated into a palisade layer with tightly packed, elongated cells (I-cells) and a spongy layer with loosely packed, complex shaped cells. An alternative palisade type, composed of branched H-cells, has evolved in a number of plant lineages. Viburnum (Adoxaceae) possesses both types of palisade, providing an opportunity to assess the significance of evolutionary switches between these forms. Methodology: An anatomical survey of 80 species spanning the Viburnum phylogeny permitted an analysis of palisade differences in relation to other characters. A geometric model of leaf mesophyll surface area for CO2 absorption correlated well with measured photosynthetic capacity in a subset of species, allowing us to infer shifts in photosynthetic function. Pivotal results: Ancestrally, viburnums probably produced a palisade with one layer of H-cells. Multiple transitions to two layers of H-cells (H2) and to one or two layers of I-cells (I1, I2) occurred. These shifts were correlated with increases in photosynthetic capacity, and H2 appear functionally equivalent to I1 with respect to CO2 absorption. Conclusions: Photosynthetic anatomy H2 and I1 palisade may represent alternative evolutionary solutions for increasing leaf CO2 absorption. Additionally, H-cells and I-cells might perform differently with respect to light absorption and/or drought tolerance. The evolution of I-palisade cells may thus have tracked movements into open environments, while H2 could increase photosynthetic capacity in the forest understory.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.457f7/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.457f7/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.50041","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.50041","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1086/673241","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.457f7"}}