{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-22T19:36:16Z","author":["Takeuchi, Hirohiko","Ding, Li","Huang, Song","Myers, Edward A.","Zhang, Yaping","Rao, Dingqi","Guo, Peng","Burbrink, Frank T.","Che, Jing","Jiang, Ke","Chen, Xin"],"title":"Data from: Assessing species boundaries and the phylogenetic position of the rare Szechwan Ratsnake, Euprepiophis perlacea (Serpentes: Colubridae), using coalescent-based methods","host":"Chen X, Jiang K, Guo P, Huang S, Rao D, Ding L, Takeuchi H, Che J, Zhang Y, Myers EA, Burbrink FT (2013) Assessing species boundaries and the phylogenetic position of the rare Szechwan Ratsnake, Euprepiophis perlacea (Serpentes: Colubridae), using coalescent-based methods. Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution 70: 130–136.","keywords":["species tree","coalescence","gene tree","species delimitation"],"description":"Delimiting species and clarifying phylogenetic relationships are the main goals of systematics. For species with questionable taxonomic status, species delimitation approaches using multi-species coalescent models with multiple loci are recommended if morphological data are unavailable or unhelpful. Moreover, these methods will also reduce subjectivity based on genetic distance or requirement of monophyletic genetic lineages. We determine the validity and phylogenetic position of a rare and long controversial species of Chinese reptile, the Szechwan ratsnake (Euprepiophis perlacea), using multi-locus data from multiple individuals and coalescent-based approaches. Species were first delimited using Bayesian Phylogenetics & Phylogeography (BP&P), Brownie and Bayes Factor model comparison approaches, while relationships among species were estimated using species tree inference in *BEAST. Results indicate that Euprepiophis perlacea is a distinct species sister to Euprepiophis mandarinus. Despite gene tree discrepancy, the coalescent model-based approaches used here demonstrate the taxonomic validity and the phylogenetic position of Euprepiophis perlacea. These approaches objectively test the validity of questionable species diagnoses based on morphological characters and determine their phylogenetic position.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53759","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53759","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1016/j.ympev.2013.09.003","PMID:24060366"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.053m3"}}