{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-11T19:49:20Z","author":["Alexander, Neil S.","Wint, William"],"title":"Data from: Projected population proximity indices (30km) for 2005, 2030 & 2050","host":"Alexander NS, Wint W (2013) Projected population proximity indices (30km) for 2005, 2030 & 2050. Journal of Open Public Health Data 1(1): e2.","keywords":["Future","Distance-weighted","EDENext extent","Proximity","Population","Projections"],"description":"This data package includes nine population proximity index layers for 2005, 2030 and 2050, for rural, urban and total populations.  The layers are distributed as 1km GeoTIFFs and GeoJPGss at 1km. The aim of these layers is to describe the population which may be likely to visit a specific locality where access is determined by Euclidean distance. By using the layers alongside other geographic datasets relating to disease risk it may help identify where people may come into contact with a disease. Human population layers are often used in models to identify risk areas where humans and viruses interact, however most pathogens are not restricted to areas of human habitation: many are found in lesser populated areas such as forests. This dataset will help identify less populated areas that may well still receive high visitor numbers. The layers have been projected to 2030 and 2050 to enable projections of human/disease interfaces in the medium-term which are required to inform policy makers at country and continental level. Urban and rural populations have been separated into individual layers as in some cases it is useful to distinguish between the behaviour and associated risks attributed to the different population segments. There may be a different risk of contacting diseases in rural habitats for rural workers than for than urban visitors.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.12734/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.48530","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.48530","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.5334/jophd.ab","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.12734"}}