{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-04-01T17:47:06Z","author":["Pendergast, Thomas H.","Anderson, Jill T.","Nuttle, Tim","Saldaña Rojas, Joe S.","Flecker, Alexander S."],"title":"Data from: Extremely long-distance seed dispersal by an overfished Amazonian frugivore","host":"Anderson JT, Nuttle T, Saldaña Rojas JS, Pendergast TH, Flecker AS (2011) Extremely long-distance seed dispersal by an overfished Amazonian frugivore. Proceedings of the Royal Society B, online in advance of print.","keywords":["dispersal kernel","movement ecology","seed dispersal","radiotelemetry","frugivorous fish"],"description":"Throughout Amazonia, overfishing has decimated populations of fruit-eating fishes, especially the largebodied\ncharacid, Colossoma macropomum. During lengthy annual floods, frugivorous fishes enter vast\nAmazonian floodplains, consume massive quantities of fallen fruits and egest viable seeds. Many tree\nand liana species are clearly specialized for icthyochory, and seed dispersal by fish may be crucial for\nthe maintenance of Amazonian wetland forests. Unlike frugivorous mammals and birds, little is known\nabout seed dispersal effectiveness of fishes. Extensive mobility of frugivorous fish could result in extremely\neffective, multi-directional, long-distance seed dispersal. Over three annual flood seasons, we tracked\nfine-scale movement patterns and habitat use of wild Colossoma, and seed retention in the digestive\ntracts of captive individuals. Our mechanistic model predicts that Colossoma disperses seeds extremely\nlong distances to favourable habitats. Modelled mean dispersal distances of 337–552 m and maximum\nof 5495 m are among the longest ever reported. At least 5 per cent of seeds are predicted to disperse\n1700–2110 m, farther than dispersal by almost all other frugivores reported in the literature. Additionally,\nseed dispersal distances increased with fish size, but overfishing has biased Colossoma populations to\nsmaller individuals. Thus, overexploitation probably disrupts an ancient coevolutionary relationship\nbetween Colossoma and Amazonian plants.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.9028/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.9028/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.9028/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.9028/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.9028","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.9028","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rspb.2011.0155","PMID:21429923"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9028"}}