{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-26T15:54:42Z","author":["Baur, Hannes","Cruaud, Astrid","Gokhman, Vladimir E.","Timokhov, Alexander V.","Rasplus, Jean-Yves","Kranz-Baltensperger, Yvonne"],"title":"Data from: Morphometric analysis and taxonomic revision of Anisopteromalus Ruschka (Hymenoptera: Chalcidoidea: Pteromalidae) – an integrative approach","host":"Baur H, Kranz-Baltensperger Y, Cruaud A, Rasplus J, Timokhov AV, Gokhman VE (2014) Morphometric analysis and taxonomic revision of Anisopteromalus Ruschka (Hymenoptera: Chalcidoidea: Pteromalidae) – an integrative approach. Systematic Entomology 39(4): 691–709.","keywords":["principal component analysis","new species","mitochondrial cytochrome b","multivariate ratio analysis","nuclear internal transcribed spacer 2","systematics","molecular analysis","ITS2","morphometry","MRA","linear discriminant analysis","Cytb","LDA","PCA"],"description":"We use an integrative taxonomic approach to revise the genus Anisopteromalus. In particular, we apply multivariate ratio analysis (MRA), a rather new statistical method based on principal component analysis (PCA) and linear discriminant analysis (LDA), to numerous body measurements and combine the data with those from our molecular analysis of Cytb and ITS2 genetic markers (on a subset of species) and all available published data on morphology, karyology, behavior, host associations, and geographic distribution. We demonstrate that the analysis of quantitative characters using MRA plays a major role for the integration of name-bearing types and thus for the association of taxa with names. Six species are recognized, of which two are new: A. cornis Baur sp. n. and A. quinarius Gokhman & Baur sp. n. For Anisopteromalus calandrae (Howard), a well-known, cosmopolitan parasitoid of stored-product pests, we have selected a neotype to foster continuity and stability in the application of this important name. The species was sometimes confused with the related A. quinarius sp. n., another cosmopolitan species that is frequently encountered in similar environments. We also show that several species originally described or later put under Anisopteromalus actually belong to different genera: Cyrtoptyx camerunus (Risbec) comb. n.; Meraporus glaber (Szelényi) comb. n.; Dinarmus schwenkei (Roomi, Khan & Khan) comb. n. Neocatolaccus indicus Ayyar & Mani is confirmed as a junior synonym of Oxysychus sphenopterae (Ferrière) syn. n. and Anisopteromalus calandrae brasiliensis (Domenichini) stat. rev. must be considered as a valid but doubtful taxon.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.km728/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.62512","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.62512","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/syen.12081","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.km728"}}