{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-29T16:09:37Z","author":["Fuller, Rebecca C","Travis, Joseph","Schrader, Matthew"],"title":"Data from: Do density-driven mating system differences explain reproductive incompatibilities between populations of a placental fish?","host":"Schrader M, Travis J, Fuller RC (2011) Do density-driven mating system differences explain reproductive incompatibilities between populations of a placental fish? Molecular Ecology 20(19): 4140-4151.","keywords":["mating system","viviparity","conflict","reproductive isolation"],"description":"Matrotrophy, the provisioning of embryos between fertilization and birth, creates the potential for conflict between mothers and embryos over the level of maternal investment. This conflict is predicted to drive the evolution of reproductive isolation between populations with different mating systems. In this study we examine whether density-driven mating system differences explain the patterns of asymmetric reproductive isolation observed in previous studies involving four populations of the matrotrophic least killifish, Heterandria formosa. Minimum sire number reconstructions suggested that two populations characterized by low densities had lower levels of concurrent multiple paternity than two populations characterized by high densities. However, low levels of genetic variation in the low-density populations greatly reduced our probability of detecting multiple mating in them. Once we took the lower level of genetic variation into account in our estimations, high levels of multiple paternity appeared the rule in all four populations. In the population where we had the greatest power of detecting multiple mating, we found that multiple paternity almost always involved multiple sires per brood and that paternity was often skewed towards one sire. Our results suggest that differences among H. formosa populations in levels of multiple paternity are not sufficient to explain the reproductive isolation seen in previous studies. We suggest that other influences on maternal-fetal conflict may contribute to the pattern of reproductive isolation observed previously. Alternatively, the asymmetric reproductive isolation seen in previous studies might reflect the disruption of maternal-fetal coadaptation.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.p21g8/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.p21g8/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.p21g8/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34498","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34498","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05264.x","PMID:21917044"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.p21g8"}}