{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-07T14:37:36Z","author":["Landis, Michael J.","Liang, Mason","Schraiber, Joshua G."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenetic analysis using Lévy processes: finding jumps in the evolution of continuous traits","host":"Landis MJ, Schraiber JG, Liang M (2012) Phylogenetic analysis using Lévy processes: finding jumps in the evolution of continuous traits. Systematic Biology 62(2): 193-204.","keywords":["saltational evolution","Bayesian inference","continuous trait evolution","Lévy processes"],"description":"Gaussian processes, a class of stochastic processes including Brownian motion and the Ornstein–Uhlenbeck process, are widely used to model continuous trait evolution in statistical phylogenetics. Under such processes, observations at the tips of a phylogenetic tree have a multivariate Gaussian distribution, which may lead to suboptimal model specification under certain evolutionary conditions, as supposed in models of punctuated equilibrium or adaptive radiation. To consider non-normally distributed continuous trait evolution, we introduce a method to compute posterior probabilities when modeling continuous trait evolution as a Lévy process. Through data simulation and model testing, we establish that single-rate Brownian motion (BM) and Lévy processes with jumps generate distinct patterns in comparative data. We then analyzed body mass and endocranial volume measurements for 126 primates. We rejected single-rate BM in favor of a Lévy process with jumps for each trait, with the lineage leading to most recent common ancestor of great apes showing particularly strong evidence against single-rate BM.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.0n761/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.0n761/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.0n761/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.0n761/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.0n761/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40591","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40591","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23034385","doi:10.1093/sysbio/sys086"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.0n761"}}