{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-17T16:11:46Z","author":["Henriksen, Marius","Creaby, Mark W.","Christensen, Robin","Lund, Hans","Juhl, Carsten"],"title":"Data from: Is there a causal link between knee loading and knee osteoarthritis progression? A systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies and randomised trials","host":"Henriksen M, Creaby MW, Lund H, Juhl C, Christensen R (2014) Is there a causal link between knee loading and knee osteoarthritis progression? A systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies and randomised trials. BMJ Open 4(7): e005368.","keywords":["RHEUMATOLOGY","STATISTICS & RESEARCH METHODS","EPIDEMIOLOGY","Knee"],"description":"Objective: We performed a systematic review, meta-analysis and assessed the evidence supporting a causal link between knee joint loading during walking and structural knee osteoarthritis (OA) progression. Design: Systematic review, meta-analysis and application of Bradford Hill's considerations on causation. Data sources: We searched MEDLINE, Scopus, AMED, CINAHL and SportsDiscus for prospective cohort studies and randomised controlled trials (RCTs) from 1950 through October 2013. Study eligibility criteria: We selected cohort studies and RCTs in which estimates of knee joint loading during walking were used to predict structural knee OA progression assessed by X-ray or MRI. Data analyses: Meta-analysis was performed to estimate the combined OR for structural disease progression with higher baseline loading. The likelihood of a causal link between knee joint loading and OA progression was assessed from cohort studies using the Bradford Hill guidelines to derive a 0–4 causation score based on four criteria and examined for confirmation in RCTs. Results: Of the 1078 potentially eligible articles, 5 prospective cohort studies were included. The studies included a total of 452 patients relating joint loading to disease progression over 12–72 months. There were very serious limitations associated with the methodological quality of the included studies. The combined OR for disease progression was 1.90 (95% CI 0.85 to 4.25; I2=77%) for each one-unit increment in baseline knee loading. The combined causation score was 0, indicating no causal association between knee loading and knee OA progression. No RCTs were found to confirm or refute the findings from the cohort studies. Conclusions: There is very limited and low-quality evidence to support for a causal link between knee joint loading during walking and structural progression of knee OA","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b40hm/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66672","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66672","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25031196","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-005368"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b40hm"}}