{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-21T13:54:54Z","author":["Dai, Can","Galloway, Laura F."],"title":"Data from: Sexual selection in a hermaphroditic plant through female reproductive success","host":"Dai C, Galloway LF (2013) Sexual selection in a hermaphroditic plant through female reproductive success. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 26(12): 2622–2632.","keywords":["experimental manipulation","phenotypic selection","path analysis","pollinator-mediated selection","Natural selection","structural equation model","Bateman gradient"],"description":"Sexual selection is well accepted as a mechanism of shaping traits in animals. However, whether and how floral traits are sexually selected in hermaphroditic plants remains less clear. Here, we use Passiflora incarnata to address how floral traits that affect pollination success are selected via female function. We manipulated the ecological context by limiting pollination and adding resources to expand the phenotypic distribution and alter the intensity of sexual selection. Total sexual selection favoured lower style deflexion because of its impact on pollen receipt and subsequent seed number. However, total selection on style deflexion was not significant, indicating additional selection on style deflexion through routes other than mating. Limited pollination and enhanced resources were expected to alter the distribution of pollen deposition and seed production and therefore intensify the Bateman gradient – the relationship between pollen receipt and seed production. Indeed, the Bateman gradient was strongest when pollination was limited, suggesting potential for sexual selection to influence floral trait evolution under these conditions. Overall, we found floral traits may be shaped by sexual selection through female reproductive success in this hermaphroditic plant. These results support manipulations to enhance the variance in mating as a mechanism to understand patterns of sexual selection.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s1q0h/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53615","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53615","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/jeb.12254","PMID:24118274"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s1q0h"}}