{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["Molecular Ecology","0962-1083"],"keywords":["Speciation","Population Genetics - Empirical","Systematics","Insects","Hybridization"],"host":"Dyer NA, Furtado A, Cano J, Ferreira F, Afonso MO, Ndong-Mabale N, Ndong-Asumu P, Centeno-Lima S, Benito A, Weetman D, Donnelly MJ, Pinto J (2009) Evidence for a discrete evolutionary lineage within Equatorial Guinea suggests that the tsetse fly Glossina palpalis palpalis exists as a species complex. Molecular Ecology 18: 3268-3282.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.1358/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.1358/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.1358","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-01T19:58:14Z","author":["Pinto, Joao","Afonso, M. Odete","Cano, Jorge","Benito, Agustín","Ndong-Asumu, Pedro","Ferreira, Filipa","Weetman, David","Donnelly, Martin","Centeno-Lima, Sonia","Ndong-Mabale, Nicolas","Dyer, Naomi","Furtado, Andreia"],"title":"Data from: Evidence for a discrete evolutionary lineage within Equatorial Guinea suggests that the tsetse fly Glossina palpalis palpalis exists as a species complex","description":"Tsetse flies of the palpalis group are major vectors of Human African Trypanosomiasis in Africa. Accurate knowledge of species identity is essential for vector control. Here we combine ribosomal internal transcribed spacer 1 (ITS1), mitochondrial Cytochrome Oxidase 1 (COI) and microsatellites to determine the population structure and phylogenetic relations of G. p. palpalis in Equatorial Guinea. COI sequence data suggest that G. p. palpalis in Equatorial Guinea are a distinct subspecies from previously described G. p. palpalis in West Africa and Democratic Republic of Congo. G. p. palpalis in Equatorial Guinea and DRC share a common ancestor which diverged from West African G. p. palpalis around 1.9 million years ago. Previous ITS1 length polymorphism data suggested the possible presence of hybrids in Equatorial Guinea. However, ITS1 showed incomplete lineage sorting compared to clearly defined COI groups, and data from twelve unlinked microsatellites provided no evidence of hybridization. Microsatellite data indicated moderate but significant differentiation between the populations analysed (Rio Campo, Mbini and Kogo). Moreover, unlike previous studies of G. p. palpalis, there was no evidence for heterozygote deficiency, presence of migrants, or cryptic population structure. Variance effective population size at Rio Campo was estimated at 501 to 731 assuming 8 generations/year. This study of the population genetics of G. p. palpalis in central Africa provides the first estimate of genetic differentiation between geographically separated G. p. palpalis populations.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.1358","isReferencedBy":["PMID:19619197","doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04265.x"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1358"}}