{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-19T17:17:31Z","author":["Illera, Juan Carlos","Laiolo, Paola","Obeso, Jose Ramon","Segura, Amalia","Melendez, Leandro"],"title":"Data from: Abiotic, biotic and evolutionary control of the distribution of C and N isotopes in food webs","keywords":["Bird","Grasslands","Phylogenetics: comparative","Environmental variability","Ecology: community","Plant","Ecology: ecosystem","Invertebrates","Nutrient cycles"],"description":"Ecosystem functioning depends on nutrient cycles and their responses to abiotic and biotic determinants, with the influence of evolutionary legacies being generally overlooked in ecosystem ecology. Along a broad elevation gradient characterized by shifting climatic and grazing environments, we addressed clines of plant N and C:N content, and of δ 13C and δ 15N in producers (herbs), and primary (grasshoppers) and secondary consumers (birds), within and between species in phylogenetically controlled scenarios. We found parallel and significant intra- and interspecific trends of isotopic variation with elevation in the three groups. In primary producers, nutrient and isotope distributions had a detectable phylogenetic signal that constrained their variation along the environmental gradient. The influence of the environment could not be ascribed to any single factor and both grazing and climate had an effect on leaf stoichiometry and thus on the resources available to consumers. Trends in consumers matched those of plants but often became non-significant after controlling for isotopic values of their direct resources, revealing direct bottom-up control and little phylogenetic dependence. By integrating ecosystem and mechanistic perspectives, we found that nutrient dynamics in food webs are governed at the base by the complex interaction of local determinants and evolutionary factors. 19 pages, 3 tables, 2 figures; Supplement","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g4p92/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.71105","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.71105","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g4p92"}}