{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"4;11;2004","keywords":["Phylogeny","Diversification","Armadillos","Molecular dating","Supermatrix","Anteaters","Sloths","Xenarthrans"],"host":"Delsuc F, Vizcaíno SF, Douzery EJP (2004) Influence of Tertiary paleoenvironmental changes on the diversification of South American mammals: a relaxed molecular clock study within xenarthrans. BMC Evolutionary Biology 4:11.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8518/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.8518/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.8518/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8518/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.8518/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.8518/5"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8518","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-09-02T19:37:56Z","author":["Douzery, Emmanuel J. P.","Delsuc, Frédéric","Vizcaíno, Sergio F."],"title":"Data from: Influence of Tertiary paleoenvironmental changes on the diversification of South American mammals: a relaxed molecular clock study within xenarthrans.","description":"BACKGROUND: Comparative genomic data among organisms allow the reconstruction of their phylogenies and evolutionary time scales. Molecular timings have been recently used to suggest that environmental global change have shaped the evolutionary history of diverse terrestrial organisms. Living xenarthrans (armadillos, anteaters and sloths) constitute an ideal model for studying the influence of past environmental changes on species diversification. Indeed, extant xenarthran species are relicts from an evolutionary radiation enhanced by their isolation in South America during the Tertiary era, a period for which major climate variations and tectonic events are relatively well documented.\n\nRESULTS: We applied a Bayesian approach to three nuclear genes in order to relax the molecular clock assumption while accounting for differences in evolutionary dynamics among genes and incorporating paleontological uncertainties. We obtained a molecular time scale for the evolution of extant xenarthrans and other placental mammals. Divergence time estimates provide substantial evidence for contemporaneous diversification events among independent xenarthran lineages. This correlated pattern of diversification might possibly relate to major environmental changes that occurred in South America during the Cenozoic.\n\nCONCLUSIONS: The observed synchronicity between planetary and biological events suggests that global change played a crucial role in shaping the evolutionary history of extant xenarthrans. Our findings open ways to test this hypothesis further in other South American mammalian endemics like hystricognath rodents, platyrrhine primates, and didelphid marsupials.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8518","isReferencedBy":["PMID:15115541","doi:10.1186/1471-2148-4-11"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8518"}}