{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-17T17:48:49Z","author":["Farkas, Timothy E.","Soria-Carrasco, Víctor","Buerkle, C. Alex","Comeault, Aaron Arthur","Gompert, Zach","Parchman, Thomas L.","Nosil, Patrik"],"title":"Data from: Genome-wide association mapping of phenotypic traits subject to a range of intensities of natural selection in Timema cristinae","host":"Comeault AA, Soria-Carrasco V, Gompert Z, Farkas TE, Buerkle CA, Parchman TL, Nosil P (2014) Genome-wide association mapping of phenotypic traits subject to a range of intensities of natural selection in Timema cristinae.The American Naturalist 183(5): 711-727.","keywords":["stick-insect","genetics","GWAS","natural selection","adaptation"],"description":"The genetic architecture of adaptive traits can reflect the evolutionary history of populations and also shape divergence among populations. Despite this central role in evolution, relatively little is known regarding the genetic architecture of adaptive traits in nature, particularly for traits subject to known selection intensities. Here we quantitatively describe the genetic architecture of traits that are subject to known intensities of differential selection between host plant species in Timema cristinae stick insects. Specifically, we used phenotypic measurements of 10 traits and 211,004 single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) to conduct multilocus genome-wide association mapping. We identified a modest number of SNPs that were associated with traits and sometimes explained a large proportion of trait variation. These SNPs varied in their strength of association with traits, and both major and minor effect loci were discovered. However, we found no relationship between variation in levels of divergence among traits in nature and variation in parameters describing the genetic architecture of those same traits. Our results provide a first step toward identifying loci underlying adaptation in T. cristinae. Future studies will examine the genomic location, population differentiation, and response to selection of the trait-associated SNPs described here.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.ck2cm/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.ck2cm/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.ck2cm/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.ck2cm/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54680","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54680","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/675497","PMID:24739202"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ck2cm"}}