{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-09T13:41:47Z","author":["Schmid-Hempel, Paul","Brown, Mark J. F.","Moret, Yannick","Reber-Funk, Christine","Bryden, John","Ruiz-González, Mario Xavier"],"title":"Data from: Dynamic transmission, host quality and population structure in a multi-host parasite of bumble bees","host":"Ruiz-González MX, Bryden J, Moret Y, Reber-Funk C, Schmid-Hempel P, Brown MJF (2012) Dynamic transmission, host quality and population structure in a multi-host parasite of bumble bees. Evolution 66(10): 3052-3066.","keywords":["population genetics","immune defence","transmission"],"description":"The evolutionary ecology of multi-host parasites is predicted to depend upon patterns of host quality and the dynamics of transmission networks. Depending upon the differences in host quality and transmission asymmetries, as well as the balance between intra- and inter-specific transmission, the evolution of specialist or generalist strategies is predicted. Using a trypanosome parasite of bumble bees we ask how host quality and transmission networks relate to parasite population structure across host species, and thus the potential for the evolution of specialist strains adapted to different host species. Host species differed in quality, with parasite growth varying across host species. Highly asymmetric transmission networks, together with differences in host quality, likely explain local population structure of the parasite across host species. However, parasite population structure across years was highly dynamic, with parasite populations varying significantly from one year to the next within individual species at a given site. This suggests that, whilst host quality and transmission may provide the opportunity for short-term host specialisation by the parasite, repeated bottlenecking of the parasite, in combination with its own reproductive biology, overrides these smaller scale effects, resulting in the evolution of a generalist parasite.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.q4f09sr3/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.q4f09sr3/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.q4f09sr3/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38736","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38736","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23025597","doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01655.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.q4f09sr3"}}