{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-15T17:17:39Z","author":["Williams, Tony D.","Stein, Robert William"],"title":"Data from: Extreme intraclutch egg-size dimorphism in Eudyptes penguins, an evolutionary response to clutch-size maladaptation","host":"Stein RW, Williams TD (2013) Extreme intraclutch egg-size dimorphism in Eudyptes penguins, an evolutionary response to clutch-size maladaptation. The American Naturalist 182(2): 260-270.","keywords":["Bird","Phylogenetics: comparative","Reproduction: costs","Life history: evolution","Ecology: evolutionary"],"description":"Eudyptes penguins (six species) are uniquely characterized by a two-egg clutch with extreme intraclutch egg-size dimorphism (ESD): the first-laid A-egg is 17.5%–56.9% smaller than the B-egg. Although A-eggs are viable, they almost never produce fledged chicks (genus average <1%). Using classical life-history theory and phylogenetic comparative methods, we demonstrate a marked slowdown in the life history of Eudyptes: age of first reproduction is 52% later and annual fecundity 48% lower compared with other two-egg clutch penguin species. All six Eudyptes species have retained a two-egg clutch, despite this pronounced life-history slowdown; this suggests evolutionary mismatch between clutch size and chicks fledged per clutch. Consistent with this, we show that Eudyptes fledge 43% fewer chicks per clutch than other two-egg clutch penguin species. Extreme intraclutch ESD in Eudyptes is associated primarily with a uniform (5%) increase in relative B-egg size, and B-egg size has evolved in accord with life history. We further show that intraclutch ESD is positively correlated with age of first reproduction in Eudyptes but not in other two-egg clutch penguin species. We argue that Eudyptes’ persistent failure to evolve a one-egg clutch constitutes a unique genus-wide evolutionary maladaptation and that extreme intraclutch ESD evolved as a correlated response to selection favoring a slower life history imposed by their extreme pelagic overwintering and migration ecology.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cd233/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47639","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47639","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/670929","PMID:23852359"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cd233"}}