{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-16T19:40:14Z","author":["Zieliński, Piotr","Liana, Marcin","Babik, Wiesław","Dudek, Katarzyna","Stuglik, Michał T."],"title":"Data from: Single nucleotide polymorphisms reveal genetic structuring of the Carpathian newt and provide evidence of interspecific gene flow in the nuclear genome","host":"Zieliński P, Dudek K, Stuglik MT, Liana M, Babik W (2014) Single nucleotide polymorphisms reveal genetic structuring of the Carpathian newt and provide evidence of interspecific gene flow in the nuclear genome. PLoS ONE 9(5): e97431.","keywords":["introgression","gene flow","refugia","admixture","genetic structure"],"description":"Genetic variation within species is commonly structured in a hierarchical manner which may result from superimposition of processes acting at different spatial and temporal scales. In organisms of limited dispersal ability, signatures of past subdivision are detectable for a long time. Studies of contemporary genetic structure in such taxa inform about the history of isolation, range changes and local admixture resulting from geographically restricted hybridization with related species. Here we use a set of 139 transcriptome-derived, unlinked nuclear single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) to assess the genetic structure of the Carpathian newt (Lissotriton montandoni, Lm) and introgression from its congener, the smooth newt (L. vulgaris, Lv). Two substantially differentiated groups of Lm populations likely originated from separate refugia, both located in the Eastern Carpathians. The colonization of the present range in north-western and south-western directions was accompanied by a modest loss of variation; admixture between the two groups has occurred in the middle of the Eastern Carpathians. Local, apparently recent introgression of Lv alleles into several Lm populations was detected, demonstrating increased power for admixture detection in comparison to a previous study based on a limited number of microsatellite markers. The level of introgression was higher in Lm populations classified as admixed than in syntopic populations. We discuss the possible causes and propose further tests to distinguish between alternatives. Several outlier loci were identified in tests of interspecific differentiation, suggesting genomic heterogeneity of gene flow between species.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.211ck/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.63239","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.63239","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24820116","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0097431"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.211ck"}}