{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-11T20:33:27Z","author":["Praz, Christophe","Baur, Hannes","Guex, Gaston-Denis","Neumeyer, Rainer"],"title":"Data from: A new species of the paper wasp genus Polistes (Hymenoptera, Vespidae, Polistinae) in Europe revealed by morphometrics and molecular analyses","host":"Neumeyer R, Baur H, Guex G, Praz C (2014) A new species of the paper wasp genus Polistes (Hymenoptera, Vespidae, Polistinae) in Europe revealed by morphometrics and molecular analyses. ZooKeys 400(2014): 67-118.","keywords":["allometry","measurements","character definition","definition","ratio spectrum","shape PCA","LDA ratio extractor","linear discriminant analysis","raw data"],"description":"We combine multivariate ratio analysis (MRA) of body measurements and analyses of mitochondrial and nuclear data to examine the status of several species of European paper wasps (Polistes Latreille, 1802) closely related to P. gallicus. Our analyses unambiguously reveal the presence of a cryptic species in Europe, as two distinct species can be recognized in what has hitherto been considered Polistes bischoffi Weyrauch, 1937. One species is almost as light coloured as P. gallicus, and is mainly recorded from Southern Europe and Western Asia. The other species is darker and has a more northern distribution in Central Europe. Both species occur syntopically in Switzerland. Given that the lost lectotype of P. bischoffi originated from Sardinia, we selected a female of the southern species as a neotype. The northern species is described as P. helveticus sp. n. here. We also provide a redescription of P. bischoffi rev. stat. and an identification key including three more closely related species, P. biglumis, P. gallicus and P. hellenicus.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9b8tt/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61160","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61160","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24843256","doi:10.3897/zookeys.400.6611"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9b8tt"}}