{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-12T15:06:33Z","author":["Winker, Kevin","McCormack, John E.","Faircloth, Brant C.","Brumfield, Robb T.","Glenn, Travis C.","Crawford, Nicholas G."],"title":"Data from: More than 1000 ultraconserved elements provide evidence that turtles are the sister group of archosaurs","host":"Crawford NG, Faircloth BC, McCormack JE, Brumfield RT, Winker K, Glenn TC (2012) More than 1000 ultraconserved elements provide evidence that turtles are the sister group of archosaurs. Biology Letters 8(5): 783-786.","keywords":["reptiles","phylogenomic","ultraconserved elements","turtles","phylogenetics","archosaurs","evolution"],"description":"We present the first genomic-scale analysis addressing the phylogenetic position of turtles, using over 1,000 loci from representatives of all major reptile lineages including tuatara. Previously, studies of morphological traits positioned turtles either at the base of the reptile tree or with lizards, snakes, and tuatara (lepidosaurs), whereas molecular analyses typically allied turtles with crocodiles and birds (archosaurs). A recent analysis of shared microRNA families found that turtles are more closely related to lepidosaurs. To test this hypothesis with data from many single-copy nuclear loci dispersed throughout the genome, we used sequence capture, high-throughput sequencing and published genomes to obtain sequences from 1,145 ultraconserved elements (UCEs) and their variable flanking DNA. The resulting phylogeny provides overwhelming support for the hypothesis that turtles evolved from a common ancestor of birds and crocodilians, rejecting the hypothesized relationship between turtles and lepidosaurs.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/20","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/22","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38214","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38214","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rsbl.2012.0331","PMID:22593086"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.75nv22qj"}}