{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-05T18:45:28Z","author":["Leppälä, Johanna","Savolainen, Outi","Leinonen, Päivi H.","Remington, David L."],"title":"Data from: Complex genetic effects on early vegetative development shape resource allocation differences between Arabidopsis lyrata populations","host":"Remington DL, Leinonen PH, Leppälä J, Savolainen O (2013) Complex genetic effects on early vegetative development shape resource allocation differences between Arabidopsis lyrata populations. Genetics 195(3): 1087-1102.","keywords":["trait network","resource allocation","pleiotropy","quantitative trait locus","structural equation model"],"description":"Costs of reproduction due to resource allocation trade-offs have long been recognized as key forces in life history evolution, but little is known about their functional or genetic basis.  Arabidopsis lyrata, a perennial relative of the annual model plant A. thaliana with a wide climatic distribution, has populations that are strongly diverged in resource allocation.  In this study, we evaluated the genetic and functional basis for variation in resource allocation in a reciprocal transplant experiment, using four A. lyrata populations and F2 progeny from a cross between North Carolina (USA) and Norway parents, which had the most divergent resource allocation patterns.  Local alleles at quantitative trait loci (QTL) at a North Carolina field site increased reproductive output while reducing vegetative growth. These QTL had little overlap with flowering date QTL.  Structural equation models incorporating QTL genotypes and traits indicated that resource allocation differences result primarily from QTL effects on early vegetative growth patterns, with cascading effects on later vegetative and reproductive development.  At a Norway field site, North Carolina alleles at some of the same QTL regions reduced survival and reproductive output components, but these effects were not associated with resource allocation trade-offs in the Norway environment.  Our results indicate that resource allocation in perennial plants may involve important adaptive mechanisms largely independent of flowering time.  Moreover, the contributions of resource allocation QTL to local adaptation appear to result from their effects on developmental timing and its interaction with environmental constraints, and not from simple models of reproductive costs.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.52942","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.52942","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1534/genetics.113.151803","PMID:23979581"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1k4gq"}}