{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-15T17:42:24Z","author":["Köblitz, Louise","Bernier, Nicholas J.","Wright, Patricia A.","Robertson, Cayleih E."],"title":"Data from: Hypoxia-inducible factor-1 mediates adaptive developmental plasticity of hypoxia tolerance in zebrafish, Danio rerio","host":"Robertson CE, Wright PA, Köblitz L, Bernier NJ (2014) Hypoxia-inducible factor-1 mediates adaptive developmental plasticity of hypoxia tolerance in zebrafish, Danio rerio. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1768): 20140637.","keywords":["hypoxia tolerance","developmental plasticity","HIF-1cellular pathway","sex ratio bias","zebrafish"],"description":"In recent years, natural and anthropogenic factors have increased aquatic hypoxia the world over. In most organisms, the cellular response to hypoxia is mediated by the master regulator hypoxia-inducible factor-1 (HIF-1). HIF-1 also plays a critical role in the normal development of the cardiovascular system of vertebrates. We tested the hypothesis that hypoxia exposures which resulted in HIF-1 induction during embryogenesis would be associated with enhanced hypoxia tolerance in subsequent developmental stages. We exposed zebrafish (Danio rerio) embryos to just 4 h of severe hypoxia or total anoxia at 18, 24 and 36 h post-fertilization (hpf). Of these, exposure to hypoxia at 24 and 36 hpf as well as anoxia at 36 hpf activated the HIF-1 cellular pathway. Zebrafish embryos that acutely upregulated the HIF-1 pathway had an increased hypoxia tolerance as larvae. The critical window for hypoxia sensitivity and HIF-1 signalling was 24 hpf. Adult male fish had a lower critical oxygen tension (Pcrit) compared with females. Early induction of HIF-1 correlated directly with an increased proportion of males in the population. We conclude that mounting a HIF-1 response during embryogenesis is associated with long-term impacts on the phenotype of later stages which could influence both individual hypoxia tolerance and population dynamics.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.3ks4h/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.3ks4h/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.62789","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.62789","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.0637","PMID:24850928"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3ks4h"}}