{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-03-05T15:23:16Z","author":["Uriarte, Maria","Inouye, Brian D.","Bruna, Emilio M.","Izzo, Thiago J.","Vasconcelos, Heraldo L."],"title":"Data from: Asymmetric dispersal and colonization success of Amazonian plant-ants queens","host":"Bruna EM, Izzo TJ, Inouye BD, Uriarte M, Vasconcelos HL (2011) Asymmetric dispersal and colonization success of Amazonian plant-ants queens. PLoS ONE 6(8): e22937.","keywords":["dispersal kernel","myrmecophyte","dispersal","inverse modeling"],"description":"Background: The dispersal ability of queens is central to understanding ant life-history evolution, and plays a fundamental role in ant population and community dynamics, the maintenance of genetic diversity, and the spread of invasive ants. In tropical ecosystems, species from over 40 genera of ants establish colonies in the stems, hollow thorns, or leaf pouches of specialized plants. However, little is known about the relative dispersal ability of queens competing for access to the same host plants. Methodology/Principal Findings: We used empirical data and inverse modeling – a technique developed by plant ecologists to model seed dispersal – to quantify and compare the dispersal kernels of queens from three Amazonian ant species that compete for access to host-plants. We found that the modal colonization distance of queens varied 8-fold, with the generalist ant species (Crematogaster laevis) having a greater modal distance than two specialists (Pheidole minutula, Azteca sp.) that use the same host-plants. However, our results also suggest that queens of Azteca sp. have maximal distances that are four-sixteen times greater than those of its competitors. Conclusions/Significance: We found large differences between ant species in both the modal and maximal distance ant queens disperse to find vacant seedlings used to found new colonies. These differences could result from interspecific differences in queen body size, and hence wing musculature, or because queens differ in their ability to identify potential host plants while in flight. Our results provide support for one of the necessary conditions underlying several of the hypothesized mechanisms promoting coexistence in tropical plant-ants. They also suggest that for some ant species, limited dispersal capability could pose a significant barrier to the rescue of populations in isolated forest fragments. Finally, we demonstrate that inverse models parameterized with field data are an excellent means of quantifying the dispersal of ant queens.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.h6t7g/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6t7g/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6t7g/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34342","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34342","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21826219","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0022937"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h6t7g"}}