{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-01-15T17:39:03Z","author":["Krompass, Denis","Aberer, Andre J.","Stamatakis, Alexandros"],"title":"Data from: Pruning rogue taxa improves phylogenetic accuracy: an efficient algorithm and webservice","host":"Aberer AJ, Krompass D, Stamatakis A (2012) Pruning rogue taxa improves phylogenetic accuracy: an efficient algorithm and webservice. Systematic Biology 62(1): 162-166.","keywords":["consensus tree","software","rogue taxa","phylogenetic post-analysis","bootstrap support","webservice"],"description":"The presence of rogue taxa (rogues) in a set of trees can frequently have a negative impact on the results of a bootstrap analysis (e.g., the overall support in consensus trees). We introduce an efficient graph-based algorithm for rogue taxon identification as well as an interactive web-service implementing this algorithm. Compared to our previous method, the new algorithm is up to four orders of magnitude faster, while returning qualitatively identical results. Because of this significant improvement in scalability, the new algorithm can now identify substantially more complex and compute-intensive rogue taxon constellations. On a large and diverse collection of real-world datasets, we show that, our method yields better supported reduced/pruned consensus trees than any competing rogue taxon identification method. Using the parallel version of our open-source code, we successfully identified rogue taxa in a set of 100 trees with 116,334 taxa each. Using simulated datasets we show that, when removing/pruning rogue taxa with our method from a tree set, we consistently obtain bootstrap consensus trees as well as maximum likelihood trees that are topologically closer to the respective true trees.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.sv515/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.sv515/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.39931","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.39931","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22962004","doi:10.1093/sysbio/sys078"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sv515"}}