{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-24T18:20:32Z","author":["Zhao, Xiangyu","Zhou, Wengang","Thatcher, Shawn R.","Wang, Bing-Bing","Baumgarten, Andy","Li, Bailin","Beatty, Mary","Leonard, April","Zastrow-Hayes, Gina"],"title":"Data from: Genome-wide analysis of alternative splicing in Zea mays: landscape and genetic regulation","host":"Thatcher SR, Zhou W, Leonard A, Wang B, Beatty M, Zastrow-Hayes G, Zhao X, Baumgarten A, Li B (2014) Genome-wide analysis of alternative splicing in Zea mays: landscape and genetic regulation. The Plant Cell, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Splicing","Isoform","Transcriptome","Maize"],"description":"Alternative splicing enhances transcriptome diversity in all eukaryotes and plays a role in plant tissue identity and stress adaptation. To catalog new maize (Zea mays) transcripts and identify genomic loci that regulate alternative splicing, we analyzed over 90 RNA-seq libraries from maize inbred lines B73 and Mo17, as well as Syn10 doubled haploid lines (progenies from B73 × Mo17). Transcript discovery was augmented with publicly available data from 14 maize tissues, expanding the maize transcriptome by more than 30,000 and increasing the percentage of intron-containing genes that undergo alternative splicing to 40%. These newly identified transcripts greatly increase the diversity of the maize proteome, sometimes coding for entirely different proteins compared with their most similar annotated isoform. In addition to increasing proteome diversity, many genes encoding novel transcripts gained an additional layer of regulation by microRNAs, often in a tissue-specific manner. We also demonstrate that the majority of genotype-specific alternative splicing can be genetically mapped, with cis-acting quantitative trait loci (QTLs) predominating. A large number of trans-acting QTLs were also apparent, with nearly half located in regions not shown to contain genes associated with splicing. Taken together, these results highlight the currently underappreciated role that alternative splicing plays in tissue identity and genotypic variation in maize.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70063","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70063","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25248552","doi:10.1105/tpc.114.130773"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g3v15"}}