{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-11-06T15:41:54Z","author":["Hunter, Mark D.","Li, James","Sternberg, Eleanore D.","LeFèvre, Thierry","de Roode, Jacobus C.","Li, Hui","Lopez Fernandez de Castillejo, Carlos"],"title":"Data from: Food plant-derived disease tolerance and resistance in a natural butterfly-plant-parasite interaction","host":"Sternberg ED, LeFèvre T, Li J, Lopez Fernandez de Castillejo C, Li H, Hunter MD, de Roode JC (2012) Food plant-derived disease tolerance and resistance in a natural butterfly-plant-parasite interaction. Evolution 66(11): 3367–3376.","keywords":["monarch butterfly","host-parasite interactions","milkweed","tolerance","resistance"],"description":"Organisms can protect themselves against parasite-induced fitness costs through resistance or tolerance. Resistance includes mechanisms that prevent infection or limit parasite growth while tolerance alleviates the fitness costs from parasitism without limiting infection. Although tolerance and resistance affect host-parasite coevolution in fundamentally different ways, tolerance has often been ignored in animal-parasite systems. Where it has been studied, tolerance has been assumed to be a genetic mechanism, unaffected by the host environment. Here we studied the effects of host ecology on tolerance and resistance to infection by rearing monarch butterflies on twelve different species of milkweed food plants and infecting them with a naturally occurring protozoan parasite. Our results show that monarch butterflies experience different levels of tolerance to parasitism depending on the species of milkweed that they feed on, with some species providing over two-fold greater tolerance than other milkweed species. Resistance was also affected by milkweed species, but there was no relationship between milkweed-conferred resistance and tolerance. Chemical analysis suggests that infected monarchs obtain highest fitness when reared on milkweeds with an intermediate concentration, diversity and polarity of toxic secondary plant chemicals known as cardenolides. Our results demonstrate that environmental factors – such as interacting species in ecological food webs – are important drivers of disease tolerance.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.82j66/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.82j66/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.39374","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.39374","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23106703","doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01693.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.82j66"}}