{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-14T15:17:13Z","author":["Cole, Ella F.","Quinn, John L."],"title":"Data from: Shy birds play it safe: personality in captivity predicts risk responsiveness during reproduction in the wild","host":"Cole EF, Quinn JL (2014) Shy birds play it safe: personality in captivity predicts risk responsiveness during reproduction in the wild. Biology Letters 10(5): 20140178.","keywords":["great tit","neophobia","life-history strategies","personality","exploration"],"description":"Despite a growing body of evidence linking personality to life-history variation and fitness, the behavioural mechanisms underlying these relationships remain poorly understood. One mechanism thought to play a key role is how individuals respond to risk. Relatively reactive and proactive (or shy and bold) personality types are expected to differ in how they manage the inherent trade-off between productivity and survival, with bold individuals being more risk-prone with lower survival probability, and shy individuals adopting a more risk-averse strategy. In the great tit (Parus major), the shy–bold personality axis has been well characterized in captivity and linked to fitness. Here, we tested whether ‘exploration behaviour’, a captive assay of the shy–bold axis, can predict risk responsiveness during reproduction in wild great tits. Relatively slow-exploring (shy) females took longer than fast-exploring (bold) birds to resume incubation after a novel object, representing an unknown threat, was attached to their nest-box, with some shy individuals not returning within the 40 min trial period. Risk responsiveness was consistent within individuals over days. These findings provide rare, field-based experimental evidence that shy individuals prioritize survival over reproductive investment, supporting the hypothesis that personality reflects life-history variation through links with risk responsiveness.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.58142/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.62983","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.62983","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24829251","doi:10.1098/rsbl.2014.0178"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.58142"}}