{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-18T17:01:52Z","author":["Kierepka, Elizabeth M.","Latch, Emily K."],"title":"Data from: Performance of partial statistics in individual-based landscape genetics","host":"Kierepka EM, Latch EK (2014) Performance of partial statistics in individual-based landscape genetics. Molecular Ecology Resources, online in advance of print.","keywords":["partial statistics","ordination","redundancy analysis","landscape genetics","Mantel test"],"description":"Individual-based landscape genetic methods have become increasingly popular for quantifying fine-scale landscape influences on gene flow. One complication for individual-based methods is that gene flow and landscape variables are often correlated with geography. Partial statistics, particularly Mantel tests, are often employed to control for these inherent correlations by removing the effects of geography while simultaneously correlating measures of genetic differentiation and landscape variables of interest. Concerns about the reliability of Mantel tests prompted this study, in which we use simulated landscapes to evaluate the performance of partial Mantel tests and two ordination methods, distance-based redundancy analysis (dbRDA) and redundancy analysis (RDA), for detecting isolation by distance (IBD) and isolation by landscape resistance (IBR). Specifically, we described the effects of suitable habitat amount, fragmentation, and resistance strength on metrics of accuracy (frequency of correct results, type I/II errors, and strength of IBR according to underlying landscape and resistance strength) for each test using realistic individual-based gene flow simulations. Mantel tests were very effective for detecting IBD, but exhibited higher error rates when detecting IBR. Ordination methods were overall more accurate in detecting IBR, but had high type I errors compared to partial Mantel tests. Thus, no one test outperformed another completely. A combination of statistical tests, for example partial Mantel tests to detect IBD paired with appropriate ordination techniques for IBR detection, provides the best characterization of fine-scale landscape genetic structure. Realistic simulations of empirical datasets will further increase power to distinguish among putative mechanisms of differentiation.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70272","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70272","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25230016","doi:10.1111/1755-0998.12332"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sc88q"}}