{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-03-23T15:22:05Z","author":["Jetz, Walter","Belmaker, Jonathan"],"title":"Data from: Regional pools and environmental controls of vertebrate richness","host":"Belmaker J, Jetz W (2012) Regional pools and environmental controls of vertebrate richness. The American Naturalist 179(4): 512-523.","keywords":["Macroecology","gradient diversity","Species diversity","Biodiversity","Vertebrates","Species richness"],"description":"The species richness of local communities depends on the richness of the regional pool and the filtering processes that preclude some regional species from occurring locally. These filters may include absolute attributes of the local environment and also how representative the local environment is of the surrounding region. The latter is consistent with a species sorting perspective, in which regional species only occupy the local habitats to which they are adapted. Here we evaluate the relative effects of local environmental conditions, environmental representativeness and environment-independent processes on the probability of local species occurrence, given their regional presence, of birds, mammals and amphibians worldwide. In multi-predictor models, environmental representativeness is a strong independent predictor of local species occurrence probability, with a relative contribution greater than that of absolute local environmental conditions. Further, we find that local occurrence probability diminishes with increased regional richness, independent of the local environment. This is consistent with reduced local occupancy in richer regions, a pattern which could stem from a largely neutral community assembly process. Our results support the importance of both environment-independent and species-sorting processes and suggest that regional richness and environmental representativeness should be jointly used for understanding richness gradients across scales.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cr5751br/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36449","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36449","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22437180","doi:10.1086/664610"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cr5751br"}}