{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-25T16:42:26Z","author":["Perrot-Minnot, Marie-Jeanne","Sanchez-Thirion, Kevin","Cézilly, Frank"],"title":"Data from: Multidimensionality in host manipulation mimicked by serotonin injection","keywords":["serotonin","parasite manipulation","Amphipod","multidimensionality","syndrome"],"description":"Manipulative parasites often alter the phenotype of their hosts along multiple dimensions. \"Multidimensionality\" in host manipulation could consist in the simultaneous alteration of several physiological pathways independently of one another, or proceed from the disruption of some key physiological parameter, followed by a cascade of effects. We compared multidimensionality in \"host-manipulation\" between two closely-related amphipod species, Gammarus fossarum and G. pulex, respectively naturally or experimentally infected with Pomphorhynchus laevis (Acanthocephala). To that end, we calculated in each host-parasite association the effect size of the difference between infected and uninfected individuals for six different traits (activity, phototaxis, geotaxis, attraction to conspecifics, refuge use, and metabolic rate). The effects sizes were highly correlated between host-parasite associations, providing evidence for a relatively constant \"infection syndrome\". Using the same methodology, we compared the extent of phenotypic alterations induced by an experimental injection of 5-HT in uninfected G. pulex to that induced by experimental infection with P. laevis. We observed a significant correlation between effect sizes across the six traits, indicating that injection with 5-HT can faithfully mimic the \"infection syndrome\". This is the first experimental evidence that multidimensionality in host-manipulation can proceed, at least partly, from the disruption of some major physiological mechanism.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.bs910/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70254","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70254","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.bs910"}}