{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-09-02T19:07:48Z","author":["Heinze, Jürgen","Walter, Bartosz Jerzy","Brunner, Elisabeth"],"title":"Data from: Policing effectiveness depends on relatedness and group size","host":"Walter BJ, Brunner E, Heinze J (2011) Policing effectiveness depends on relatedness and group size. The American Naturalist 177(3): 368-376.","keywords":["Evolution: social","Kin: conflict","Ecology: behavioral","Behavior: social","social","ants","Conflict","Behavior: reproductive","Behavior: dominance"],"description":"Cohesion of social groups requires the suppression of individual selfishness. Indeed, worker egg laying in insect societies is usually suppressed or punished \nthrough aggression and egg removal. The effectiveness of such \"policing\" is expected to increase with decreasing relatedness, as inclusive fitness of group members is \nmore strongly affected by selfish worker reproduction when group members are less closely related to each other. As inclusive fitness is also influenced by the costs and \nbenefits of helping, the effectiveness of policing should decrease with increasing colony size, because the costs for the whole colony from selfish worker reproduction \nare proportionally reduced in large groups. Here, we show that policing effectiveness in colonies of the ant Temnothorax unifasciatus is low in large groups and high in \nsmall groups when relatedness is high. When we experimentally decreased the relatedness in groups, the policing effectiveness reached the same high level as in small \nhighly related groups, irrespectively of group size. Therefore, our results indicate that policing effectiveness is simultaneously shaped by relatedness and group size, \ni.e. an ecological factor. This may have major implications for testing policing across species of animals.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8042/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.8042/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8042/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8042","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8042","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21460545","doi:10.1086/658396"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8042"}}