{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-10T13:07:12Z","author":["Michel, Andy P.","Wenger, Jacob A."],"title":"Data from: Implementing an evolutionary framework for understanding genetic relationships of phenotypically defined insect biotypes in the invasive soybean aphid (Aphis glycines)","host":"Wenger JA, Michel AP (2013) Implementing an evolutionary framework for understanding genetic relationships of phenotypically defined insect biotypes in the invasive soybean aphid (Aphis glycines). Evolutionary Applications 6(7): 1041–1053.","keywords":["Population Genetics - Empirical","soybean aphid","Adaptation","insect biotypes","plant resistance"],"description":"Adaptive evolution of pest insects in response to the introduction of resistant cultivars is well documented and commonly results in virulent (i.e. capable of feeding upon resistant cultivars) insect populations being labeled as distinct biotypes. Phenotypically defined, biotypes frequently remain evolutionarily indistinct, resulting in ineffective application of virulence control measures and shorter durability of resistant cultivars. Here we utilize an evolutionary framework to discern the genetic relationship between biotypes of the soybean aphid (Aphis glycines, Matsumura). The soybean aphid is invasive in North America, and is among the most destructive pests of commercial soybean on the continent. Attempts to breed host-plant resistant soybean have been hampered by the emergence of virulent aphid biotypes that are unaffected by the plant’s resistance mechanism(s). Comparative population genetic analysis of virulent and avirulent (i.e. unable to feed on resistant cultivars) biotypes found populations to be genetically indistinguishable across biotype and geographic distance, with high rates of inter-population immigration and admixture. The lack of genetic distinction between biotypes coupled with elevated genotypic diversity within all populations suggested virulence has a non-genetic based or includes a gene complex that is widely distributed throughout soybean aphid populations, which undergo regular dispersal and unimpeded sexual recombination.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.092fc/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.092fc/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.50383","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.50383","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24187586","doi:10.1111/eva.12084"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.092fc"}}