{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-23T17:13:45Z","author":["Eisen, Michael B.","MacManes, Matthew D."],"title":"Data from: Improving transcriptome assembly through error correction of high-throughput sequence reads","host":"MacManes MD, Eisen MB (2013) Improving transcriptome assembly through error correction of high-throughput sequence reads. PeerJ 1: e113.","description":"The study of functional genomics, particularly in non-model organisms, has been dramatically improved over the last few years by the use of transcriptomes and RNAseq. While these studies are potentially extremely powerful, a computationally intensive procedure, the de novo construction of a reference transcriptome must be completed as a prerequisite to further analyses. The accurate reference is critically important as all downstream steps, including estimating transcript abundance are critically dependent on the construction of an accurate reference. Though a substantial amount of research has been done on assembly, only recently have the pre-assembly procedures been studied in detail. Specifically, several stand-alone error correction modules have been reported on and, while they have shown to be effective in reducing errors at the level of sequencing reads, how error correction impacts assembly accuracy is largely unknown. Here, we show via use of a simulated and empiric dataset, that applying error correction to sequencing reads has significant positive effects on assembly accuracy, and should be applied to all datasets. A complete collection of commands which will allow for the production of Reptile corrected reads is available at https://github.com/macmanes/error_correction/tree/master/scripts","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.km540/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.km540/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51509","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51509","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.7717/peerj.113","PMID:23904992"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.km540"}}