{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Systematic Biology","keywords":["maximum likelihood","phylogeny","eutherian mammals","c-myc gene","DNA sequences"],"host":"Miyamoto MM, Porter CA, Goodman M (2000) c-Myc gene sequences and the phylogeny of bats and other eutherian mammals. Systematic Biology 49: 501-514.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.590/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.590","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-28T19:06:28Z","author":["Porter, Calvin A.","Miyamoto, Michael M.","Goodman, Morris"],"title":"Data from: c-Myc gene sequences and the phylogeny of bats and other eutherian mammals","description":"The complete protein-coding sequences of the c-myc proto-oncogene were determined for five species of four new orders of eutherian (placental) mammals. These newly obtained sequences were aligned to each other and to other available orthologues for the phylogenetic estimation of eutherian interordinal relationships. Several measures of sequence difference and base composition were first calculated to assess the major evolutionary properties of the three codon positions and two protein-coding exons of the gene. On the basis of these calculations, different parsimony, distance, and maximum likelihood approaches were adopted, with the most sophisticated involving the separate, then combined, likelihood analyses of the third codon positions of exon 2 vs. all other sites. These phylogenetic approaches provide clear support for the grouping of Chiroptera (bats) with Artiodactyla (ruminants, camels, and pigs) and Carnivora (cats, dogs, and their allies), an interordinal arrangement that receives strong corroboration from other lines of evidence including complete mitochondrial DNA sequences. In contrast, these analyses fail to provide strong to reasonable support for any other interordinal group. This study concludes with specific recommendations about sampling and other strategies for maximizing the phylogenetic contributions of the c-myc gene to the continued resolution of the eutherian ordinal tree.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.590","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1080/10635159950127367","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.590"}}