{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-30T18:54:35Z","author":["Allen, Eric E.","Ugalde, Juan A.","Espinoza, Carola","Ruiz-Tagle, Nathaly","Gallardo, Victor A.","Ferrada-Fuentes, Sandra","Gallardo, Maria J.","Belmar, Camila","Muñoz, Práxedes"],"title":"Data from: Microbial life in a fjord: metagenomic analysis of a microbial mat in Chilean Patagonia","host":"Ugalde JA, Gallardo MJ, Belmar C, Muñoz P, Ruiz-Tagle N, Ferrada-Fuentes S, Espinoza C, Allen EE, Gallardo VA (2013) Microbial life in a fjord: metagenomic analysis of a microbial mat in Chilean Patagonia. PLoS ONE 8(8): e71952.","keywords":["metagenomics","microbial mats"],"description":"The current study describes the taxonomic and functional composition of metagenomic sequences obtained from a filamentous microbial mat isolated from the Comau fjord, located in the northernmost part of the Chilean Patagonia. The taxonomic composition of the microbial community showed a high proportion of members of the Gammaproteobacteria, including a high number of sequences that were recruited to the genomes of Moritella marina MP-1 and Colwellia psycherythraea 34H, suggesting the presence of populations related to these two psychrophilic bacterial species. Functional analysis of the community indicated a high proportion of genes coding for the transport and metabolism of amino acids, as well as in energy production. Among the energy production functions, we found protein-coding genes for sulfate and nitrate reduction, both processes associated with Gammaproteobacteria-related sequences. This report provides the first examination of the taxonomic composition and genetic diversity associated with these conspicuous microbial mat communities and provides a framework for future microbial studies in the Comau fjord.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.pk8qv/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.pk8qv/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51925","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51925","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0071952","PMID:24015199"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pk8qv"}}