{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-14T20:09:40Z","author":["Monroe, Emy M.","Inoue, Kentaro","Berg, David J.","Elderkin, Curt L."],"title":"Data from: Phylogeographic and population genetic analyses reveal Pleistocene isolation followed by high gene flow in a wide- ranging, but endangered, freshwater mussel","host":"Inoue K, Monroe EM, Elderkin CL, Berg DJ (2014) Phylogeographic and population genetic analyses reveal Pleistocene isolation followed by high gene flow in a wide- ranging, but endangered, freshwater mussel. Heredity 112(3): 282-290.","keywords":["microsatellite","post-glacial dispersal","COI","spectaclecase","genetic diversity"],"description":"Freshwater organisms of North America have had their contemporary genetic structure shaped by vicariant events, especially Pleistocene glaciations. Life history traits promoting dispersal and gene flow continue to shape population genetic structure. Cumberlandia monodonta, a widespread but imperiled (IUCN listed as endangered) freshwater mussel, was examined to determine genetic diversity and population genetic structure range-wide. MtDNA sequences and microsatellite loci were used to measure genetic diversity and simulate demographic events during the Pleistocene using approximate Bayesian computation (ABC) to test explicit hypotheses explaining the evolutionary history of current populations. A phylogeny and molecular clock suggested past isolation created two mtDNA lineages during the Pleistocene that are now widespread. Two distinct groups were also detected with microsatellites. ABC simulations indicated the presence of two glacial refugia and post-glacial admixture of them followed by simultaneous dispersal throughout the current range of the species. The Ouachita population is distinct from others and has the lowest genetic diversity, indicating that this is a peripheral population of the species. Gene flow within this species has maintained high levels of genetic diversity in northern populations, however, all population have experienced fragmentation. Extirpation from the center of its range likely has isolated remaining populations due to the geographic distances among them.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.439vn/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54054","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54054","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24149656","doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.104"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.439vn"}}