{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-23T14:33:20Z","author":["Hubbard, Joanna K.","Safran, Rebecca J.","Vitousek, Maren N.","Jenkins, Brittany R."],"title":"Data from: An experimental analysis of the heritability of variation in glucocorticoid concentrations in a wild avian population","host":"Jenkins BR, Vitousek MN, Hubbard JK, Safran RJ (2014) An experimental analysis of the heritability of variation in glucocorticoid concentrations in a wild avian population. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1790): 20141302.","keywords":["glucocorticoids","cross-foster","barn swallow","animal model","heritability","environmental variation"],"description":"Glucocorticoid hormones (CORT) are predicted to promote adaptation to variable environments, yet little is known about the potential for CORT secretion patterns to respond to selection in free-living populations. We assessed the heritable variation underlying differences in hormonal phenotypes using a cross-foster experimental design with nestling North American barn swallows (Hirundo rustica erythrogaster). Using a bivariate animal model, we partitioned variance in baseline and stress-induced CORT concentrations into their additive genetic and rearing environment components and estimated their genetic correlation. Both baseline and stress-induced CORT were heritable with heritability of 0.152 and 0.343, respectively. We found that the variation in baseline CORT was best explained by rearing environment, whereas the variation in stress-induced CORT was contributed to by a combination of genetic and environmental factors. Further, we did not detect a genetic correlation between these two hormonal traits. Although rearing environment appears to play an important role in the secretion of both types of CORT, our results suggest that stress-induced CORT levels are underlain by greater additive genetic variance compared with baseline CORT levels. Accordingly, we infer that the glucocorticoid response to stress has a greater potential for evolutionary change in response to selection compared with baseline glucocorticoid secretion patterns.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.h14kk/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.h14kk/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.h14kk/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.65213","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.65213","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25056627","doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.1302"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h14kk"}}