{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-02T16:35:57Z","author":["Rasmann, Sergio","Agrawal, Anurag A"],"title":"Data from: Evolution of specialization: a phylogenetic study of host range in the red milkweed beetle (Tetraopes tetraophthalmus)","host":"Rasmann S, Agrawal AA (2011) Evolution of specialization: a phylogenetic study of host range in the red milkweed beetle (Tetraopes tetraophthalmus). American Naturalist 177(6): 728-737.","keywords":["Phylogeny","Phylogenetics: comparative","Coevolution","Interactions: coevolution","Macroevolution","Ecology: chemical","Adaptation","Trade offs","Interactions: plant/herbivore"],"description":"Specialization is common in most lineages of insect herbivores, one of the most diverse groups of organisms on earth. To address how and why specialization is maintained over evolutionary time, we hypothesized that plant defense and other ecological attributes of potential host plants would predict the performance of a specialist root feeding herbivore (the red milkweed beetle, Tetraopes tetraophthalmus). Using a comparative phylogenetic and functional trait approach, we assessed the determinants of insect host range across 18 species of Asclepias. Larval survivorship decreased with increasing phylogenetic distance from the true host, A. syriaca, suggesting that adaptation to plant traits drives specialization.  Among several root traits measured, only cardenolides (toxic defense chemicals) correlated with larval survival, and cardenolides also explained the phylogenetic distance effect in phylogenetically controlled multiple regression analyses. Additionally, milkweed species having a known association with other Tetraopes beetles were better hosts than species lacking Tetraopes herbivores, and milkweeds with similar specific leaf area values (a trait related to leaf function and habitat affiliation) to A. syriaca were better hosts than species having divergent values. We thus conclude that phylogenetic distance is an integrated measure of phenotypic and ecological attributes of Asclepias species, especially defensive cardenolides, which can be used to explain specialization and constraints on host shifts over evolutionary time.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8557/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8557","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8557","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21597250","doi:10.1086/659948"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8557"}}