{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-12-14T17:05:42Z","author":["Jaarola, Maarit","Paupério, Joana","Searle, Jeremy B.","Alves, Paulo C.","Herman, Jeremy S.","Melo-Ferreira, José"],"title":"Data from: Cryptic speciation in the field vole: a multilocus approach confirms three highly divergent lineages in Eurasia","host":"Paupério J, Herman JS, Melo-Ferreira J, Jaarola M, Alves PC, Searle JB (2012) Cryptic speciation in the field vole: a multilocus approach confirms three highly divergent lineages in Eurasia. Molecular Ecology 21(24): 6015–6032.","keywords":["demography","Phylogeography","species tree","cryptic species"],"description":"Species are generally described from morphological features, but there is growing recognition of sister forms that show substantial genetic differentiation without obvious morphological variation and may therefore be considered ‘cryptic species’. Here, we investigate the field vole (Microtus agrestis), a Eurasian mammal with little apparent morphological differentiation but which, on the basis of previous sex-linked nuclear and mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) analyses, is subdivided into a northern and a southern lineage, sufficiently divergent that they may represent two cryptic species. These earlier studies also provided limited evidence for two major mtDNA lineages within Iberia. In our present study we extend these findings through a multilocus approach. We sampled 160 individuals from 46 localities, mainly in Iberia, and sequenced 7 loci, maternally, paternally and bi-parentally inherited. Our results show that the mtDNA lineage identified in Portugal is indeed a distinct third lineage on the basis of other markers as well. In fact, multilocus coalescent based methods clearly support three separate evolutionary units which may represent cryptic species: Northern, Southern and Portuguese. Divergence among these units was inferred to have occurred during the last glacial period; the Portuguese lineage split occurred first (estimated at ca. 70 000 years BP) and the Northern and Southern lineages separated at around the Last Glacial Maximum (estimated at ca. 18 500 years BP). Such recent formation of evolutionary units that might be considered species has repercussions in terms of understanding evolutionary processes and the diversity of small mammals in a European context.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t/8"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40981","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40981","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23163319","doi:10.1111/mec.12024"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.kp79t"}}