{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-08-15T16:14:12Z","author":["Kennedy, Jonathan David","Weir, Jason T.","Price, Trevor Douglas","Tietze, D. Thomas","Martens, Jochen","Hooper, Daniel Marc"],"title":"Data from: Ecological limits on diversification of the Himalayan core Corvoidea","host":"Kennedy JD, Weir JT, Hooper DM, Tietze DT, Martens J, Price TD (2012) Ecological limits on diversification of the Himalayan core Corvoidea. Evolution 66(8): 2599-2613.","keywords":["Ecological controls","Diversity-dependence","Macroevolution","Phylogenetics","Adaptive radiation"],"description":"Within regions, differences in the number of species among clades must be explained by clade age, net diversification rate, or immigration. We examine these alternatives by assessing historical causes of the low diversity of a bird parvorder in the Himalayas (the core Corvoidea, 57 species present) relative to its more species rich sister clade. The core Corvoidea contain ecologically diverse species spanning a large range of body sizes and elevations. Despite this diversity, on the basis of ecological, morphological, and phylogenetic information, we infer that the best explanation for the low number of species within the core Corvoidea is one in which ecology limits diversification. Within the core Corvoidea, body size is correlated with elevation; large species are found at high elevations, and small species at lower elevations. Cladogenetic events leading to ecological differences between species in body size and shape mostly occurred millions of years ago, and the rate of evolutionary change has declined towards the present. Elevational distributions have been evolutionarily more labile, but are also associated with ancient cladogenetic events. We suggest the core Corvoidea occupy a restricted volume of ecological space in competition with other bird species, and this limits in situ diversification and/or immigration.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.p9t061vc/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.p9t061vc/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38511","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38511","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01618.x","PMID:22834756"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.p9t061vc"}}