{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-08-23T19:42:26Z","author":["Lemmon, Alan R.","Lemmon, Emily Moriarty","Emme, Sandra"],"title":"Data from: Anchored hybrid enrichment for massively high-throughput phylogenomics","host":"Lemmon AR, Emme S, Lemmon EM (2012) Anchored hybrid enrichment for massively high-throughput phylogenomics. Systematic Biology 61(5): 727-744.","keywords":["phylogeography","anchor regions","hybrid enrichment","ultraconserved elements","highly-conserved regions","anchored enrichment","phylogenetics","sequence capture"],"description":"The field of phylogenetics is on the cusp of a major revolution, enabled by new methods of data collection that leverage both genomic resources and recent advances in DNA sequencing. Previous phylogenetic work has required labor-intensive marker development coupled with single-locus PCR and DNA sequencing on a clade-by-clade and marker-by-marker basis. Here, we present a new, cost-efficient, and rapid approach to obtaining data from hundreds of genes for potentially hundreds of individuals for deep and shallow phylogenetic studies. Specifically, we designed probes for target enrichment of >500 loci in highly-conserved anchor regions of vertebrate genomes (flanked by less conserved regions) from five model species and tested enrichment efficiency in non-model species up to 254 million years divergent from the nearest model. We found that hybrid enrichment using conserved probes (anchored enrichment) can recover a large number of unlinked loci that are useful at a diversity of phylogenetic timescales. This new approach has the potential to not only expedite resolution of deep-scale portions of the Tree of Life but also to greatly accelerate resolution of the large number of shallow clades that remain unresolved. The combination of low cost (~1% of the cost of traditional Sanger sequencing and ~3.5% of the cost of high-throughput amplicon sequencing for projects on the scale of 500 loci x 100 individuals) and rapid data collection (~2 weeks of laboratory time) are expected to make this approach tractable even for researchers working on systems with limited or non-existent genomic resources.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128/11"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38700","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38700","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/sysbio/sys049","PMID:22605266"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.r606d128"}}