{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-17T18:06:44Z","author":["Olsen, Odd-Arne","Mayer, Klaus F. X.","Sandve, Simen R.","Pfeifer, Matthias","Marcussen, Thomas","The International Wheat Genome Sequencing Consortium,","Wulff, Brande B. H.","Jakobsen, Kjetill S.","Spannagl, Manuel","Heier, Lise","Steuernagel, Burkhard"],"title":"Data from: Ancient hybridizations among the ancestral genomes of bread wheat","host":"Marcussen T, Sandve SR, Heier L, Spannagl M, Pfeifer M, The International Wheat Genome Sequencing Consortium, Jakobsen KS, Wulff BBH, Steuernagel B, Mayer KFX, Olsen O (2014) Ancient hybridizations among the ancestral genomes of bread wheat. Science 345(6194).","keywords":["2269 gene trees of hexaploid wheat genomes","WINBUGS model for multi species coalescent","275 gene trees including diploid and hexaploid wheat genomes","Multiple sequence alignments for 2269 ortholog groups of hexaploid wheats","Multiple sequence alignments for 275 ortholog groups of diploid and hexaploid wheats"],"description":"The allohexaploid bread wheat genome consists of three closely related subgenomes (A, B, and D), but a clear understanding of their phylogenetic history has been lacking. We used genome assemblies of bread wheat and five diploid relatives to analyze genome-wide samples of gene trees, as well as to estimate evolutionary relatedness and divergence times. We show that the A and B genomes diverged from a common ancestor ~7 million years ago and that these genomes gave rise to the D genome through homoploid hybrid speciation 1 to 2 million years later. Our findings imply that the present-day bread wheat genome is a product of multiple rounds of hybrid speciation (homoploid and polyploid) and lay the foundation for a new framework for understanding the wheat genome as a multilevel phylogenetic mosaic.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f6c34/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64678","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64678","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25035499","doi:10.1126/science.1250092"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f6c34"}}