{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-04-16T19:23:56Z","author":["Heppell, Victoria","Moscrop, Andrew","Ward, Alison","Heneghan, Carl","Harrison, Sian"],"title":"Data from: Primary care follow-up and measured mental health outcomes among women referred for ultrasound assessment of pain and/or bleeding in early pregnancy: a quantitative questionnaire study","host":"Moscrop A, Harrison S, Heppell V, Heneghan C, Ward A (2013) Primary care follow-up and measured mental health outcomes among women referred for ultrasound assessment of pain and/or bleeding in early pregnancy: a quantitative questionnaire study. BMJ Open 3: e002595.","keywords":["primary care","miscarriage","gynaecology","pregnancy","health services administration & management","referral and consultation"],"description":"Objectives To examine the extent of primary care follow-up and mental health outcomes among women referred for ultrasound assessment of pain and/or bleeding in early pregnancy, including those whose pregnancy is found to be viable on ultrasound assessment. Design Questionnaire study with prospective follow-up. Setting Urgent gynaecology clinic in secondary care, England. Participants 57 women participated in the study. Entry criteria: referral to the urgent gynaecology clinic with pain and/or bleeding in early pregnancy; gestation less than 16 weeks (the clinic's own ‘cut-off’); no previous attendance at the clinic during the current pregnancy. Exclusion criteria: inability to understand English or to provide informed consent. Primary and secondary outcome measures Incidence of primary care follow-up among women referred to the urgent gynaecology clinic; incidence of women with measured mental health scores suggesting significant symptoms of distress. Results Fewer than 1 in 10 women referred for ultrasound assessment of pain and/or bleeding in early pregnancy had follow-up arrangements made with their general practitioner (GP). Most women who had GP follow-up found it helpful and a significant minority of women who did not have GP follow-up felt that it would have been helpful. Following ultrasound assessment, more than one-third of women had significant symptoms of distress. Symptoms of distress, particularly anxiety, were present among those women found to have viable pregnancies, as well as among those with non-viable pregnancies. Conclusions GPs are advised to consider offering follow-up to all women referred for ultrasound assessment of pain and/or bleeding in early pregnancy. Researchers in this area are advised to consider the experiences of women with pain and/or bleeding in early pregnancy whose pregnancies are ultimately found to be viable on ultrasound scan.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3tr8d/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47735","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47735","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23585390","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002595"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3tr8d"}}