{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-12T15:37:12Z","author":["Leroi, Armand M.","Burt, Austin","Mauch, Matthias","MacCallum, Robert M."],"title":"Data from: Evolution of music by public choice","host":"MacCallum RM, Mauch M, Burt A, Leroi AM (2012) Evolution of music by public choice. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 109(30): 12081–12086.","keywords":["cultural evolution","music","evolutionary algorithm","evolution"],"description":"Music evolves as composers, performers, and consumers favor some musical variants over others. To investigate the role of consumer selection, we constructed a Darwinian music engine consisting of a population of short audio loops that sexually reproduce and mutate. This population evolved for 2,513 generations under the selective influence of 6,931 consumers who rated the loops’ aesthetic qualities. We found that the loops quickly evolved into music attributable, in part, to the evolution of aesthetically pleasing chords and rhythms. Later, however, evolution slowed. Applying the Price equation, a general description of evolutionary processes, we found that this stasis was mostly attributable to a decrease in the fidelity of transmission. Our experiment shows how cultural dynamics can be explained in terms of competing evolutionary forces. The audio files attached below can also be heard at <http://soundcloud.com/uncoolbob/sets/darwintunes/>.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/23","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/22","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/21","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228/20"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40013","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40013","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1073/pnas.1203182109","PMID:22711832"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h0228"}}