{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-09-02T19:42:29Z","author":["Gabirot, Marianne","Runemark, Anna","Svensson, Erik I"],"title":"Data from: Population divergence in chemical signals and the potential for premating isolation between islet- and mainland populations of the Skyros wall  lizard, (Podarcis gaigeae)","host":"Runemark A, Gabirot M, Svensson EI (2011) Population divergence in chemical signals and the potential for premating isolation between islet- and mainland populations of the Skyros wall lizard (Podarcis gaigeae). Journal of Evolutionary Biology 24(4): 795–809.","keywords":["Population genetics","Molecular evolution"],"description":"When sexually selected traits diverge due to different local selective environments premating isolation might arise as a correlated response. However, sexually \nselected traits might also diverge by stochastic forces. Here, we show that odour-based mate preferences and scent composition have diverged between islet- and mainland \npopulations of Skyros wall lizard, Podarcis gaigeae. We quantified the degree of scent-mediated premating isolation between populations. Islet lizards preferred scent \nfrom islet lizards, whereas the mainland populations were less discriminatory. The pheromone compositions differed more between islets than between islet- and mainland \npopulations, and did not differ significantly between mainland populations. There was a tendency for population divergence in pheromones to be positively correlated with \nneutral genetic divergence. This might indicate a role for genetic drift in evolutionary change in these signals and partial decoupling between signals and preferences. \nOur results suggest that chemical signals and associated mate preferences can diverge through stochastic and selective forces and influence premating \nisolation.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8265/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8265/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8265","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8265","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21261773","doi:10.1111/j.1420-9101.2010.02214.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8265"}}