{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-11T14:27:58Z","author":["Shang, Hui","Luo, Yi-Bo","Bai, Wei-Ning"],"title":"Data from: Influence of asymmetrical mating patterns and male reproductive success on the maintenance of sexual polymorphism in Acer pictum subsp. mono (Aceraceae)","host":"Shang H, Luo Y, Bai W (2012) Influence of asymmetrical mating patterns and male reproductive success on the maintenance of sexual polymorphism in Acer pictum subsp. mono (Aceraceae). Molecular Ecology 21(15): 3869-3878.","keywords":["disassortative mating","sexual plasticity","duodichogamous","intraphenotype mating","paternity analysis"],"description":"Populations of Acer species often contain more than three sexual phenotypes with very complex sexual polymorphism such as duodichogamy, protandry, and protogyny. We investigated whether mating patterns and male reproductive success are important factors that maintain sexual polymorphism in Acer. Paternity analyses were used to estimate rates of outcrossing and disassortative mating, as well as male reproductive success, in Acer pictum subsp. mono. A pollen-transfer model was modified to investigate whether the unequal ratios of sexual phenotypes were associated with observed mating patterns. The mating pattern of Acer pictum subsp. mono was mainly outcrossing and disassortative among the sexual phenotypes. Although the duodichogamous phenotype showed a significant amount of intraphenotypic mating, the frequency did not exceed that of disassortative mating. No significant differences in male reproductive success were observed among sexual phenotypes. The pollen-transfer model demonstrated that sexual phenotype ratios could be maintained by the observed mating pattern in the population. The results indicated that disassortative mating among the sexual phenotypes can maintain sexual polymorphism in A. pictum subsp. mono, and ratios biased towards duodichogamy can result from frequent intraphenotypic mating in this phenotype.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v5t5t5d5/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.37418","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.37418","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05555.x","PMID:22680336"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v5t5t5d5"}}