{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-03-28T16:17:01Z","author":["Kjærandsen, Jostein","Martinsson, Svante"],"title":"Data from: Katatopygia gen. n., a monophyletic branch segregated from Boletina (Diptera, Mycetophilidae)","host":"Martinsson S, Kjærandsen J (2012) Katatopygia gen. n., a monophyletic branch segregated from Boletina (Diptera, Mycetophilidae). ZooKeys 175: 37–67.","keywords":["revision","identification key","new genus","phylogeny","new synonymy","taxonomy"],"description":"The genus Katatopygia gen. n. is proposed for the Boletina erythropyga/punctus-group that was first introduced by Garrett (1924, 1925) and currently comprises eight described species. Molecular studies have strongly indicated that this group forms a monophyletic sister-group to a clade consisting of all other Boletina, Coelosia and Gnoriste, and its monophyly is supported by morphological data as well. The new genus includes the following species: Katatopygia antoma (Garrett, 1924), comb. n., Katatopygia antica (Garrett, 1924), comb. n., Katatopygia erythropyga (Holmgren, 1883), comb. n., Katatopygia hissarica (Zaitzev & Polevoi, 2002), comb. n., Katatopygia magna (Garrett, 1925), comb. n., Katatopygia laticauda (Saigusa, 1968), comb. n., Katatopygia neoerythropyga (Zaitzev & Polevoi, 2002), comb. n. andKatatopygia sahlbergi (Lundström, 1906), comb. n., all transferred from Boletina. Katatopygia sahlbergi is found to be a senior synonym of Boletina punctus Garrett, 1925, syn. n. A phylogeny based on morphological data and using parsimony analysis yielded four most parsimonious trees where the new genus is retrieved as monophyletic with high support. Katatopygia neoerythropyga is found to be the sister-taxon to all other species that form two clades, one with Katatopygia sahlbergi-like species and one with Katatopygia erythropyga-like species. A key to males of Katatopygia is provided.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.682t7442/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38030","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38030","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.3897/zookeys.175.2388","PMID:22451790"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.682t7442"}}