{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-02T21:03:31Z","author":["Goldberg, Emma E.","Lancaster, Lesley T.","Ree, Richard H."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenetic inference of reciprocal effects between geographic range evolution and diversification","host":"Goldberg EE, Lancaster LT, Ree RH (2011) Phylogenetic inference of reciprocal effects between geographic range evolution and diversification. Systematic Biology 60(4): 451-465.","keywords":["comparative methods","macroevolution","diversification","biogeography"],"description":"Geographic characters---traits relating to the spatial distribution of\na species---may both affect and be affected by processes associated\nwith lineage birth and death.  This is potentially confounding to\ncomparative analyses of species distributions because current models\ndo not allow reciprocal interactions between the evolution of traits\nand the growth of phylogenetic trees.  Here we introduce a\nlikelihood-based approach to estimating region-dependent rates of\nspeciation, extinction, and range evolution from a phylogeny, using a\nnew model in which these processes are interdependent.  We demonstrate\nthe method with simulation tests that accurately recover parameters\nrelating to the mode of speciation and source-sink dynamics.  We then\napply it to the evolution of habitat occupancy in Californian plant\ncommunities, where we find higher rates of speciation in chaparral\nthan in forests and evidence for expanding habitat tolerances.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.8343/10"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8343","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8343","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/sysbio/syr046","PMID:21551125"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8343"}}