{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-10-01T17:38:10Z","author":["Bruun, Hans Henrik","Vandepitte, Katrien","Closset-Kopp, Déborah","De Kort, Hanne","Mergeay, Joachim","Honnay, Olivier"],"title":"Data from: Landscape genomics and a common garden trial reveal adaptive differentiation to temperature across Europe in the tree species Alnus glutinosa","host":"De Kort H, Vandepitte K, Bruun HH, Closset-Kopp D, Honnay O, Mergeay J (2014) Landscape genomics and a common garden trial reveal adaptive differentiation to temperature across Europe in the tree species Alnus glutinosa. Molecular Ecology 23(19): 4709-4721.","keywords":["Contemporary Evolution","Quantitative Genetics","Climate Change","Adaptation"],"description":"The adaptive potential of tree species to cope with climate change has important ecological and economic implications. Many temperate tree species experience a wide range of environmental conditions, suggesting high adaptability to new environmental conditions. We investigated adaptation to regional climate in the drought-sensitive tree species Alnus glutinosa (Black alder), using a complementary approach that integrates genomic, phenotypic and landscape data. A total of 24 European populations were studied in a common garden and through landscape genomic approaches. Genotyping-By-Sequencing was used to identify SNPs across the genome, resulting in 1990 SNPs. Although a relatively low percentage of putative adaptive SNPs was detected (2.86% outlier SNPs), we observed clear associations among outlier allele frequencies, temperature, and plant traits. In line with the typical drought avoiding nature of A. glutinosa, leaf size varied according to a temperature gradient and significant associations with multiple outlier loci were observed, corroborating the ecological relevance of the observed outlier SNPs. Moreover, the lack of isolation-by-distance, the very low genetic differentiation among populations and the high intra-population genetic variation all support the notion that high gene exchange combined with strong environmental selection promotes adaptation to environmental cues.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rg82f/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61985","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61985","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24860941","doi:10.1111/mec.12813"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rg82f"}}