{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Systematic Biology","keywords":["mitochondrial DNA genomes","amino acid composition","K/T boundary","CSR Logdeterminant","rodent monophyly","mammalian evolution"],"host":"Penny D, Hasegawa M, Waddell PJ, Hendy MD (1999) Mammalian evolution: timing and implications from using the LogDeterminant transform for proteins of differing amino acid composition. Systematic Biology 48: 76-93.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.389/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.389","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-28T19:13:04Z","author":["Hendy, Michael D.","Waddell, Peter J.","Penny, David","Hasegawa, Masami"],"title":"Data from: Mammalian evolution: timing and implications from using the LogDeterminant transform for proteins of differing amino acid composition","description":"We explore the tree of mammalian mtDNA sequences, using particularly the LogDet transform on amino acid sequences, the distance Hadamard transform, and the Closest Tree selection criterion. The amino acid composition of different species show significant differences, even within mammals. After compensating for these differences, nearest-neighbor bootstrap results suggest that the tree is locally stable, though a few groups show slightly greater rearrangements when a large proportion of the constant sites are removed. Many parts of the trees we obtain agree with those on published protein ML trees. Interesting results include a preference for rodent monophyly. The detection of a few alternative signals to those on the optimal tree were obtained using the distance Hadamard transform (with results expressed as a Lento plot). One rearrangement suggested was the interchange of the position of primates and rodents on the optimal tree. The basic stability of the tree, combined with two calibration points (whale/cow and horse/rhinoceros), together with a distant secondary calibration from the mammal/bird divergence, allows inferences of the times of divergence of putative clades. Allowing for sampling variances due to finite sequence length, most major divergences amongst lineages leading to modern orders, appear to occur well before the Cretaceous/Tertiary (K/T) boundary. Implications arising from these early divergences are discussed, particularly the possibility of competition between the small dinosaurs and the new mammal clades.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.389","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1080/106351599260454","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.389"}}