{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-06-21T18:05:43Z","author":["Völker, Elke","Thielsch, Anne","Schwenk, Klaus","Kraus, Robert H. S."],"title":"Data from: Discrimination of hybrid classes using cross-species amplification of microsatellite loci: methodological challenges and solutions in Daphnia","host":"Thielsch A, Völker E, Kraus RHS, Schwenk K (2012) Discrimination of hybrid classes using cross-species amplification of microsatellite loci: methodological challenges and solutions in Daphnia. Molecular Ecology Resources 12(4): 697-705.","keywords":["Species delineation","Daphnia longispina complex","Null allele","Assignment testing","Flanking region","Hybridization"],"description":"Microsatellite markers are important tools in population, conservation and forensic studies and are frequently used for species delineation, the detection of hybridization and introgression. Therefore, marker sets that amplify variable DNA regions in two species are required; however, cross-species amplification is often difficult, as genotyping errors such as null alleles may occur. In order to estimate the level of potential misidentifications based on genotyping errors, we compared the occurrence of parental alleles in laboratory and natural Daphnia hybrids (Daphnia longispina group). We tested a set of twelve microsatellite loci with regard to their suitability for unambiguous species and hybrid class identification using F1 hybrids bred in the laboratory. Further, a large set of 44 natural populations of D. cucullata, D. galeata and D. longispina (1715 individuals) as well as their interspecific hybrids were genotyped to validate the discriminatory power of different marker combinations. Species delineation using microsatellite multi-locus genotypes produced reliable results for all three studied species using assignment tests. D. galeata x cucullata hybrid detection was limited due to three loci exhibiting D. cucullata specific null alleles which most likely are caused by differences in primer binding sites of parental species. Overall discriminatory power in hybrid detection was improved when a subset of markers was identified that amplifies equally well in both species.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.dv6j84kt/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38227","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38227","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1755-0998.2012.03142.x","PMID:22487563"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.dv6j84kt"}}