{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-23T19:40:44Z","author":["Palmer, William J.","Mbogo, Charles M.","Jiggins, Francis M.","Osei-Poku, Jewelna"],"title":"Data from: Deep sequencing reveals extensive variation in the gut microbiota of wild mosquitoes from Kenya.","host":"Osei-Poku J, Mbogo CM, Palmer WJ, Jiggins FM (2012) Deep sequencing reveals extensive variation in the gut microbiota of wild mosquitoes from Kenya. Molecular Ecology 21(20): 5138–5150.","keywords":["Gut microbiota","Bacteria","Host Parasite Interactions","Mosquito","Insects","Population Ecology"],"description":"The mosquito midgut is a hostile environment that vector-borne parasites must survive in order to be transmitted. Commensal bacteria in the midgut can reduce the ability of mosquitoes to transmit disease, either by having direct anti-parasite effects or by stimulating basal immune responses of the insect host. As different bacteria have different effects on parasite development, the composition of the bacterial community in the mosquito gut is likely to affect the probability of disease transmission. We investigated the diversity of mosquito gut bacteria in the field using 454 pyrosequencing of 16S rRNA to build up a comprehensive picture of the diversity of gut bacteria in 8 mosquito species. We found that mosquito gut typically has a very simple gut microbiota that is dominated by a single bacterial taxon. Although different mosquito species share remarkably similar gut bacteria, individuals in a population are extremely variable and can have little overlap in the bacterial taxa present in their guts. This may be an important factor in causing differences in disease transmission rates within mosquito populations.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2dm26/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40717","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40717","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05759.x","PMID:22988916"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2dm26"}}