{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["Systematic Biology","47:2, 181 - 207"],"keywords":["molecular clock","introgression","floral evolution","data set conflict","phylogeny","biogeography"],"host":"Baum DA, Small RL, Wendel JF (1998) Biogeography and floral evolution of baobabs (Adansonia, Bombacaceae) as inferred from multiple data sets. Systematic Biology 47: 181-207.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.66/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-28T18:20:42Z","author":["Wendel, Jonathan F.","Baum, David A.","Small, Randall L."],"title":"Data from: Biogeography and floral evolution of baobabs (Adansonia, Bombacaceae) as inferred from multiple data sets","description":"The phylogeny of baobab trees was analyzed using four data sets: chloroplast DNA restriction sites, sequences of the chloroplast rpl 16 intron, sequences of the internal transcribed spacer ITS region of nuclear ribosomal DNA, and morphology. We sampled each of the eight species of Adansonia plus three outgroup taxa from tribe Adansonieae. These data were analyzed singly and in combination using parsimony. ITS and morphology provided the greatest resolution and were largely concordant. The two chloroplast data sets showed concordance with one another but showed significant conflict with ITS and morphology. A possible explanation for the conflict is genealogical discordance within the Malagasy Longitubae, perhaps due to introgression events. A maximum likelihood analysis of branching times shows that the dispersal between Africa and Australia occurred well after the fragmentation of Gondwana and therefore involved overwater dispersal. The phylogeny does not permit unambiguous reconstruction of floral evolution but suggests the plausible hypothesis that hawkmoth pollination was ancestral in Adansonia and that there were two parallel switches to pollination by mammals in the genus.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1080/106351598260879","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.66"}}