{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-15T18:38:46Z","author":["Børsting, Claus","Simonsen, Bo T.","Siegismund, Hans R.","Frandsen, Peter","Hvilsom, Christina","Carlsen, Frands","Sallé, Bettina"],"title":"Data from: Understanding geographic origins and history of admixture among chimpanzees in European zoos, with implications for future breeding programmes","host":"Hvilsom C, Frandsen P, Børsting C, Carlsen F, Sallé B, Simonsen BT, Siegismund HR (2013) Understanding geographic origins and history of admixture among chimpanzees in European zoos, with implications for future breeding programmes. Heredity 110(6): 586-593.","keywords":["structure","subspecies","chimpanzee conservation","microsatellites"],"description":"Despite ample focus on this endangered species, conservation planning for chimpanzees residing outside Africa has proven a challenge because of the lack of ancestry information. Here, we analysed the largest number of chimpanzee samples to date, examining microsatellites in >100 chimpanzees from the range of the species in Africa, and 20% of the European zoo population. We applied the knowledge about subspecies differentiation throughout equatorial Africa to assign origin to chimpanzees in the largest conservation management programme globally. A total of 63% of the genotyped chimpanzees from the European zoos could be assigned to one of the recognized subspecies. The majority being of West African origin (40%) will help consolidate the current breeding programme for this subspecies and the identification of individuals belonging to the two other subspecies so far found in European zoos can form the basis for breeding programmes for these. Individuals of various degree of mixed ancestry made up 37% of the genotyped European zoo population and thus highlight the need for appropriate management programmes guided by genetic analysis to preserve maximum genetic diversity and reduce hybridization among subspecies.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1th15/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46018","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46018","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.9","PMID:23531981"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1th15"}}