{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"270;6;2009","keywords":["allometric scaling","forelimbs","morphometrics","prey size"],"host":"Meachen-Samuels J, Van Valkenburgh B (2009) Forelimb indicators of prey-size preference in the Felidae. Journal of Morphology 270(6): 729-744.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1fh61/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.33558","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-04-28T20:25:30Z","author":["Van Valkenburgh, Blaire","Meachen-Samuels, Julie"],"title":"Data from: Forelimb indicators of prey-size preference in the Felidae","description":"The forelimbs, along with the crania, are an essential part of the prey-killing apparatus in cats.\nLinear morphometrics of the forelimbs were used to determine the morphological differences between felids that specialize on large prey, small prey, or mixed prey. We also compared the scaling of felid forelimbs to those\nof canids to test whether prey capture strategies affect\nforelimb scaling. Results suggest that large prey specialists\nhave relatively robust forelimbs when compared with smaller prey specialists. This includes relatively more robust humeri and radii, relatively larger distal\nends of the humerus, and relatively larger articular\nareas of the humerus and radius. Large prey specialists also had relatively longer olecranon processes of the ulna and wider proximal paws. These characters are all important for subduing large prey while the cat positions\nitself for the killing bite. Small prey specialists have relatively longer distal limb elements for swift prey capture, and mixed prey specialists had intermediate\nvalues with relatively more robust metacarpals. Arboreal felids also had more robust limbs. They had relatively longer proximal phalanges for better grip while\nclimbing, and a relatively short brachial index (radius to\nhumerus ratio). Additionally, we found that felids and canids differ in forelimb scaling, which emphasizes the dual use of forelimbs for locomotion and prey capture in felids. This morphometric technique worked well to separate prey-size preference in felids, but did not work as\nwell to separate locomotor groups, as scansorial and terrestrial\nfelids were not clearly distinguished.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.33558","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1002/jmor.10712","PMID:19123240"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1fh61"}}