{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-29T17:49:11Z","author":["Billiard, Sylvain","Abu Awad, Diala","Gervais, Camille Elsa","Castric, Vincent","Roze, Denis"],"title":"Data from: Genetic architecture of inbreeding depression and the maintenance of gametophytic self-incompatibility","host":"Gervais CE, Abu Awad D, Roze D, Castric V, Billiard S (2014) Genetic architecture of inbreeding depression and the maintenance of gametophytic self-incompatibility. Evolution, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Fitness","Population Genetics","Evolutionary Genomics","Models/Simulations","Mating Systems","Inbreeding"],"description":"Gametophytic self-incompatibility is a widespread genetic system, which enables hermaphroditic plants to avoid self-fertilization and mating with close relatives. Inbreeding depression is thought to be the major force maintaining self-incompatibility; however, inbreeding depression is a dynamical variable that depends in particular on the mating system. In this paper we use multilocus, individual based simulations to examine the co-evolution of self-incompatibility and inbreeding depression within finite populations. We focus on the conditions for the maintenance of self-incompatibility when self-compatible mutants are introduced in the population by recurrent mutation, and compare simulation results with predictions from an analytical model treating inbreeding depression as a fixed parameter (thereby neglecting effects of purging within the self-compatible sub-population). In agreement with previous models, we observe that the maintenance of self-incompatibility is associated with high inbreeding depression and is facilitated by high rates of self-pollination. Purging of deleterious mutations by self-compatible mutants has little effect on the spread of those mutants as long as most deleterious alleles have weak fitness effects: in this case, the genetic architecture of inbreeding depression has little effect on the maintenance of self-incompatibility. By contrast, purging may greatly enhance the spread of self-compatible mutants when deleterious alleles have strong fitness effects.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746/6"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67427","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67427","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12495","PMID:25065256"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rv746"}}