{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"19;1;2009","keywords":["disturbance","marine protected areas","gene flow","recruitment","genetic connectivity","reef-building coral","microsatellites","marine reserves"],"host":"Underwood JN, Smith LD, van Oppen MJH, Gilmour JP (2009) Ecologically relevant dispersal of corals on isolated reefs: implications for managing resilience. Ecological Applications 19(1): 18-29.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s3r4hn4p/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36264","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-11-30T15:34:43Z","author":["Gilmour, James P.","van Oppen, Madeleine J.H.","Smith, Luke D.","Underwood, James N."],"title":"Data from: Ecologically relevant dispersal of corals on isolated reefs: implications for managing resilience","description":"Coral reefs are in decline worldwide, and marine reserve networks have been advocated as a powerful management tool for maximizing the resilience of coral communities to an increasing variety, number, and severity of disturbances. However, the effective design of reserves must account for the spatial scales of larval dispersal that affect the demography of communities over ecological time frames. Ecologically relevant distances of dispersal were inferred from DNA microsatellite data in a broadcast-spawning (Acropora tenuis) and a brooding (Seriatopora hystrix) coral at isolated reef systems off northwest Australia. Congruent with expectations based on life histories, levels of genetic subdivision among populations were markedly higher in the brooder than in the broadcast spawner. Additionally, significant subdivision for both species between systems (>100 km), and between (>10 km) or within reefs (<10 km) within systems, indicated that many reefs or reef patches are demographically independent. There was also a clear distinction in the scale of genetic structure between the different systems; at the more geographically complex of the systems, a much finer scale structure was detected in both species. This suggested that the hydrodynamics associated with these complex reefs restrict distances regularly traveled by larvae. The primary implication is that short-term recovery of these coral communities after severe disturbance requires the input of larvae from viable communities kilometers to a few tens of kilometers away. Therefore, to be self-sustaining, we suggest that coral reef protected areas need to be large enough to encompass these routine dispersal distances. Further, to facilitate recovery from severe disturbances, protected areas need to be replicated over these spatial scales. However, specific designs also need to account for size, complexity, and isolation of reefs, which will either restrict or enhance dispersal within this range.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36264","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1890/07-1461.1","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s3r4hn4p"}}