{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-10T15:48:48Z","author":["Neiman, Maurine","Krois, Nicole R.","Puttagunta, Nikhil","Cherukuri, Anvesh"],"title":"Data from: Higher rate of tissue regeneration in polyploid asexual vs. diploid sexual freshwater snails","host":"Krois NR, Cherukuri A, Puttagunta N, Neiman M (2013) Higher rate of tissue regeneration in polyploid asexual vs. diploid sexual freshwater snails. Biology Letters 9(4): 20130422.","keywords":["sexual reproduction","polyploidy"],"description":"Characterizing phenotypic differences between sexual and asexual organisms is a critical step towards understanding why sexual reproduction is so common. Because asexuals are often polyploid, understanding how ploidy influences phenotype is directly relevant to the study of sex and will provide key insights into the evolution of ploidy-level variation. The well-established association between genome size and cell cycle duration, evidence for a link between genome size and tissue regeneration rate and the growing body of research showing that ploidy influences growth rate and gene expression led us to hypothesize that healing and tissue regeneration might be affected by ploidy-level variation. We evaluated this hypothesis by measuring the rate of regeneration of antenna tissue of Potamopyrgus antipodarum, a New Zealand snail characterized by frequent coexistence between diploid sexuals and polyploid asexuals. Antennae of triploid and presumptive tetraploid asexuals regenerated more rapidly than the antennae of diploid sexuals, but regeneration rate did not differ between triploids and tetraploids. These results suggest either that ploidy elevation has nonlinear positive effects on tissue regeneration and/or that factors associated directly with reproductive mode affect regeneration rate more than ploidy level. The results of this study also indicate that the lower ploidy of sexual P. antipodarum is unlikely to confer advantages associated with more rapid regeneration.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.68nj4/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51206","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51206","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23843218","doi:10.1098/rsbl.2013.0422"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.68nj4"}}