{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-26T14:16:03Z","author":["Slotte, Tanja","Stern, David L","Andolfatto, Peter","Wright, Stephen I.","Hazzouri, Khaled Michel"],"title":"Data from: Genetic architecture and adaptive significance of the selfing syndrome in Capsella","host":"Slotte T, Hazzouri KM, Stern DL, Andolfatto P, Wright SI (2011) Genetic architecture and adaptive significance of the selfing syndrome in Capsella. Evolution 66(5): 1360-1374.","keywords":["Population Genetics","Quantitative Genetics","Morphological Evolution","Mating Systems","Adaptation"],"description":"The transition from outcrossing to predominant self-fertilization is one of the most common evolutionary transitions in flowering plants. This shift is often accompanied by a suite of changes in floral and reproductive characters termed the selfing syndrome. Here, we characterize the genetic architecture and evolutionary forces underlying evolution of the selfing syndrome in Capsella rubella following its recent divergence from the outcrossing ancestor Capsella grandiflora. We conduct genotyping by multiplexed shotgun sequencing and map floral and reproductive traits in a large (N=550) F2 population. Our results suggest that in contrast to previous studies of the selfing syndrome, changes at a few loci, some with major effects, have shaped the evolution of the selfing syndrome in Capsella. The directionality of QTL effects as well as population genetic patterns of polymorphism and divergence at 318 loci are consistent with a history of directional selection on the selfing syndrome. Our study provides an important step towards characterizing the genetic basis and evolutionary forces underlying the evolution of the selfing syndrome in a genetically accessible model system.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.f0gg64v5/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.f0gg64v5/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.f0gg64v5/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36396","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36396","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22519777","doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2011.01540.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f0gg64v5"}}