{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Molecular Identification of trophic Interactions;;","keywords":["Agriculture","Species Interactions","Diet Analysis","Invertebrates","Insects"],"host":"Wallinger C, Staudacher K, Schallhart N, Mitterutzner E, Steiner E, Juen A, Traugott M (2014) How generalist herbivores exploit belowground plant diversity in temperate grasslands. Molecular Ecology 23(15): 3826-3837.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f45q2/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54572","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2014-07-24T15:51:04Z","author":["Juen, Anita","Staudacher, Karin","Traugott, Michael","Wallinger, Corinna","Steiner, Eva-Maria","Mitterutzner, Evi","Schallhart, Nikolaus"],"title":"Data from: How generalist herbivores exploit belowground plant diversity in temperate grasslands","description":"Belowground herbivores impact plant performance, thereby inducing changes in plant community composition, which potentially leads to cascading effects onto higher trophic levels and ecosystem processes and productivity. Amongst soil-living insects, external root-chewing generalist herbivores have the strongest impact on plants. However, the lack of knowledge on their feeding behaviour under field conditions considerably hampers achieving a comprehensive understanding of how they affect plant communities. Here, we address this gap of knowledge by investigating the feeding behaviour of Agriotes click beetle larvae, which are common generalist external root-chewers in temperate grassland soils. Utilizing diagnostic multiplex PCR to assess the larval diet, we examined the seasonal patterns in feeding activity, putative preferences for specific plant taxa, and whether species identity and larval instar affects food choices of the herbivores. Contrary to our hypothesis, most of the larvae were feeding-active throughout the entire vegetation period, indicating that the grassland plants are subjected to constant belowground feeding pressure. Feeding was selective, with members of Plantaginaceae and Asteraceae being preferred; Apiaceae were avoided. Poaceae, although assumed to be most preferred, had an intermediate position. The food preferences exhibited seasonal changes, indicating a fluctuation in plant traits important for wireworm feeding choice. Species- and instar-specific differences in dietary choice of the Agriotes larvae were small, suggesting that species and larval instars occupy the same trophic niche. According to the current findings, the food choice of these larvae is primarily driven by plant identity, exhibiting seasonal changes. This needs to be considered when analysing soil herbivore-plant interactions.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54572","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12579","PMID:24188592"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f45q2"}}