{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-16T17:31:27Z","author":["Restoux, Gwendal","Fernandez-Manjarres, Juan F.","Frascaria-Lacoste, Nathalie","Thomasset, Muriel","Douglas, Gerry C.","Hodkinson, Trevor R."],"title":"Data from: Thank you for not flowering: conservation genetics and gene flow analysis of native and non-native populations of Fraxinus (Oleaceae) in Ireland","host":"Thomasset M, Hodkinson TR, Restoux G, Frascaria-Lacoste N, Douglas GC, Fernandez-Manjarres JF (2014) Thank you for not flowering: conservation genetics and gene flow analysis of native and non-native populations of Fraxinus (Oleaceae) in Ireland. Heredity 112(6): 596-606.","keywords":"SSR Genotypes","description":"The risks of gene flow between interfertile native and introduced plant populations are greatest when there is no spatial isolation of pollen clouds and phenological patterns overlap completely. Moreover, invasion probabilities are further increased if introduced populations are capable of producing seeds by selfing. Here we investigated the mating system and patterns of pollen-mediated gene flow among populations of native ash (Fraxinus excelsior) and mixed plantations of non-native ash (F. angustifolia and F. excelsior) as well as hybrid ash (F. excelsior × F. angustifolia) in Ireland. We analysed the flowering phenology of the mother trees and genotyped with six microsatellite loci in progeny arrays from 132 native and plantation trees (1493 seeds) and 444 potential parents. Paternity analyses suggested that plantation and native trees were pollinated by both native and introduced trees. No signs of significant selfing in the introduced trees were observed and no evidence of higher male reproductive success was found for introduced trees compared with native ones either. A small but significant genetic structure was found (φft=0.05) and did not correspond to an isolation-by-distance pattern. However, we observed a significant temporal genetic structure related to the different phenological groups, especially with early and late flowering native trees; each phenological group was pollinated with distinctive pollen sources. Implications of these results are discussed in relation to the conservation and invasiveness of ash and the spread of resistance genes against pathogens such as the fungus Chalara fraxinea that is destroying common ash forests in Europe.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.55c2f/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56984","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56984","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24424162","doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.141"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.55c2f"}}