{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-05T18:46:18Z","author":["Redwine, Angela","Siu, Jenna C.","Ksiazek, Kelly","Dyer, Rodney J.","López-Villalobos, Adriana","DiLeo, Michelle F.","Rhodes, Matthew K."],"title":"Data from: The gravity of pollination: integrating at-site features into spatial analysis of contemporary pollen movement.","host":"DiLeo MF, Siu JC, Rhodes MK, López-Villalobos A, Redwine A, Ksiazek K, Dyer RJ (2014) The gravity of pollination: integrating at-site features into spatial analysis of contemporary pollen movement. Molecular Ecology 23(16): 3973-3982.","keywords":["Gene Flow","Landscape Genetics","Gravity Models","Population Graphs"],"description":"Pollen-mediated gene flow is a major driver of spatial genetic structure in plant populations. Both individual plant characteristics and site-specific features of the landscape can modify the perceived attractiveness of plants to their pollinators and thus play an important role in shaping spatial genetic variation. Most studies of landscape-level genetic connectivity in plants have focused on the effects of inter-individual distance using spatial and increasingly ecological separation; yet have not incorporated individual plant characteristics or other at-site ecological variables. Using spatially explicit simulations, we first tested the extent to which the inclusion of at-site variables influencing local pollination success improved the statistical characterization of genetic connectivity based upon examination of pollen pool genetic structure. The addition of at-site characteristics provided better models than those that only considered inter-individual spatial distance (e.g., IBD). Models parameterized using conditional genetic covariance (e.g., Population Graphs) also outperformed those assuming panmixia. In a natural population of Cornus florida L. (Cornaceae), we showed that the addition of at-site characteristics (clumping of primary canopy opening above each maternal tree and maternal tree floral output) provided significantly better models describing gene flow than models including only between-site spatial (IBD) and ecological (Isolation By Resistance) variables. Overall, our results show that including inter-individual and local ecological variation greatly aids in characterizing landscape-level measures of contemporary gene flow.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.774s8/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.774s8/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66201","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66201","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24995799","doi:10.1111/mec.12839"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.774s8"}}