{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-12-27T20:08:17Z","author":["Silvestro, Daniele","Zizka, Georg","Schulte, Katharina"],"title":"Data from: Disentangling the effects of key innovations on the diversification of Bromelioideae (Bromeliaceae)","host":"Silvestro D, Zizka G, Schulte K (2013) Disentangling the effects of key innovations on the diversification of Bromelioideae (Bromeliaceae). Evolution 68(1): 163–175.","keywords":["BiSSE","speciation extinction rates","Key Innovation","Macroevolution"],"description":"The evolution of key innovations, novel traits that promote diversification, is often seen as major driver for the unequal distribution of species richness within the tree of life. In this study, we aim to determine the factors underlying the extraordinary radiation of the subfamily Bromelioideae, one of the most diverse clades among the neotropical plant family Bromeliaceae. Based on an extended molecular phylogenetic data set, we examine the effect of two putative key innovations, that is, the Crassulacean acid metabolism (CAM) and the water-impounding tank, on speciation and extinction rates. To this aim, we develop a novel Bayesian implementation of the phylogenetic comparative method, binary state speciation and extinction, which enables hypotheses testing by Bayes factors and accommodates the uncertainty on model selection by Bayesian model averaging. Both CAM and tank habit were found to correlate with increased net diversification, thus fulfilling the criteria for key innovations. Our analyses further revealed that CAM photosynthesis is correlated with a twofold increase in speciation rate, whereas the evolution of the tank had primarily an effect on extinction rates that were found five times lower in tank-forming lineages compared to tank-less clades. These differences are discussed in the light of biogeography, ecology, and past climate change.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.0dm16/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.0dm16/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.52507","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.52507","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24372602","doi:10.1111/evo.12236"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.0dm16"}}