{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-04T18:21:02Z","author":["Chapman, Tracey","Poissant, Jocelyn","Edward, Dominic Alexander","Wilson, Alastair J."],"title":"Data from: Sexual conflict and interacting phenotypes: a quantitative genetic analysis of fecundity and copula duration in Drosophila melanogaster","host":"Edward DA, Poissant J, Wilson AJ, Chapman T (2014) Sexual conflict and interacting phenotypes: a quantitative genetic analysis of fecundity and copula duration in Drosophila melanogaster. Evolution 68(6): 1651-1660.","keywords":["Sexual Conflict","Fecundity","Quantitative Genetics","Mating Systems","Selection - Sexual","Heritability"],"description":"Many reproductive traits that have evolved under sexual conflict may be influenced by both sexes. Investigation of the genetic architecture of such traits can yield important insight into their evolution, but this entails that the heritable component of variation is estimated for males and females – as an interacting phenotype. We address the lack of research in this area through an investigation of egg production and copula duration in the fruit fly, Drosophila melanogaster. Despite egg production rate being determined by both sexes, which may cause sexual conflict, an assessment of this trait as an interacting phenotype is lacking. It is currently unclear whether copula duration is determined by males and/or females. We found significant female, but not male, genetic variance for egg production rate which may indicate reduced potential for ongoing sexually antagonistic coevolution. In contrast, copula duration was determined by significant genetic variance in both sexes. We also identified genetic variation in egg retention among virgin females. Although previously identified in wild populations, it is unclear why this should be present in a laboratory stock. This study provides a novel insight into the shared genetic architecture of reproductive traits that are the subject of sexual conflict.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qr92p/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.59097","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.59097","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24495114","doi:10.1111/evo.12376"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qr92p"}}