{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-03-19T21:19:04Z","author":["Sanders, Nathan J.","Souza, Lara","Classen, Aimée T.","Cregger, Melissa A.","Wright, Phoebe"],"title":"Data from: The effects of insects, nutrients, and plant invasion on community structure and function above- and belowground","host":"Wright P, Cregger MA, Souza L, Sanders NJ, Classen AT (2014) The effects of insects, nutrients, and plant invasion on community structure and function above- and belowground. Ecology and Evolution 4(6): 732-742.","keywords":["Bacteria","old fields","fungi","fertilization","biomass","enzymes","invasive plants","nitrogen"],"description":"Soil nutrient availability, invasive plants, and insect presence can directly alter ecosystem structure and function, but less is known about how these factors may interact. In this 6-year study in an old-field ecosystem, we manipulated insect abundance (reduced and control), the propagule pressure of an invasive nitrogen-fixing plant (propagules added and control), and soil nutrient availability (nitrogen added, nitrogen reduced and control) in a fully crossed, completely randomized plot design. We found that nutrient amendment and, occasionally, insect abundance interacted with the propagule pressure of an invasive plant to alter above- and belowground structure and function at our site. Not surprisingly, nutrient amendment had a direct effect on aboveground biomass and soil nutrient mineralization. The introduction of invasive nitrogen-fixing plant propagules interacted with nutrient amendment and insect presence to alter soil bacterial abundance and the activity of the microbial community. While the larger-scale, longer-term bulk measurements such as biomass production and nutrient mineralization responded to the direct effects of our treatments, the shorter-term and dynamic microbial communities tended to respond to interactions among our treatments. Our results indicate that soil nutrients, invasive plants, and insect herbivores determine both above- and belowground responses, but whether such effects are independent versus interdependent varies with scale.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gk23s/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.57255","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.57255","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24683456","doi:10.1002/ece3.961"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gk23s"}}