{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-10-20T19:18:13Z","author":["Clemento, Anthony J.","Abadía-Cardoso, Alicia","Starks, Hilary A.","Garza, John C."],"title":"Data from: Discovery and characterization of single nucleotide polymorphisms in Chinook salmon, Oncorhynchus tshawytscha","host":"Clemento AJ, Abadía-Cardoso A, Starks HA, Garza JC (2011) Discovery and characterization of single nucleotide polymorphisms in Chinook salmon, Oncorhynchus tshawytscha. Molecular Ecology Resources 11(suppl. 1): 50-66.","keywords":["Fisheries Management","Population Genetics - Empirical","Conservation Genetics","Fish","Ecological Genetics"],"description":"Molecular population genetics of non-model organisms has been dominated by the use of microsatellite loci over the last two decades. The availability of extensive genomic resources for many species is contributing to a transition to the use of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) for the study of many natural populations. Here we describe the discovery of a large number of SNPs in Chinook salmon, one of the world’s most important fishery species, through large-scale Sanger sequencing of expressed sequence tag (EST) regions. More than 3MB of sequence was collected in a survey of variation in more than 131KB of unique genic regions, from more than 225 separate ESTs, in a diverse ascertainment panel of 24 salmon. This survey yielded 117 TaqMan (5’ nuclease) assays, almost all from separate EST regions, which were validated in population samples from 5 major stocks of salmon from the three largest basins on the Pacific coast of the coterminous United States: the Sacramento, Klamath and Columbia Rivers. The proportion of these loci that was variable in each of these stocks ranged from 86.3 to 90.6% and the mean minor allele frequency ranged from 0.194 to 0.236. There was substantial differentiation between populations with these markers, with a mean FST estimate of 0.107, and values for individual loci ranging from 0 to 0.592. This substantial polymorphism and population-specific differentiation indicates that these markers will be broadly useful, including for both pedigree reconstruction and genetic stock identification applications.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8108/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8108","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8108","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02972.x","PMID:21429162"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8108"}}