{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-19T21:43:20Z","author":["Sota, Teiji","Okuzaki, Yutaka"],"title":"Data from: How the length of genital parts affects copulation performance in a carabid beetle: implications for correlated genital evolution between the sexes","host":"Okuzaki Y, Sota T (2014) How the length of genital parts affects copulation performance in a carabid beetle: implications for correlated genital evolution between the sexes. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 27(3): 565–574.","keywords":["Genital dimensions","Adaptation","Sexual selection & conflicts","Insects","Sperm competition"],"description":"To identify factors leading to the correlated evolution of exaggerated male and female genitalia, we studied the effects of the variable dimensions of corresponding functional genital parts (male copulatory piece and female vaginal appendix) on copulatory performance in the polygamous carabid beetle Carabus (Ohomopterus) maiyasanus. We used mating pairs of individuals from two populations to increase the variances in genital dimensions and determined the copulation performance (insemination and spermatophore replacement, and copulation time) in single- and double-mating situations. In single mating, insemination success was not affected by genital dimensions, although the copulation time was significantly shorter when the male aedeagus was longer. In the double-mating experiment, insemination and replacement of spermatophores by the second male succeeded more frequently when the copulatory piece was shorter and the vaginal appendix was longer, and when the difference between the length of the copulatory piece and the vaginal appendix was smaller. Thus, a matching of the corresponding genital parts between the sexes increases the male's reproductive success in sperm competition, but elongation of the copulatory piece cannot be explained simply by the improvement in male reproductive success. We discuss possible factors for the elongation of genital parts in terms of sexual conflict and reproductive interference through interspecific copulation.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gd0nc/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.58058","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.58058","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24471576","doi:10.1111/jeb.12323"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gd0nc"}}