{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-10-25T18:53:57Z","author":["Houck, Marlys L.","Vliet, Kent A.","Charter, Suellen","Austin, James D.","Shirley, Matthew H.","DeSalle, Robert","Blum, Michael J.","Thorbjarnarson, John","Hekkala, Evon","Amato, George"],"title":"Data from: Splitting an ancient icon: mummy DNA resurrects a cryptic Nile crocodile","host":"Hekkala E, Shirley MH, Amato G, Austin JD, Charter S, Thorbjarnarson J, Vliet KA, Houck ML, DeSalle R, Blum MJ (2011) Splitting an ancient icon: mummy DNA resurrects a cryptic Nile crocodile. Molecular Ecology 20(20): 4199-4215.","keywords":["Speciation","Phylogeography","Conservation Genetics","Systematics"],"description":"The Nile crocodile (Crocodylus niloticus) is an ancient icon of both cultural and scientific interest. The species is emblematic of the great civilizations of the Nile River valley and serves as a model for international wildlife conservation. Despite its familiarity, a centuries-long dispute over the taxonomic status of the Nile crocodile remains unresolved. This dispute not only confounds our understanding of the origins and biogeography of the “true crocodiles” of the crown genus Crocodylus, but also complicates conservation and management of this commercially valuable species. We have taken a total evidence approach involving phylogenetic analysis of mitochondrial and nuclear markers as well as karyotype analysis of chromosome number and structure to assess the monophyletic status of the Nile crocodile. Samples were collected from throughout Africa, covering all major bioregions. We also utilized specimens from museum collections, including mummified crocodiles from the ancient Egyptian temples at Thebes and the Grottes de Samoun, to reconstruct the genetic profiles of extirpated populations. Our analyses reveal a cryptic evolutionary lineage within the Nile crocodile that elucidates the biogeographic history of the genus and clarifies long-standing arguments over the species’ taxonomic identity and conservation status. An examination of crocodile mummy haplotypes indicates that the cryptic lineage corresponds to an earlier description of C. suchus and suggests that both African Crocodylus lineages historically inhabited the Nile River. Recent survey efforts indicate that C. suchus is declining or extirpated throughout much of its distribution. Without proper recognition of this cryptic species, current sustainable use-based management policies for the Nile crocodile may do more harm than good.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34228","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34228","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21906195","doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05245.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s1m9h"}}