{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-28T15:00:19Z","author":["Moreno, Marta","Pinto, Joao","Donnelly, Martin J.","Gomes, Bruno","Weetman, David","della Torre, Alessandra","Elissa, Nohal","Santalomazza, Federica","Egyir-Yawson, Alexander","Caccone, Adalgisa","Vicente, José L.","Simard, Frederic","Charlwood, Jacques D."],"title":"Data from: Geographic population structure of the African malaria vector Anopheles gambiae suggests a role for the forest-savannah biome transition as a barrier to gene flow","host":"Pinto J, Egyir-Yawson A, Vicente JL, Gomes B, Santalomazza F, Moreno M, Charlwood JD, Simard F, Elissa N, Weetman D, Donnelly MJ, Caccone A, della Torre A (2013) Geographic population structure of the African malaria vector Anopheles gambiae suggests a role for the forest-savannah biome transition as a barrier to gene flow. Evolutionary Applications 6(6): 910-924.","keywords":["Speciation","Population Genetics - Empirical","Parasitology"],"description":"The primary Afrotropical malaria mosquito vector Anopheles gambiae sensu stricto has a complex population structure. In western Africa, this species is split into two molecular forms and displays local and regional variation in chromosomal arrangements and behaviours. To investigate patterns of macro-geographic population substructure, 25 An. gambiae samples from 12 African countries were genotyped at 13 microsatellite loci. This analysis detected the presence of additional population structuring, with the M-form being subdivided into distinct west, central and southern African genetic clusters. These clusters are coincident with the central African rainforest belt and northern and southern savannah biomes, which suggests restrictions to gene flow associated with the transition between these biomes. By contrast geographically patterned population substructure appears much weaker within the S-form.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.201rm/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49333","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49333","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24062800","doi:10.1111/eva.12075"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.201rm"}}