{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-09-02T19:40:28Z","author":["St-Cyr, Jérôme","Jeukens, Julie","Boyle, Brian","Kukavica-Ibrulj, Irena","Lévesque, Roger C","Bernatchez, Louis"],"title":"Data from: BAC library construction, screening and clone sequencing of lake whitefish (Coregonus clupeaformis, Salmonidae) towards the elucidation of adaptive species divergence","host":"Jeukens J, Boyle B, Kukavica-Ibrulj I, St-Cyr J, Lévesque RC, Bernatchez L (2011) BAC library construction, screening and clone sequencing of lake whitefish (Coregonus clupeaformis, Salmonidae) towards the elucidation of adaptive species divergence. Molecular Ecology 11(3): 541–549.","keywords":["Speciation","Genomics/Proteomics","Fish","Molecular Evolution"],"description":"Genomic DNA sequences and other genomic resources are essential towards the elucidation of the genomic bases of adaptive divergence and reproductive isolation. Here, we describe the construction, characterization and screening of a nonarrayed BAC library for lake whitefish (Coregonus clupeaformis). We then show how the combined use of BAC library screening and next-generation sequencing can lead to efficient full-length assembly of candidate genes. The lake whitefish BAC library consists of 181 050 clones derived from a single heterozygous fish. The mean insert size is 92 Kb, representing 5.2 haploid genome equivalents. Ten BAC clones were isolated following a quantitative real-time PCR screening approach that targeted five previously identified candidate genes. Sequencing of these clones on a 454 GS FLX system yielded 178 000 reads with a mean length of 358 bp, for a total of 63.8 Mb. De novo assembly and annotation then allowed retrieval of contigs corresponding to each candidate gene, which also contained up- and/or downstream noncoding sequences. These results suggest that the lake whitefish BAC library combined with next-generation sequencing technologies will be key resources to achieve a better understanding of both adaptive divergence and reproductive isolation in lake whitefish species pairs as well as salmonid evolution in general.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8100/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.8100/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.8100/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.8100/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.8100/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8100","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8100","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21481212","doi:10.1111/j.1755-0998.2011.02982.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8100"}}