{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-26T22:04:32Z","author":["Castellanos, Maria Clara","Pausas, Juli G.","Moreira, Bruno"],"title":"Data from: Genetic component of flammability variation in a Mediterranean shrub","host":"Moreira B, Castellanos MC, Pausas JG (2014) Genetic component of flammability variation in a Mediterranean shrub. Molecular Ecology 23(5): 1213-1223.","keywords":["plant flammability","Population Genetics - Empirical","Natural Selection and Contemporary Evolution","fire regime","phenotype-loci associations","AFLP genome scan","Life History Evolution","Population Ecology","obligate seeder"],"description":"Recurrent fires impose a strong selection pressure in many ecosystems worldwide. In such ecosystems, plant flammability is of paramount importance because it enhances population persistence, particularly in non-resprouting species. Indeed, there is evidence of phenotypic divergence of flammability under different fire regimes. Our general hypothesis is that flammability-enhancing traits are adaptive; here we test whether they have a genetic component. To test this hypothesis we used the post-fire obligate seeder Ulex parviflorus from sites historically exposed to different fire recurrence. We associated molecular variation in potentially adaptive loci detected with a genomic scan (using AFLP markers) to individual phenotypic variability in flammability across fire regimes. We found that at least 42% of the phenotypic variation in flammability was explained by the genetic divergence in a subset of AFLP loci. In spite of generalised gene flow, the genetic variability was structured by differences in fire recurrence. Our results provide the first field evidence supporting that traits enhancing plant flammability have a genetic component and thus can be responding to natural selection driven by fire. These results highlight the importance of flammability as an adaptive trait in fire-prone ecosystems.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.c62kd/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.58360","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.58360","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24433213","doi:10.1111/mec.12665"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.c62kd"}}