{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-07T06:30:04Z","author":["Safran, Rebecca J.","Lovette, Irby","Dor, Roi","Lotem, Arnon","Vortman, Yoni"],"title":"Data from: Multiple sexual signals and behavioral reproductive isolation in a diverging population","host":"Vortman Y, Lotem A, Dor R, Lovette I, Safran RJ (2013) Multiple sexual signals and behavioral reproductive isolation in a diverging population. The American Naturalist 182(4): 514-523.","keywords":["Bird","Ecology: behavioral","Mate choice","Selection: sexual","Speciation: reinforcement"],"description":"Sexual trait divergence has been shown to play a role in the evolution of reproductive isolation. While variation in multiple sexual signals is common among closely related species, little is known about the role of these different axes of phenotype variation with respect to the evolution of behavioral reproductive isolation. Here we study a unique population of barn swallows (Hirundo rustica transitiva) which can only be distinguished phenotypically from its neighboring populations based on two features of male plumage: exaggerated expression of both long tail streamers and dark ventral coloration. Using phenotype manipulation experiments, we conducted a paternity study to examine whether both traits are sexually selected. Our results show that an exaggerated form of the local male phenotype (with both tail elongation and color darkening) is favored by local females whereas males whose phenotypes were manipulated to look like males of neighboring subspecies suffered paternity losses from their social mates. These results confirm the multiple signaling role of the unique tail and color combination in our diverging population and suggest a novel possibility according to which multiple sexual signals may also be used to discriminate among males from nearby populations when pre-zygotic reproductive isolation is adaptive.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.g8n63/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.g8n63/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.g8n63/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49518","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49518","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/671908","PMID:24021403"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g8n63"}}