{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-01-15T16:35:24Z","author":["Richard, Antoine","Wang, Jinliang","Bernatchez, Louis","Dionne, Mélanie"],"title":"Data from: Does catch and release affect the mating system and individual reproductive success of wild Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar L.)?","host":"Richard A, Dionne M, Wang J, Bernatchez L (2012) Does catch and release affect the mating system and individual reproductive success of wild Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar L.)? Molecular Ecology 22(1): 187-200.","keywords":["Fisheries Management","Sexual Selection","fitness","Fish","Salmo salar","Wildlife Management"],"description":"In this study, we documented the breeding system of a wild population of Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar L.) by genetically sampling every returning adult and assessed the determinants of individual fitness. We then quantified the impacts of catch and release (C&R) on mating and reproductive success. Both sexes showed high variance in individual reproductive success, and the estimated standardized variance was higher for males (2.86) than for females (0.73). We found a weak positive relationship between body size and fitness and observed that fitness was positively correlated with the number of mates, especially in males. Mature male parr sired 44% of the analysed offspring. The impact of C&R on the number of offspring was size dependent, as the reproductive success of larger fish was more impaired than smaller ones. Also, there was an interactive negative effect of water temperature and air exposure time on reproductive success of C&R salmon. This study improves our understanding of the complex reproductive biology of the Atlantic salmon and is the first to investigate the impact of C&R on reproductive success. Our study expands the management toolbox of appropriate C&R practices that promote conservation of salmon populations and limit negative impacts on mating and reproductive success.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.m2m8f/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.m2m8f/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.m2m8f/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.m2m8f/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42221","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42221","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12102","PMID:23163395"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.m2m8f"}}