{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["0014-3820","Evolution"],"keywords":["Phenotypic Plasticity","Quantitative Genetics","Predation","Mating Systems","Inbreeding","Life-History Evolution"],"host":"Auld JR (2010) The effects of predation risk on mating system expression in a freshwater snail. Evolution 64(12): 3476-3494.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1690/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.1690","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T20:49:13Z","author":"Auld, Josh R","title":"Data from: The effects of predation risk on mating system expression in a freshwater snail","description":"Environmental effects on mating system expression are central to understanding mating system evolution in nature.  Here I report the results from a quantitative-genetic experiment aimed at understanding the role of predation risk in the expression and evolution of life-history and mating-system traits in a hermaphroditic freshwater snail (Physa acuta).  I reared 30 full-sib families in four environments that factorially contrast predation risk and mate availability and measured age/size at first reproduction, growth rate, a morphological defense, and the early survival of outcrossed/selfed eggs that were laid under predator/no-predator conditions.  I evaluated the genetic basis of trade-offs among traits and the stability of the G matrix across environments.  Mating reduced growth while predation risk increased growth, but the effects of mating were weaker for predator-induced snails and the effects of predation risk were weaker for snails without mates.  Predation risk reduced the amount of time that individuals waited before self-fertilizing and reduced inbreeding depression in the offspring.  There was a positive among-family relationship between the amount of time that individuals delayed selfing under predation risk and the magnitude of inbreeding depression.  These results highlight several potential roles of enemies in mating-system expression and evolution.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.1690","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01079.","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1690"}}