{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-06T16:26:25Z","author":["Maklakov, Alexei A.","Berger, David","Lind, Martin I.","Goenaga, Julieta","Arnqvist, Göran","Grieshop, Karl"],"title":"Data from: Intralocus sexual conflict and environmental stress","host":"Berger D, Grieshop K, Lind MI, Goenaga J, Maklakov AA, Arnqvist G (2014) Intralocus sexual conflict and environmental stress. Evolution 68(8): 2184-2196.","keywords":["sexually antagonistic","genetic quality","condition dependence","Adaptation","Selection - Sexual","temperature"],"description":"Intralocus sexual conflict (ISC) occurs when selection at a given locus favors different alleles in males and females, placing a fundamental constraint on adaptation. However, the relative impact of ISC on adaptation may become reduced in stressful environments that expose conditionally deleterious mutations to selection. The genetic correlation for fitness between males and females (rMF) provides a quantification of ISC across the genome. We compared ISC at a benign (29˚C) and a stressful (36˚C) temperature by estimating rMFs in two natural populations of the seed beetle Callosobruchus maculatus using isofemale lines. In one population, we found substantial ISC under benign conditions signified by a negative rMF (-0.51) and, as predicted, a significant reduction of ISC under stress signified by a reversed and positive rMF (0.21). The other population displayed low ISC at both temperatures (rMF: 0.38; 0.40). In both populations, isofemale lines harboring alleles beneficial to males but detrimental to females at benign conditions tended to show overall low fitness under stress. These results offer support for low ISC under stress and suggest that environmentally sensitive and conditionally deleterious alleles that are sexually selected in males mediate changes in ISC. We discuss implications for adaptive evolution in sexually reproducing populations.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.m06s2/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.62816","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.62816","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24766035","doi:10.1111/evo.12439"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.m06s2"}}