{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-20T17:57:34Z","author":["Holekamp, Kay E.","Van Meter, Page E.","Swanson, Eli M."],"title":"Data from: Developmental constraints on behavioral flexibility","host":"Holekamp KE, Swanson EM, Van Meter PE (2013) Developmental constraints on behavioral flexibility. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B 368(1618): 20120350.","keywords":["morphology","behavioural flexibility","maternal effects","evolvability","constraints"],"description":"We suggest that variation in mammalian behavioural flexibility not accounted for by current socioecological models may be explained in part by developmental constraints. From our own work we provide examples of constraints affecting variation in behavioural flexibility, not only among individuals, but also among species and higher taxonomic units. We first implicate organizational maternal effects of androgens in shaping individual differences in aggressive behaviour emitted by female spotted hyenas throughout the lifespan. We then compare carnivores and primates with respect to their locomotor and craniofacial adaptations. We inquire whether antagonistic selection pressures on the skull might impose differential functional constraints on evolvability of skulls and brains in these two orders, thus ultimately affecting behavioural flexibility in each group. We suggest that, even when carnivores and primates would theoretically benefit from the same adaptations with respect to behavioural flexibility, carnivores may nevertheless exhibit less behavioural flexibility than primates because of constraints imposed by past adaptations in the morphology of the limbs and skull. Phylogenetic analysis consistent with this idea suggests greater evolutionary lability in relative brain size within families of primates than carnivores. Thus consideration of developmental constraints may help elucidate variation in mammalian behavioural flexibility.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.305mq/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.305mq/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46379","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46379","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23569298","doi:10.1098/rstb.2012.0350"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.305mq"}}