{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-09-02T20:11:06Z","author":["Rossi, Jean-Pierre","Rousselet, Jerome","Santos, Helena","Burban, Christian","Kerdelhué, Carole","Branco, Manuela"],"title":"Data from: Incipient allochronic speciation in the pine processionary moth Thaumetopoea pityocampa (Lepidoptera: Notodontidae)","host":"Santos H, Burban C, Rousselet J, Rossi JP, Branco M, Kerdelhué C (2010) Incipient allochronic speciation in the pine processionary moth Thaumetopoea pityocampa (Lepidoptera: Notodontidae). Journal of Evolutionary Biology 24(1): 146-158.","keywords":["sympatric speciation","Speciation","Population genetics","pine processionary moth","Life history evolution","Allochronic differentiation","phenology","Molecular evolution","microsatellites","Insects"],"description":"A plausible case of allochronic differentiation, where barrier to gene flow is primarily due to a phenological shift, was recently discovered in Portugal for the pine processionary moth Thaumetopoea pityocampa. Previous results suggested that the observed \"summer population\" (SP) originated from the sympatric winter population (WP). Our objectives were to finely analyse these patterns and test their stability in time, through field monitoring and genetic analyses of larvae and adults across different years. Reproductive activity never overlapped between SP and WP. Microsatellites showed a clear differentiation of the SP, consistent with a strong reduction of gene flow due to the phenological shift. Assignment tests suggested that some individuals shift from the SP to the WP phenology, causing some hybridization. We discuss these patterns and their maintenance over time. This could be a first stage of allochronic speciation and SP should be considered as a distinct phenological race.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2001/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.2001","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.2001","isReferencedBy":["PMID:20964783","doi:10.1111/j.1420-9101.2010.02147.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2001"}}