{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Systematic Biology","keywords":["DGGE","molecular phylogeny","partial mantel tests","cytochrome b sequence","lizards","lineage introgression","historical hypotheses"],"host":"Thorpe RS, Black H, Malhotra A (1996) Matrix correspondence tests on the DNA phylogeny of the Tenerife lacertid elucidate both historical causes and morphological adaptation. Systematic Biology 45(3): 335-343.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.734/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.734","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-28T18:04:58Z","author":["Thorpe, Roger S.","Black, Heather","Malhotra, Anita"],"title":"Data from: Matrix correspondence tests on the DNA phylogeny of the Tenerife lacertid elucidate both historical causes and morphological adaptation","description":"Previous studies using partial regression Mantel tests of matrix correspondence on within-island geographic variation in the color pattern of the Tenerife (Canary Islands) lacertid lizard (Gallotia galloti) support natural selection for different north--south climatically determined biotopes but do not support any historical cause. However, tests on the DNA phylogeny based primarily on population data from 57 localities on Tenerife support the hypothesis that there were populations on two putative precursor islands that have come into secondary contact and introgressed after these islands were joined to form Tenerife by the eruption of the Canadas edifice. Subsequent partial Mantel tests continue to support the hypothesis that color pattern is adapted to the climatic biotopes even when this phylogenetic information is taken into account by (1) testing for color pattern adaptation separately within each lineage and (2) testing for color pattern adaptation across the entire island while considering the molecular phylogenetic relationships as representing an alternative explanation. Selection has largely expunged any trace of the geological history from current morphological variation, and the introgression of these island populations after an estimated 0.7 million years of separation gives an insight into the relationships between allopatric divergence and reproductive isolation.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.734","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1093/sysbio/45.3.335","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.734"}}