{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-04-25T18:54:23Z","author":["Chisholm, Sallie W.","Kashtan, Nadav","Stepanauskas, Ramunas","Biller, Steven J.","Malmstrom, Rex R.","Coe, Allison","Rodrigue, Sébastien","Ding, Huiming","Roggensack, Sara E.","Marttinen, Pekka","Follows, Michael J.","Thompson, Jessie W.","Stocker, Roman"],"title":"Data from: Single-cell genomics reveals hundreds of coexisting subpopulations in wild Prochlorococcus","host":"Kashtan N, Roggensack SE, Rodrigue S, Thompson JW, Biller SJ, Coe A, Ding H, Marttinen P, Malmstrom RR, Stocker R, Follows MJ, Stepanauskas R, Chisholm SW (2014) Single-cell genomics reveals hundreds of coexisting subpopulations in wild Prochlorococcus. Science 344(6182): 416-420.","keywords":["Biodiversity","Environmental microbiology","microbial ecology","Evolution"],"description":"Extensive genomic diversity within coexisting members of a microbial species has been revealed through selected cultured isolates and metagenomic assemblies. Yet, the cell-by-cell genomic composition of wild uncultured populations of co-occurring cells is largely unknown. In this work, we applied large-scale single-cell genomics to study populations of the globally abundant marine cyanobacterium Prochlorococcus. We show that they are composed of hundreds of subpopulations with distinct “genomic backbones,” each backbone consisting of a different set of core gene alleles linked to a small distinctive set of flexible genes. These subpopulations are estimated to have diverged at least a few million years ago, suggesting ancient, stable niche partitioning. Such a large set of coexisting subpopulations may be a general feature of free-living bacterial species with huge populations in highly mixed habitats.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61165","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61165","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24763590","doi:10.1126/science.1248575"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9r0p6"}}