{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-22T19:13:24Z","author":["Lee, Ernest K.","Ward, Philip S.","Atallah, Joel","Johnson, Brian R.","Chiu, Joanna C.","Borowiec, Marek L."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenomics resolves evolutionary relationships among ants, bees, and wasps","host":"Johnson BR, Borowiec ML, Chiu JC, Lee EK, Atallah J, Ward PS (2013) Phylogenomics resolves evolutionary relationships among ants, bees, and wasps. Current Biology 23(20): 2058–2062.","keywords":["phylogenomics","evolution of aculeates","transcriptomics","eusociality"],"description":"Eusocial behavior has arisen in few animal groups, most notably in the aculeate Hymenoptera, a clade comprising ants, bees, and stinging wasps. Phylogeny is crucial to understanding the evolution of the salient features of these insects, including eusociality. Yet the phylogenetic relationships among the major lineages of aculeate Hymenoptera remain contentious. We address this problem here by generating and analyzing genomic data for a representative series of taxa. We obtain a single well-resolved and strongly supported tree, robust to multiple methods of phylogenetic inference. Apoidea (spheciform wasps and bees) and ants are sister groups, a novel finding that contradicts earlier views that ants are closer to ectoparasitoid wasps. Vespid wasps (paper wasps, yellow jackets, and relatives) are sister to all other aculeates except chrysidoids. Thus, all eusocial species of Hymenoptera are contained within two major groups, characterized by transport of larval provisions and nest construction, likely prerequisites for the evolution of eusociality. These two lineages are interpolated among three other clades of wasps whose species are predominantly ectoparasitoids on concealed hosts, the inferred ancestral condition for aculeates. This phylogeny provides a new framework for exploring the evolution of nesting, feeding, and social behavior within the stinging Hymenoptera.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jt440/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53201","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53201","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1016/j.cub.2013.08.050","PMID:24094856"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jt440"}}