{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-28T14:36:34Z","author":["Camargo, Arley","Avila, Luciano Javier","Sites Jr., Jack W.","Morando, Mariana"],"title":"Data from: Species delimitation with ABC and other coalescent-based methods: a test of accuracy with simulations and an empirical example with lizards of the Liolaemus darwinii complex (Squamata: Liolaemidae)","host":"Camargo A, Morando M, Avila LJ, Sites JWJ (2012) Species delimitation with ABC and other coalescent-based methods: a test of accuracy with simulations and an empirical example with lizards of the Liolaemus darwinii complex (Squamata: Liolaemidae). Evolution 66(9): 2834–2849.","keywords":["Gene Flow","Speciation","Gene trees","Simulation","Divergence"],"description":"Species delimitation is a major research focus in evolutionary biology because accurate species boundaries are a prerequisite for the study of speciation. New species delimitation methods (SDMs) can accommodate non-monophyletic species and gene tree discordance as a result of incomplete lineage sorting via the coalescent model, but do not explicitly accommodate gene flow after divergence. Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) can incorporate gene flow and estimate other relevant parameters of the speciation process while testing alternative species delimitation hypotheses. We evaluated the accuracy of BPP, SpeDeSTEM, and ABC for delimiting species using simulated data and applied these methods to empirical data from lizards of the Liolaemus darwinii complex. Overall, BPP was the most accurate, ABC showed an intermediate accuracy, and SpeDeSTEM was the least accurate under most simulated conditions. All three SDMs showed lower accuracy when speciation occurred despite gene flow, as found in previous studies, but ABC was the method with the smallest decrease in accuracy. All three SDMs consistently supported the distinctness of southern and northern lineages within L. darwinii. These SDMs based on genetic data should be complemented with novel SDMs based on morphological and ecological data to achieve truly integrative and statistically robust approaches to species discovery.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652/10"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38346","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38346","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01640.x","PMID:22946806"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.4409k652"}}