{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-12T18:31:21Z","author":["Burke, Terry","Sin, Yung Wa","Macdonald, David W.","Annavi, Geetha","Newman, Chris","Dugdale, Hannah L."],"title":"Data from: Pathogen burden, co-infection and major histocompatibility complex variability in the European badger (Meles meles)","host":"Sin YW, Annavi G, Dugdale HL, Newman C, Burke T, Macdonald DW (2014) Pathogen burden, co-infection and major histocompatibility complex variability in the European badger (Meles meles). Molecular Ecology, online in advance of print.","keywords":["heterozygote advantage hypothesis","rare allele advantage","pathogen-mediated selection","host-parasite co-evolution","Evolutionary arms race","frequency-dependent selection"],"description":"Pathogen-mediated selection is thought to maintain the extreme diversity in the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) genes, operating through the heterozygote advantage, rare-allele advantage and fluctuating selection mechanisms. Heterozygote advantage (i.e., recognizing and binding a wider range of antigens than homozygotes) is expected to be more detectable when multiple pathogens are considered simultaneously. Here, we test if MHC diversity in a wild population of European badgers (Meles meles) is driven by pathogen-mediated selection. We examined individual prevalence (infected or not), infection intensity and co-infection of 13 pathogens from a range of taxa, and examined their relationships with MHC class I and class II variability. This population has a variable, but relatively low, number of MHC alleles and is infected by a variety of naturally-occurring pathogens, making it very suitable for the investigation of MHC-pathogen relationships. We found associations between pathogen infections and specific MHC haplotypes and alleles. Co-infection status was not correlated with MHC heterozygosity, but there was evidence of heterozygote advantage against individual pathogen infections. This suggests that rare-allele advantages and/or fluctuating selection, as well as heterozygote advantage are likely to be the selective forces shaping MHC diversity in this species. We show stronger evidence for MHC-associations with infection intensity than for prevalence, and conclude that examining both pathogen prevalence and infection intensity is important. Moreover, examination of a large number and diversity of pathogens, and both MHC class I and II genes (which have different functions), provide an improved understanding of the mechanisms driving MHC diversity.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.6408r/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.6408r/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.69966","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.69966","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25211523","doi:10.1111/mec.12917"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6408r"}}