{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-09T18:43:30Z","author":["Lemoine, Nathan P.","Burkepile, Deron E.","Parker, John D."],"title":"Data from: Variable effects of temperature on insect herbivory","host":"Lemoine NP, Burkepile DE, Parker JD (2014) Variable effects of temperature on insect herbivory. PeerJ 2: e376.","keywords":["Hierarchical model","Thermal response curve","Climate change"],"description":"Rising temperatures can influence the top-down control of plant biomass by increasing herbivore metabolic demands. Unfortunately, we know relatively little about the effects of temperature on herbivory rates for most insect herbivores in a given community. Evolutionary history, adaptation to local environments, and dietary factors may lead to variable thermal response curves across different species. Here we characterized the effect of temperature on herbivory rates for 21 herbivore-plant pairs, encompassing 14 herbivore and 12 plant species. We show that overall consumption rates increase with temperature between 20 and 30  C but do not increase further with increasing temperature. However, there is substantial variation in thermal responses among individual herbivore-plant pairs at the highest temperatures. Over one third of the herbivore-plant pairs showed declining consumption rates at high temperatures, while an approximately equal number showed increasing consumption rates. Such variation existed even within herbivore species, as some species exhibited idiosyncratic thermal response curves on different host plants. Thus, rising temperatures, particularly with respect to climate change, may have highly variable effects on plant-herbivore interactions and, ultimately, top-down control of plant biomass.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.9fd75/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.9fd75/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.63641","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.63641","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.7717/peerj.376","PMID:24860701"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9fd75"}}