{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-08T17:04:12Z","author":["Lejzerowicz, Franck","Decelle, Johan","Majewski, Wojciech","Martinez Arbizu, Pedro","Szczuciński, Witold","Pawlowski, Jan","Esling, Philippe","Obadia, Cyril"],"title":"Data from: Ancient DNA complements microfossil record in deep-sea subsurface sediments","host":"Lejzerowicz F, Esling P, Majewski W, Szczuciński W, Decelle J, Obadia C, Martinez Arbizu P, Pawlowski J (2013) Ancient DNA complements microfossil record in deep-sea subsurface sediments. Biology Letters 9(4): 20130283.","keywords":["high-throughput sequencing","micropaleontology","ancient DNA","deep-sea sediments","paleogenomics"],"description":"Deep-sea subsurface sediments are the most important archives of marine biodiversity. Until now, these archives were studied mainly using the microfossil record, disregarding large amounts of DNA accumulated on the deep-sea floor. Accessing ancient DNA (aDNA) molecules preserved down-core would offer unique insights into the history of marine biodiversity, including both fossilized and non-fossilized taxa. Here, we recover aDNA of eukaryotic origin across four cores collected at abyssal depths in the South Atlantic, in up to 32.5 thousand-year-old sediment layers. Our study focuses on foraminifera and radiolaria, two major groups of marine microfossils also comprising diverse non-fossilized taxa. We describe their assemblages in down-core sediment layers applying both micropaleontological and environmental DNA sequencing approaches. Short fragments of the foraminiferal and radiolarian SSU rRNA gene recovered from sedimentary DNA extracts provide evidence that eukaryotic aDNA is preserved in deep-sea sediments encompassing the Last Glacial Maximum. Most aDNA were assigned to non-fossilized taxa that also dominate in molecular studies of modern environments. Our study reveals the potential of aDNA to better document the evolution of past marine ecosystems and opens new horizons for the development of deep-sea palaeogenomics.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b5m0j/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.48591","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.48591","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rsbl.2013.0283","PMID:23658006"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b5m0j"}}