{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-12T17:25:12Z","author":["Johannesen, Jes","Albert, Andreas","Maixner, Michael"],"title":"Data from: Survival relative to new and ancestral host plants, phytoplasma infection and genetic constitution in host races of a polyphagous insect disease vector","host":"Maixner M, Albert A, Johannesen J (2014) Survival relative to new and ancestral host plants, phytoplasma infection and genetic constitution in host races of a polyphagous insect disease vector. Ecology and Evolution 4(15): 3082-3092.","keywords":["gene-behaviour interaction","tritrophic interaction","stolbur phytoplasma","microsatellites","host race evolution"],"description":"Dissemination of vectorborne diseases depends strongly on the vector's host range and the pathogen's reservoir range. Because vectors interact with pathogens, the direction and strength of a vector's host shift is vital for understanding epidemiology and is embedded in the framework of ecological specialization. This study investigates survival in host-race evolution of a polyphagous insect disease vector, Hyalesthes obsoletus, whether survival is related to the direction of the host shift (from field bindweed to stinging nettle), the interaction with plant-specific strains of obligate vectored pathogens/symbionts (stolbur phytoplasma), and whether survival is related to genetic differentiation between the host races. We used a twice repeated, identical nested experimental design to study survival of the vector on alternative hosts and relative to infection status. Survival was tested with Kaplan–Meier analyses, while genetic differentiation between vector populations was quantified with microsatellite allele frequencies. We found significant direct effects of host plant (reduced survival on wrong hosts) and sex (males survive longer than females) in both host races and relative effects of host (nettle animals more affected than bindweed animals) and sex (males more affected than females). Survival of bindweed animals was significantly higher on symptomatic than nonsymptomatic field bindweed, but in the second experiment only. Infection potentially had a positive effect on survival in nettle animals but due to low infection rates the results remain suggestive. Genetic differentiation was not related to survival. Greater negative plant-transfer effect but no negative effect of stolbur in the derived host race suggests preadaptation to the new pathogen/symbiont strain before strong diversifying selection during the specialization process. Physiological maladaptation or failure to accept the ancestral plant will have similar consequences, namely positive assortative mating within host races and a reduction in the likelihood of oviposition on the alternative plant and thus the acquisition of alternative stolbur strains.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.dh05q/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.dh05q/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67078","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67078","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1002/ece3.1158","PMID:25247065"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.dh05q"}}