{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-03T14:25:33Z","author":["Schwab, Daniel B.","Moczek, Armin P."],"title":"Data from: Resource allocation during ontogeny is influenced by genetic, developmental, and ecological factors in the horned beetle, Onthophagus taurus","host":"Schwab DB, Moczek AP (2014) Resource allocation during ontogeny is influenced by genetic, developmental, and ecological factors in the horned beetle, Onthophagus taurus. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1793): 20141625.","description":"Resource allocation trade-offs arise when developing organs are in competition for a limited pool of resources to sustain growth and differentiation. Such competition may constrain the maximal size to which structures can grow and may force a situation in which the evolutionary elaboration of one structure may only be possible at the expense of another. However, recent studies have called into question both the consistency and evolutionary importance of resource allocation trade-offs. This study focuses on a well-described trade-off between the horns and eyes of Onthophagus beetles and assesses the degree to which it is influenced by genetic, developmental and ecological conditions. Contrary to expectations, we observed that trade-off signatures (i) were mostly absent within natural populations, (ii) mostly failed to match naturally evolved divergences in horn investment among populations, (iii) were subject to differential changes in F1 populations derived from divergent field populations and (iv) remained largely unaffected by developmental genetic manipulations of horn investment. Collectively, our results demonstrate that populations subject to different ecological conditions exhibit different patterns of, and differential plasticity in, resource allocation. Further, variation in ecological conditions, rather than canalized developmental mechanisms, may determine whether and to what degree morphological structures engage in resource allocation trade-offs.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jg43t/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68875","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68875","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.1625","PMID:25186002"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jg43t"}}