{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-06-26T16:03:53Z","author":["Ellegren, Hans","Mueller, Jakob C.","Schielzeth, Holger","Kempenaers, Bart","Forstmeier, Wolfgang"],"title":"Data from: Heterozygosity-fitness correlations in zebra finches: microsatellite markers can be better than their reputation","host":"Forstmeier W, Schielzeth H, Mueller JC, Ellegren H, Kempenaers B (2012) Heterozygosity-fitness correlations in zebra finches: microsatellite markers can be better than their reputation. Molecular Ecology 21(13): 3237-3249.","keywords":["Population Genetics - Empirical","Conservation Genetics","Inbreeding","Birds"],"description":"Numerous studies have reported associations between heterozygosity in microsatellite markers and fitness-related traits (heterozygosity-fitness correlations, HFCs). However, it has often been questioned whether HFCs reflect general inbreeding depression, because a small panel of microsatellite markers does not reflect very well an individual’s inbreeding coefficient (F) as calculated from a pedigree. Here we challenge this prevailing view. Due to chance events during Mendelian segregation, an individual’s realized proportion of the genome that is identical by descent (IBD) may substantially deviate from the pedigree-based expectation (i.e. F). This Mendelian noise may result in a weak correlation between F and multi-locus heterozygosity, but this does not imply that multi-locus heterozygosity is a bad estimator of realized IBD. We examined correlations between 11 fitness-related traits measured in up to 1,192 captive zebra finches and three measures of inbreeding: (1) heterozygosity across 11 microsatellite markers, (2) heterozygosity across 1,359 SNP markers, and (3) F, based on a 5-generation pedigree. All 11 phenotypic traits showed positive relationships with measures of heterozygosity, especially traits that are most closely related to fitness. Remarkably, the small panel of microsatellite markers produced equally strong HFCs as the large panel of SNP markers, and both marker-based approaches produced stronger correlations with phenotypes than the pedigree-based F. We argue that a small panel of microsatellites with high allelic richness may better reflect an individual’s realized IBD than previously appreciated, especially in species like the zebra finch, where much of the genome is inherited in large blocks that rarely experience cross-over during meiosis.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3/14"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38381","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38381","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05593.x","PMID:22554318"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6v0h65g3"}}