{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-04T14:29:27Z","author":["Zane, Lorenzo","Cariani, Alessia","Tinti, Fausto","Farrell, Edward","Riginella, Emilio","Mazzoldi, Carlotta","Marino, Ilaria"],"title":"Data from: New molecular tools for the identification of two endangered smooth-hound sharks, Mustelus mustelus and Mustelus punctulatus","keywords":["Mustelus","genetic identification","smooth-hound sharks","ITS2 Subject area: Conservation genetics and biodiversity","microsatellite loci","mitochondrial DNA"],"description":"The smooth-hounds represent a significant proportion of the elasmobranch catch in the Adriatic basin of the Mediterranean Sea, where the common (Mustelus mustelus) and blackspotted (M. punctulatus) smooth-hounds co-occur. The two species share several morphological and morphometric characters that lead to frequent misidentification. In order to provide information useful for their species identification, we performed a morphological identification of several Mustelus specimens to select individuals unambiguously attributed to one of the two species, and assayed these with three new molecular markers. First, we developed and validated a mitochondrial DNA assay based on species-specific amplification of the cytochrome oxidase subunit 1 (COI). Second, a fragment analysis of 15 microsatellites cross-amplified from several triakid species was performed to identify diagnostic loci. Finally, a length difference was identified in the internal transcribed spacer 2 (ITS2) region and a diagnostic test based on its amplification was established. All the samples classified morphologically as Mustelus mustelus and M. punctulatus showed a species-specific profile using all the three molecular markers. In addition, cross-amplification of microsatellites allowed identification of nine highly polymorphic loci that will be useful for the study of the mating system and population differentiation of the two species.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.39q83/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.39q83/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70172","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70172","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.39q83"}}