{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-08-17T18:06:18Z","author":["Gashi, Agim","Ibrahimi, Halil","Grapci-Kotori, Linda","Kučinić, Mladen"],"title":"Data from: The caddisfly fauna (Insecta, Trichoptera) of the rivers of the Black Sea basin in Kosovo with distributional data for some rare species","host":"Ibrahimi H, Kučinić M, Gashi A, Grapci-Kotori L (2012) The caddisfly fauna (Insecta, Trichoptera) of the rivers of the Black Sea basin in Kosovo with distributional data for some rare species. ZooKeys 182: 71-85.","keywords":"aquatic insects","description":"Adult caddisfly specimens were collected by the means of UV light trap in twelve stations that belong to the Black Sea water basin in Kosovo. Sixty-five species out of seventy-six reported in this paper are first records for the Kosovo caddisfly fauna. Most of the species belong to the Palearctic type of fauna (17) followed by the Euro-Asian group with 16 species, the European group with 10 species, the Middle or South-European group with 7 species, than the Balkanic group, the Balkanic-Carpathian group and the Middle or South-Eastern European group with 6 species each, the Mediterranean group with 5 species and finally the Eurosibirian group with 3 species. A sudden discovery of several species during this investigation (Agapetus delicatulus McLachlan, 1884, Psychomyia klapaleki Malicky, 1995, Tinodes janssensi Jacquemart, 1957, Hydropsyche emarginata Navas, 1923, Drusus botosaneanui Kumanski, 1968, Potamophylax rotundipennis (Brauer, 1857), Potamophylax schmidi Marinković, 1970, Ceraclea albimacula (Rambur, 1842), Helicopsyche bacescui Orghidan & Botosaneanu, 1953, Adicella filicornis Pictet, 1834, Beraea maurus (Curtis, 1834) and Beraeamyia hrabei Mayer, 1937) shows that in future data from poorly investigated areas in Europe will revise the existing knowledge on distribution of these and other species with known limited distributions.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6mg14v2q/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38847","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38847","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22539915","doi:10.3897/zookeys.182.2485"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6mg14v2q"}}