{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","series":"66;;2010","keywords":["new species","Biodiversity hotspot","biogeography","phylogenetics","taxonomy"],"host":"Blackburn DC, Gvoždík V, Leaché AD (2010) A new squeaker frog (Arthroleptidae: Arthroleptis) from the mountains of Cameroon and Nigeria. Herpetologica 66: 335-348.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1916/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.1916","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-09-02T17:14:07Z","author":["Gvoždík, Václav","Blackburn, David C","Leaché, Adam D"],"title":"Data from: A new squeaker frog (Arthroleptidae: Arthroleptis) from the mountains of Cameroon and Nigeria","description":"A new species of squeaker frog (genus Arthroleptis) is described from the northern mountains\nof the Cameroon Volcanic Line, a species-rich region within the West African biodiversity hotspot. This new\nspecies is associated with human-altered landscapes, including farms and grasslands, and is known from the\nhighland areas near Bamenda, including Mt. Oku, Cameroon, as well as the Obudu and Mambilla Plateaus of\neastern Nigeria. The known distribution suggests that it may eventually also be found throughout the Acha-\nTugi Ridge that traverses the Cameroon–Nigeria border. More than 40 years ago, a specimen from one of\nthese populations was recognized as probably representing a new species, but no further work was published\non this material. We posit that the taxonomy of this new species has proven problematic because of\nmorphological similarity to Arthroleptis poecilonotus. Although in some ways resembling A. poecilonotus, a\nmolecular phylogeny based on mitochondrial gene sequence data demonstrates that the new species is not\nclosely related to A. poecilonotus and, instead, forms a clade with A. krokosua, A. perreti, and A. variabilis.\nThe new species is diagnosable by the combination of medium–small body size (24–29 mm snout–vent length\nin adult females), the color patterns of the venter and head, and a relatively stout hindlimb with a prominent\ninner metatarsal tubercle. The description of this new species further highlights these mountains as an\nimportant region of endemism within the Cameroon Volcanic Line.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.1916","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1655/HERPETOLOGICA-D-10-00015.1","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1916"}}