{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-19T20:47:52Z","author":["Byrne, Margaret","Millar, Melissa Ann"],"title":"Data from: Cryptic divergent lineages of Pultenaea pauciflora M.B. Scott (Fabaceae, Mirbelieae) exhibit different evolutionary history","host":"Millar MA, Byrne M (2013) Cryptic divergent lineages of Pultenaea pauciflora M.B. Scott (Fabaceae, Mirbelieae) exhibit different evolutionary history. Biological Journal of the Linnean Society 108(4): 871–881.","keywords":["fragmentation","conservation genetics","evolutionary significant units","conservation units","evolutionary history","genetic diversity","cryptic species"],"description":"Genetic structure among disjunct population groups of Pultenaea pauciflora was assessed to determine the evolutionary history of this species as a basis for conservation management strategies. Analysis of individuals from all extant populations using 1737 amplified length polymorphism markers revealed two highly divergent genetic entities with strong geographical structuring. Populations located at Narrogin and Brookton clustered together in Bayesian assignment analysis with every individual optimally placed in a single cluster with complete membership. Genetic differentiation between populations in these two areas was very low. Populations at Boddington were highly divergent from those located at Narrogin and Brookton. All individuals from Boddington populations were optimally placed into a second cluster with complete membership. Populations located at Boddington maintain lower levels of allelic diversity, yet greater levels of mean heterozygosity than populations located at Narrogin and Brookton. The degree of genetic differentiation and different patterns of genetic diversity strongly suggest historical divergence and separate evolutionary influences on the two lineages that occur in different ecological habitat. These Evolutionary Significant Units are likely to represent two cryptic sister taxa in the extant populations currently recognized as P. pauciflora, and the reassessment of taxonomic and conservation status of both lineages is required.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5cg14/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.43754","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.43754","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/bij.12002","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5cg14"}}