{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-21T21:09:56Z","author":["Zheng, Sika","Han, Areum","Lin, Chia-Ho","Stoilov, Peter","Black, Douglas L.","Fu, Xiang-Dong","Li, Qin"],"title":"Data from: The splicing regulator PTBP2 controls a program of embryonic splicing required for neuronal maturation","host":"Li Q, Zheng S, Han A, Lin C, Stoilov P, Fu X, Black DL (2014) The splicing regulator PTBP2 controls a program of embryonic splicing required for neuronal maturation. eLife 3: e01201.","keywords":["RNA binding protein","neuron","alternative splicing","neuronal development"],"description":"We show that the splicing regulator PTBP2 controls a genetic program essential for neuronal maturation. Depletion of PTBP2 in developing mouse cortex leads to degeneration of these tissues over the first three postnatal weeks, a time when the normal cortex expands and develops mature circuits. Cultured Ptbp2−/− neurons exhibit the same initial viability as wild type, with proper neurite outgrowth and marker expression. However, these mutant cells subsequently fail to mature and die after a week in culture. Transcriptome-wide analyses identify many exons that share a pattern of mis-regulation in the mutant brains, where isoforms normally found in adults are precociously expressed in the developing embryo. These transcripts encode proteins affecting neurite growth, pre- and post-synaptic assembly, and synaptic transmission. Our results define a new genetic regulatory program, where PTBP2 acts to temporarily repress expression of adult protein isoforms until the final maturation of the neuron.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.58134","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.58134","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.7554/eLife.01201","PMID:24448406"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cv39v"}}