{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-28T22:15:02Z","author":["Brand, Cara L.","Wilkinson, Gerald S.","Rose, Emily G."],"title":"Data from: Rapid evolution of asymmetric reproductive incompatibilities in stalk-eyed flies","host":"Rose EG, Brand CL, Wilkinson GS (2013) Rapid evolution of asymmetric reproductive incompatibilities in stalk-eyed flies. Evolution 68(2): 384–396.","keywords":["Gametic isolation","Conspecific sperm precedence","Speciation","Postcopulatory sexual selection","Teleopsis dalmanni","Hybrid inviability"],"description":"The steps by which isolated populations acquire reproductive incompatibilities remain poorly understood. One potentially important process is postcopulatory sexual selection because it can generate divergence between populations in traits that influence fertilization success after copulation. Here we present a comprehensive analysis of this form of reproductive isolation by conducting reciprocal crosses between variably diverged populations of stalk-eyed flies (Teleopsis dalmanni). First, we measure seven types of reproductive incompatibility between copulation and fertilization. We then compare fertilization success to hatching success to quantify hybrid inviability. Finally, we determine if sperm competition acts to reinforce or counteract any incompatibilities. We find evidence for multiple incompatibilities in most crosses, including failure to store sperm after mating, failure of sperm to reach the site of fertilization, failure of sperm to fertilize eggs, and failure of embryos to develop. Local sperm have precedence over foreign sperm, but this effect is due mainly to differences in sperm transfer and reduced hatching success. Crosses between recently diverged populations are asymmetrical with regard to the degree and type of incompatibility. Because sexual conflict in these flies is low, postcopulatory sexual selection, rather than antagonistic coevolution, likely causes incompatibilities due to mismatches between male and female reproductive traits.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.24r7q/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.24r7q/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55765","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55765","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12307","PMID:24171729"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.24r7q"}}