{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-15T20:52:48Z","author":["Franco, Miguel","Hsu, Joanna S.","Adler, Peter B.","Ray-Mukherjee, Jayanti","Salguero-Gómez, Roberto","Mbeau-Ache, Cyril","Compagnoni, Aldo"],"title":"Data from: Functional traits explain variation in plant life history strategies","host":"Adler PB, Salguero-Gómez R, Compagnoni A, Hsu JS, Ray-Mukherjee J, Mbeau-Ache C, Franco M (2013) Functional traits explain variation in plant life history strategies. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 111(2): 740–745.","keywords":["seed size","wood density","elasticity","vital rates","specific leaf area","matrix population models"],"description":"Ecologists seek general explanations for the dramatic variation in species abundances in space and time. An increasingly popular solution is to predict species distributions, dynamics and responses to environmental change based on easily measured anatomical and morphological traits. Trait-based approaches assume that simple functional traits influence fitness and life history evolution, but rigorous tests of this assumption are lacking because they require quantitative information about the full life-cycles of many species representing different life histories. Here we link a global traits database with empirical matrix population models for 222 species and report strong relationships between functional traits and plant life histories. Species with large seeds, long-lived leaves, or dense wood have slow life histories, with mean fitness (i.e. population growth rates) more strongly influenced by survival than by growth or fecundity, compared to fast life history species with small seeds, short-lived leaves, or soft wood. In contrast to measures of demographic contributions to fitness based on whole life-cycles, analyses focused on raw demographic rates may underestimate the strength of association between traits and mean fitness. Our results help establish the physiological basis for plant life history evolution and show the potential for trait-based approaches in population dynamics.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8g252.2/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.8g252.2/2.1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8g252.2/1.1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8g252.2/3.1"],"identifier_uri":["http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.57427","http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67683"],"oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67683","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24379395","doi:10.1073/pnas.1315179111"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8g252.2"}}