{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-19T13:52:43Z","author":["Pusey, Anne","Plooij, Frans X.","van de Rijt-Plooij, Hetty","Fischer, Martha"],"title":"Data from: Longitudinal recordings of the vocalizations of immature Gombe chimpanzees for developmental studies","host":"Plooij FX, van de Rijt-Plooij H, Fischer M, Pusey A (2014) Longitudinal recordings of the vocalizations of immature Gombe chimpanzees for developmental studies. Scientific Data 1: 140025.","keywords":["chimpanzee","development","vocalizations","sound recordings","infants"],"description":"Many researchers are interested in chimpanzee vocal communication, both as an important aspect of chimpanzee social behavior and as a source of insights into the evolution of human language. Nonetheless, very little is known about how chimpanzee vocal communication develops from infancy to adulthood. The largest dataset of audiorecordings from free-living immature chimpanzees was collected by the late Hetty van de Rijt-Plooij and Frans X. Plooij at Gombe National Park, Tanzania (1971–1973). These recordings have not yet been analysed. Therefore, the most extensive effort to study the development of chimpanzee vocalizations remains unfinished. The audiospecimens total over 10 h on 28 tapes, including 20 tapes focusing on 17 specific immature individuals with a total of 1,136 recordings. In order to make this dataset available to more researchers, the analogue sound recordings were digitized and stored in the Macaulay Library and the Dryad Repository. In addition, the original notes on the contexts of the calls were translated and transcribed from Dutch into English.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/27","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/28","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/26","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/25","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/24","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/23","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/22","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/21","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/20","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80/9"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.65122","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.65122","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1038/sdata.2014.25","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5tq80"}}