{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-04-23T18:24:48Z","author":["Tian-Bi, Yves-Nathan Tah","Jarne, Philippe","N'Goran, Eliézer Kouakou","Utzinger, Jüerg","Konan, Jean-Noel Kouamé"],"title":"Data from: Contrasting the distribution of phenotypic and molecular variation in the freshwater snail Biomphalaria pfeifferi, the intermediate host of Schistosoma mansoni","host":"Tian-Bi YT, Jarne P, Konan JK, Utzinger J, N'Goran EK (2013) Contrasting the distribution of phenotypic and molecular variation in the freshwater snail Biomphalaria pfeifferi, the intermediate host of Schistosoma mansoni. Heredity 110(5): 466–474.","keywords":["population differentiation","microsatellite markers","life-history traits","Qst–Fst analysis"],"description":"Population differentiation was investigated by confronting phenotypic and molecular variation in the highly selfing freshwater snail Biomphalaria pfeifferi, the intermediate host of Schistosoma mansoni. We sampled seven natural populations separated by a few kilometers, and characterized by different habitat regimes (permanent/temporary) and openness (open/closed). A genetic analysis based on five microsatellite markers confirms that B. pfeifferi is a selfer (s≈0.9) and exhibits limited variation within populations. Most pairwise FST were significant indicating marked population structure, though no isolation by distance was detected. Families from the seven populations were monitored under laboratory conditions over two generations (G1 and G2), allowing to record several life-history traits, including growth, fecundity and survival, over 25 weeks. Marked differences were detected among populations for traits expressed early in the life cycle (up to sexual maturity). Age and size at first reproduction had high heritability values, but such a trend was not found for early reproductive traits. In most populations, G1 snails matured later and at a larger size than G2 individuals. Individuals from permanent habitats matured at a smaller size and were more fecund than those from temporary habitats. The mean phenotypic differentiation over all populations (QST) was lower than the mean genetic differentiation (FST), suggesting stabilizing selection. However, no difference was detected between QST and FST for both habitat regime and habitat openness.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.pq56h/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.pq56h/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44680","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44680","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2012.115","PMID:23321708"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pq56h"}}