{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-13T15:06:37Z","author":["Schindler, Daniel E.","Griffiths, Jennifer R.","Seeb, Lisa W."],"title":"Data from: How stock of origin affects performance of individuals across a meta-ecosystem: an example from Sockeye salmon","host":"Griffiths JR, Schindler DE, Seeb LW (2013) How stock of origin affects performance of individuals across a meta-ecosystem: an example from Sockeye salmon. PLoS ONE 8(3): e58584.","keywords":["single nucleotide polymorphisms","meta-ecosystem","body condition","lakes","connectivity","sockeye salmon"],"description":"Connectivity among diverse habitats can buffer populations from adverse environmental conditions, influence the functioning of meta-ecosystems, and ultimately affect the reliability of ecosystem services. This stabilizing effect on populations is proposed to derive from complementarity in growth and survival conditions experienced by individuals in the different habitats that comprise meta-ecosystems. Here we use the fine scale differentiation of salmon populations between diverse lake habitats to assess how rearing habitat and stock of origin affect the body condition of juvenile sockeye salmon. We use genetic markers (single nucleotide polymorphisms) to assign individuals of unknown origin to stock group and in turn characterize ecologically relevant attributes across habitats and stocks. Our analyses show that body condition of juvenile salmon is related to the productivity of alternative habitats across the watershed, irrespective of their stock of origin. Emigrants and residents with genetic origins in the high productivity lake were also differentiated by their body condition, poor and high respectively. These emigrants represented a substantial proportion of juvenile sockeye salmon rearing in the lower productivity lake habitat. Despite emigrants originating from the more productive lake, they did not differ in body condition from the individuals spawned in the lower productivity, recipient habitat. Genetic tools allowed us to assess the performance of different stocks groups across the diverse habitats comprising their meta-ecosystem. The ability to characterize the ecological consequences of meta-ecosystem connectivity can help develop strategies to protect and restore ecosystems and the services they provide to humans.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.jn14d/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.jn14d/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.jn14d/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.jn14d/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.jn14d/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.jn14d/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46506","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46506","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23505539","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0058584"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jn14d"}}