{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"96;4;2009","keywords":["morphology","dentition","crania"],"host":"Meachen-Samuels J, Van Valkenburgh B (2009) Biological Journal of the Linnean Society 96(4): 784-799.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6h722/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.33483","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-04-27T20:56:53Z","author":["Van Valkenburgh, Blaire","Meachen-Samuels, Julie"],"title":"Data from: Craniodental indicators of prey size preference in the Felidae","description":"In the present study, we used linear morphometrics of the crania, mandible and dentition to explore the association\nbetween craniodental shape and prey size among 35 species of living felids. To accomplish this, felids were divided\ninto three prey-size groups: (1) large prey specialists; (2) small prey specialists; and (3) mixed prey feeders. From\nthese linear measurements, large prey specialist felids can be distinguished from small and mixed prey feeders by\ntheir relatively robust canines and incisors and relatively wide muzzles. These cranial characters are advantageous\nwhen dispatching large prey, due to the stranglehold that cats employ during this activity. Robust canines resist\nthe bending and torsional forces applied by struggling prey and a wider muzzle helps to stabilize grip and\ndistribute bite forces more evenly during the killing bite. Small prey specialists had smaller canines, narrower\nmuzzles and slightly longer jaws for a speed advantage when catching small, quick prey. Mixed prey feeders were\nintermediate between large and small prey specialists, indicating they are adapted to killing both sizes of prey.\nGiven the success of this ecomorphological analysis of living felids that specialize on different prey sizes, we look\nforward to applying this same approach to extinct species.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.33483","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/j.1095-8312.2008.01169.x","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6h722"}}