{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-15T16:39:16Z","author":["Rasotto, Maria B.","Locatello, Lisa","Poli, Federica"],"title":"Data from: Tactic-specific differences in seminal fluid influence sperm performance","host":"Locatello L, Poli F, Rasotto MB (2013) Tactic-specific differences in seminal fluid influence sperm performance. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 280(1755): 20122891.","description":"Seminal fluid often makes up a large part of an ejaculate, yet most empirical and theoretical studies on sperm competition have focused on how sperm characteristics (number and quality) affect fertilization success. However, seminal fluid influences own sperm performance and may potentially influence the outcome of sperm competition, by affecting also that of rivals.  As a consequence males may be expected to allocate their investment in both sperm and seminal fluid in relation to the potential level of competition. Grass goby (Zosterisessor ophiocephalus) is an external fertilizer with guard-sneaker mating tactics, where sperm competition risk varies according to the tactic adopted. Here, we experimentally manipulated grass goby ejaculates by separately combining sperm and seminal fluid from territorial and sneaker males. While sperm of sneaker and territorial males did not differ in their performance when they interacted with their own seminal fluid only, sperm of sneakers increased their velocity and fertilization rate in presence of territorial males’ seminal fluid. In contrast, sneaker seminal fluid had a detrimental effect on the performance of territorial males' sperm. Sperm velocity was unaffected by the seminal fluid of males employing the same tactic, suggesting that seminal fluid's effect on rival-tactic sperm is not based on a self/non-self recognition mechanism. Our findings show that cross interactions of sperm and seminal fluid may influence the fertilization success of competing ejaculates with males investing in both sperm and seminal fluid in response to sperm competition risk.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1pb77/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.45445","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.45445","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rspb.2012.2891","PMID:23363633"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1pb77"}}