{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-30T16:12:39Z","author":["Horne, John B.","Momigliano, Paolo","Newman, Stephen J.","van Herwerden, Lynne"],"title":"Data from: Murky waters: searching for structure in genetically depauperate blue threadfin populations of Western Australia","host":"Horne JB, Momigliano P, van Herwerden L, Newman SJ (2013) Murky waters: searching for structure in genetically depauperate blue threadfin populations of Western Australia. Fisheries Research 146: 1-6.","keywords":["population genetics","self-recuitment","Polynemidae","recruitment cohorts"],"description":"The blue threadfin (Eleutheronema tetradactylum) is an exploited fishery species in southeast Asia and Australia. Demographic studies have revealed fine-scale stock structure throughout the Australian coastline, with demographically isolated populations separated by only tens of km. Similarly, population genetic analysis revealed fine-scale structure across most of its Australian range with important implications for fisheries management. However, in northern Western Australia, genetic stock structure analysis showed a contradictory lack of structure. In the present study, one mtDNA marker and a suite of five microsatellite loci were used to further investigate the stock structure of Western Australian blue threadfin populations. By increasing sample sizes from previously investigated areas: Roebuck Bay (n = 93 adults) and Eighty-mile Beach (n = 92 adults and 163 recruits from two settlement cohorts), we were able to detect subtle genetic differentiation that was previously obscured by low levels of genetic polymorphism. Therefore, the same fine-scale stock structure that has been observed elsewhere in this species also appears to exist in Western Australia. This has clear ramifications for a revised management strategy that incorporates the fine scale structuring of northwest Western Australian stocks of the blue threadfin.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.40rd6/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.40rd6/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47681","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47681","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1016/j.fishres.2013.03.013","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.40rd6"}}