{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-12T15:49:22Z","author":["Marra, Nicholas J.","Waser, Peter M.","Eo, Soo Hyung","Hale, Matthew C.","DeWoody, J. Andrew"],"title":"Data from: A priori and a posteriori approaches for finding genes of evolutionary interest in non-model species: Osmoregulatory genes in the kidney transcriptome of the desert rodent Dipodomys spectabilis (banner-tailed kangaroo rat)","host":"Marra NJ, Eo SH, Hale MC, Waser PM, DeWoody JA (2012) A priori and a posteriori approaches for finding genes of evolutionary interest in non-model species: Osmoregulatory genes in the kidney transcriptome of the desert rodent Dipodomys spectabilis (banner-tailed kangaroo rat). Comparative biochemistry and physiology. Part D, Genomics and proteomics 7(4): 328–339.","keywords":["454","molecular evolution","next-generation","water balance","Digital Gene Expression"],"description":"One common goal in evolutionary biology is the identification of genes underlying adaptive traits of evolutionary interest.  Recently next-generation sequencing techniques have greatly facilitated such evolutionary studies in species otherwise depauperate of genomic resources.  Kangaroo rats (Dipodomys sp.) serve as exemplars of adaptation in that they inhabit extremely arid environments,yet require no drinking water because of ultra-efficient kidney function and osmoregulation.  As a basis for identifying water conservation genes in kangaroo rats, we conducted a priori bioinformatics searches in model rodents (Mus musculus and Rattus norvegicus) to identify candidate genes with known or suspected osmoregulatory function.  We then obtained 446,758 reads via 454 pyrosequencing to characterize genes expressed in the kidney of banner-tailed kangaroo rats (D. spectabilis).  We also determined candidates a posteriori by identifying genes that were overexpressed in the kidney.  The kangaroo rat sequences revealed nine different a priori candidate genes predicted from our Mus and Rattus searches, as well as 32 a posteriori candidate genes that were overexpressed in kidney.  Mutations in two of these genes, Slc12a1 and Slc12a3, cause human renal diseases that result in the inability to concentrate urine.  These genes are likely key determinants of physiological water conservation in desert rodents.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.sf654/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.sf654/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.sf654/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.sf654/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40968","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40968","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22841684","doi:10.1016/j.cbd.2012.07.001"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sf654"}}