{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-25T14:32:36Z","author":["Holzapfel, Christina M.","Bradshaw, William E.","Emerson, Kevin J."],"title":"Data from: Genetic correlations and the evolution of photoperiodic time measurement within a local population of the pitcher-plant mosquito, Wyeomyia smithii","host":"Bradshaw WE, Emerson KJ, Holzapfel CM (2012) Genetic correlations and the evolution of photoperiodic time measurement within a local population of the pitcher-plant mosquito, Wyeomyia smithii. Heredity 108: 473–479.","keywords":["photoperiodism","artificial selection","circadian clock"],"description":"The genetic relationship between the daily circadian clock and the seasonal photoperiodic timer remains a subject of intense controversy. In Wyeomyia smithii, the critical photoperiod (an overt expression of the photoperiodic timer) evolves independently of the rhythmic response to the Nanda-Hamner protocol (an overt expression of the daily circadian clock) over a wide geographic range in North America. Herein, we focus on these two processes within a single local population in which there is a negative genetic correlation between them. We show that antagonistic selection against this genetic correlation rapidly breaks it down and, in fact, reverses its sign, showing that the genetic correlation is due primarily to linkage and not pleiotropy. This rapid reversal of the genetic correlation within a small, single population means that it is difficult to argue that circadian rhythmicity forms the necessary, causal basis for the adaptive divergence of photoperiodic time measurement within populations or for the evolution of photoperiodic time measurement among populations over a broad geographic gradient of seasonal selection.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs/8"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35361","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35361","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2011.108","PMID:22072069"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.87ht85rs"}}