{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-07-06T18:59:46Z","author":["Hahn, Matthew W.","Han, Mira V."],"series":"190;;2012","title":"Data from: Inferring the history of interchromosomal gene transposition in Drosophila using n-Dimensional parsimony","host":"Han MV, Hahn MW (2011) Inferring the history of interchromosomal gene transposition in Drosophila using n-Dimensional parsimony. Genetics 190(2): 813-825.","description":"Gene transposition puts a new gene copy in a novel genomic environment. Moreover, genes moving between the autosomes and the X chromosome experience change in several evolutionary parameters. Previous studies of gene transposition have not utilized the phylogenetic framework that becomes possible with the availability of whole genomes from multiple species. Here we used parsimonious reconstruction on the genomic distribution of gene families to analyze interchromosomal gene transposition in Drosophila. We identified 782 genes that have moved chromosomes within the phylogeny of 10 Drosophila species, including 87 gene families with multiple independent movements on different branches of the phylogeny. Using this large catalog of transposed genes, we detected accelerated sequence evolution in duplicated genes that transposed when compared to the parental copy at the original locus. We also observed a more refined picture of the biased movement of genes from the X chromosome to the autosomes. The bias of X-to-autosome movement was significantly stronger for RNA-based movements than for DNA-based movements, and among DNA-based movements there was an excess of genes moving onto the X chromosome as well. Genes involved in female-specific functions moved onto the X chromosome while genes with male-specific functions moved off the X. There was a significant overrepresentation of proteins involving chromosomal function among transposed genes, suggesting that genetic conflict between sexes and among chromosomes may be a driving force behind gene transposition in Drosophila.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sn5r5/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40678","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40678","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22095076","doi:10.1534/genetics.111.135947"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sn5r5"}}