{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-26T19:41:07Z","author":["Murray, Dennis L.","Bennett, Amanda M."],"title":"Data from: Maternal body condition influences magnitude of anti-predator response in offspring","host":"Bennett AM, Murray DL (2014) Maternal body condition influences magnitude of anti-predator response in offspring. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1794): 20141806.","description":"Organisms exhibit plasticity in response to their environment, but there is large variation even within populations in the expression and magnitude of response. Maternal influence alters offspring survival through size advantages in growth and development. However, the relationship between maternal influence and variation in plasticity in response to predation risk is unknown. We hypothesized that variation in the magnitude of plastic responses between families is at least partly due to maternal provisioning and examined the relationship between maternal condition, egg provisioning and magnitude of plastic response to perceived predation risk (by dragonfly larvae: Aeshna spp.) in northern leopard frogs (Lithobates pipiens). Females in better body condition tended to lay more (clutch size) larger (egg diameter) eggs. Tadpoles responded to predation risk by increasing relative tail depth (morphology) and decreasing activity (behaviour). We found a positive relationship between morphological effect size and maternal condition, but no relationship between behavioural effect size and maternal condition. These novel findings suggest that limitations imposed by maternal condition can constrain phenotypic variation, ultimately influencing the capacity of populations to respond to environmental change.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7tb6b/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.63536","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.63536","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25253460","doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.1806"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7tb6b"}}