{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-21T15:09:28Z","author":["Podos, Jeffrey","De León, Luis","Herrel, Anthony","Gardezi, Tariq","Hendry, Andrew"],"series":"27;6;2014","title":"Data from: Darwin’s finches and their diet niches: the sympatric co-existence of imperfect generalists","keywords":["sympatry","resource use","niche partitioning","ground finches","generalist","specialist","ecological speciation","adaptive radiation"],"description":"Adaptive radiation can be strongly influenced by inter-specific competition for resources, which can lead to diverse outcomes ranging from competitive exclusion to character displacement. In each case, sympatric species are expected to evolve into distinct ecological niches, such as different food types, and yet this expectation is not always met when such species are examined in nature. The most common hypotheses to account for the coexistence of species with substantial diet overlap rests on temporal variation in niches (often diets). Yet spatial variation in niche overlap might also be important, pointing to the need for spatiotemporal analyses of diet and diet overlap between closely related species persisting in sympatry. We here perform such an analysis by characterizing the diets of, and diet overlap among, four sympatric Darwin’s ground finch species at three sites and over five years on a single Galápagos island (Santa Cruz). We find that the different species have broadly similar and overlapping diets – they are to some extent generalists and opportunists – yet we also find that each species retains some “private” resources for which their morphologies are best suited. Importantly, use of these private resources increased considerably, and diet overlap decreased accordingly, when the availability of preferred shared foods, such as arthropods, was reduced during drought conditions. Spatial variation in food resources was also important. These results together suggest that the ground finches are “imperfect generalists” that use overlapping resources under benign conditions (in space or time), but then retreat to resources for which they are best adapted during periods of food limitation. These conditions likely promote local and regional coexistence.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.q3b41/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.q3b41/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68021","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68021","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.q3b41"}}