{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-23T15:06:51Z","author":["Valero, Myriam","Le Gall, Line","Mauger, Stéphane","Robuchon, Marine"],"title":"Data from: Contrasting genetic diversity patterns in two sister kelp species co-distributed along the coast of Brittany, France","host":"Robuchon M, Le Gall L, Mauger S, Valero M (2014) Contrasting genetic diversity patterns in two sister kelp species co-distributed along the coast of Brittany, France. Molecular Ecology 23(11): 2669-2685.","keywords":"microsatellites genotypes","description":"We investigated patterns of genetic structure in two sister kelp species to explore how distribution width along the shore, zonation, latitudinal distribution and historical factors contribute to contrasting patterns of genetic diversity. We implemented a hierarchical sampling scheme to compare patterns of genetic diversity and structure in these two kelp species co-distributed along the coasts of Brittany (France) using a total of 12 microsatellites, 9 for Laminaria hyperborea and 11 for Laminaria digitata, of which 8 amplified in both species. The genetic diversity and connectivity of L. hyperborea populations was greater than that of L. digitata populations in accordance with the larger cross-shore distribution width along the coast and the greater depth occupied by L. hyperborea populations in contrast to L. digitata populations. In addition, marginal populations showed reduced genetic diversity and connectivity, which erased isolation-by-distance patterns in both species. As L. digitata encounters its southern range limit in southern Brittany while L. hyperborea extends down to mid-Portugal, it was possible to distinguish the effect of habitat continuity from range edge effects. We found that L. digitata did not harbour high regional diversity at its southern edge, as expected in a typical rear edge, suggesting that refuges from the last glacial maximum for L. digitata were probably not located in southern Brittany, but most likely further north. For both species, the highest levels of genetic diversity were found in the Iroise Sea and Morlaix Bay, the two regions in which they are being currently harvested. Preserving genetic diversity of these two foundation species in these areas should, thus, be a priority for the management of this resource in Brittany.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.pv28c/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.pv28c/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.62144","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.62144","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12774","PMID:24787679"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pv28c"}}