{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-16T17:25:11Z","author":["Moury, Benoit","Quenouille, Julie","Palloix, Alain","Paulhiac, Estelle"],"title":"Data from: Quantitative trait loci from the host genetic background modulate the durability of a resistance gene: a rational basis for sustainable resistance breeding in plants","host":"Quenouille J, Paulhiac E, Moury B, Palloix A (2014) Quantitative trait loci from the host genetic background modulate the durability of a resistance gene: a rational basis for sustainable resistance breeding in plants. Heredity 112(6): 579-587.","keywords":["mapping population","phenotype data","doubled haploid lines","genotype data"],"description":"The combination of major resistance genes with quantitative resistance factors is hypothesized as a promising breeding strategy to preserve the durability of resistant cultivar, as recently observed in different pathosystems. Using the pepper (Capsicum annuum)/Potato virus Y (PVY, genus Potyvirus) pathosystem, we aimed at identifying plant genetic factors directly affecting the frequency of virus adaptation to the major resistance gene pvr23 and at comparing them with genetic factors affecting quantitative resistance. The resistance breakdown frequency was a highly heritable trait (h²=0.87). Four loci including additive quantitative trait loci (QTLs) and epistatic interactions explained together 70% of the variance of pvr23 breakdown frequency. Three of the four QTLs controlling pvr23 breakdown frequency were also involved in quantitative resistance, strongly suggesting that QTLs controlling quantitative resistance have a pleiotropic effect on the durability of the major resistance gene. With the first mapping of QTLs directly affecting resistance durability, this study provides a rationale for sustainable resistance breeding. Surprisingly, a genetic trade-off was observed between the durability of PVY resistance controlled by pvr23 and the spectrum of the resistance against different potyviruses. This trade-off seemed to have been resolved by the combination of minor-effect durability QTLs under long term farmer selection.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s4n76/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56742","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56742","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.138","PMID:24569635"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s4n76"}}