{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-09-06T14:46:44Z","author":["Breed, Martin F.","Gardner, Michael G.","Ottewell, Kym M.","Lowe, Andrew J.","Marklund, Maria H. K.","Dormontt, Eleanor E."],"title":"Data from: Mating patterns and pollinator mobility are critical traits in forest fragmentation genetics","host":"Breed MF, Ottewell KM, Gardner MG, Marklund MHK, Dormontt EE, Lowe AJ (2013) Mating patterns and pollinator mobility are critical traits in forest fragmentation genetics. Heredity, online in advance of print.","keywords":["mating system","plant genetic resources","pollen competition","pollen discounting","plant-pollinator mutualisms"],"description":"Most woody plants are animal-pollinated, but the global problem of habitat fragmentation is changing pollination dynamics. Consequently, the genetic diversity and fitness of progeny of animal-pollinated woody plants sired in fragmented landscapes tend to decline due to shifts in plant mating patterns (e.g. reduced outcrossing rate, pollen diversity). However, the magnitude of this mating pattern shift should theoretically be a function of pollinator mobility. We first test this hypothesis by exploring the mating patterns of three ecologically divergent eucalypts sampled across a habitat fragmentation gradient in southern Australia. We demonstrate increased selfing and decreased pollen diversity with increased fragmentation for two small-insect pollinated eucalypts, but no such relationship for the mobile-bird pollinated eucalypt. In a meta-analysis, we then show that fragmentation generally does increase selfing rates and decrease pollen diversity, and that more mobile pollinators tended to dampen these mating pattern shifts. Together, our findings support the premise that variation in pollinator form contributes to the diversity of mating pattern responses to habitat fragmentation.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.g7j86/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.g7j86/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.48918","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.48918","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.48","PMID:24002239"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g7j86"}}