{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Systematic Biology","keywords":["homoplasy","spiders","sexual selection","speciation","phylogeny","differentiation","hybridization","geographic variation"],"host":"Maddison W, McMahon M (2000) Divergence and reticulation among montane populations of a jumping spider (Habronattus pugillis Griswold). Systematic Biology 49: 400-421.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.587/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.587","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-28T19:05:53Z","author":["McMahon, Michelle","Maddison, Wayne"],"title":"Data from: Divergence and reticulation among montane populations of a jumping spider (Habronattus pugillis Griswold)","description":"Populations of the jumping spider Habronattus pugillis Griswold isolated on nearby mountain ranges in southern Arizona are differentiated in many features of the males (color, shape and orientation of setae on face, shape of carapace, markings of palpi and legs, motions during courtship behavior). These features are (mostly) consistent within a range and different between ranges. The concentration of differences to male courtship behavior and body parts exposed to the female during courtship and correlations between form and courtship behavior suggest sexual selection was involved in the differentiation. A phylogenetic analysis of the populations yields a tree that for the most part groups geographic neighbors, but the history of H. pugillis populations may not be adequately described by a tree. Geographic proximity of apparent convergences suggests that populations from at least some of the mountain ranges acquired characteristics through introgression. Lowering of the woodland habitat during the last glacial period probably brought some populations into contact, but it is not clear if the interrange woodlands would have provided corridors for extensive mixing.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.587","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1080/10635159950127312","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.587"}}