{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-21T14:50:21Z","author":["Moore, Brian R.","Landis, Michael J.","Matzke, Nicholas J.","Huelsenbeck, John P."],"title":"Data from: Bayesian analysis of biogeography when the number of areas is large","host":"Landis MJ, Matzke NJ, Moore BR, Huelsenbeck JP (2013) Bayesian analysis of biogeography when the number of areas is large. Systematic Biology 62(6): 789-804.","keywords":["historical biogeography","ancestral area analysis","data augmentation","Bayesian biogeographic inference","Markov chain Monte Carlo"],"description":"Historical biogeography is increasingly studied from an explicitly statistical perspective, using stochastic models to describe the evolution of species range as a continuous-time Markov process of dispersal between and extinction within a set of discrete geographic areas. The main constraint of these methods is the computational limit on the number of areas that can be specified. We propose a Bayesian approach for inferring biogeographic history that extends the application of biogeographic models to the analysis of more realistic problems that involve a large number of areas. Our solution is based on a ‘data-augmentation’ approach, in which we first populate the tree with a history of biogeographic events that is consistent with the observed species ranges at the tips of the tree. We then calculate the likelihood of a given history by adopting a mechanis- tic interpretation of the instantaneous-rate matrix, which specifies both the exponential waiting times between biogeographic events and the relative probabilities of each biogeographic change. We develop this approach in a Bayesian framework, marginalizing over all possible biogeographic histories using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC). Besides dramatically increasing the number of areas that can be accommodated in a biogeographic analysis, our method allows the parameters of a given biogeographic model to be estimated and different biogeographic models to be objectively compared. Our approach is implemented in the program, BayArea.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8346r/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.8346r/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8346r/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.8346r/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.45132","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.45132","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/sysbio/syt040","PMID:23736102"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8346r"}}