{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-22T14:41:08Z","author":["Roderick, George K.","Kremen, Claire","Leong, Misha"],"title":"Data from: Pollinator interactions with yellow starthistle (Centaurea solstitialis) across urban, agricultural, and natural landscapes","host":"Leong M, Kremen C, Roderick GK (2014) Pollinator interactions with yellow starthistle (Centaurea solstitialis) across urban, agricultural, and natural landscapes. PLoS ONE 9(1): e86357.","keywords":["urban","plant-pollinator interactions","land use change","bees","seed set","floral visitation","peri-urban","invasive","pollinators","agricultural","human-altered landscapes","yellow starthistle"],"description":"Pollinator-plant relationships are found to be particularly vulnerable to land use change. Yet despite extensive research in agricultural and natural systems, less attention has focused on these interactions in neighboring urban areas and its impact on pollination services. We investigated pollinator-plant interactions in a peri-urban landscape on the outskirts of the San Francisco Bay Area, California, where urban, agricultural, and natural land use types interface. We made standardized observations of floral visitation and measured seed set of yellow starthistle (Centaurea solstitialis), a common grassland invasive, to test the hypotheses that increasing urbanization decreases 1) rates of bee visitation, 2) viable seed set, and 3) the efficiency of pollination (relationship between bee visitation and seed set). We unexpectedly found that bee visitation was highest in urban and agricultural land use contexts, but in contrast, seed set rates in these human-altered landscapes were lower than in natural sites. An explanation for the discrepancy between floral visitation and seed set is that higher plant diversity in urban and agricultural areas, as a result of more introduced species, decreases pollinator efficiency. If these patterns are consistent across other plant species, the novel plant communities created in these managed landscapes and the generalist bee species that are favored by human-altered environments will reduce pollination services.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b5np1/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55963","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55963","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0086357","PMID:24466050"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b5np1"}}