{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-12-13T17:27:27Z","author":["Rodrigues-Antunes, Symara","Maques-Aguiar, Suely Aparecida","Aguiar, Gilberto Ferreira de Souza","e Silva Jr, José de Sousa","de Andrade, Fernanda Atanaena Gonçalves","Borges, Bárbara do Nascimento","Ferreira, Wallax Augusto Silva","Harada, Maria Lúcia"],"title":"Data from: Phylogeography of the dark fruit-eating bat Artibeus obscurus in the Brazilian Amazon","host":"Ferreira WAS, Borges BdN, Rodrigues-Antunes S, de Andrade FAG, Aguiar GFdS, e Silva Jr JdS, Maques-Aguiar SA, Harada ML (2013) Phylogeography of the dark fruit-eating bat Artibeus obscurus in the Brazilian Amazon. Journal of Heredity 105(1): 48-59.","keywords":["Molecular systematics and phylogenetics","Amazon forest","phylogeography","cytochrome b","Population structure and phylogeography"],"description":"Artibeus obscurus (Mammalia: Chiroptera) is endemic to South America, being found in at least 18 Brazilian states. Recent studies revealed that different populations of this genus present distinct phylogeographic patterns; however, very little is known on the population genetics structure of A. obscurus in the Amazon rainforest. Here, using a fragment (1010bp) of the mitochondrial gene cytochrome b from 87 samples, we investigated patterns of genetic divergence among populations of A. obscurus from different locations in the Brazilian Amazon rainforest and compared them with other Brazilian and South American regions. Analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA), fixation index (Fst) analysis, and phylogeographic patterns showed divergence between two major monophyletic groups, each one corresponding to a geographic region associated with the Atlantic and Amazon forest biomes. The Atlantic forest clusters formed a monophyletic group with a high bootstrap support and a fragmented distribution that follows the pattern predicted by the Refuge Theory. On the other hand, a different scenario was observed for the Amazon forest, where no fragmentation was identified. The AMOVA results revealed a significant geographic heterogeneity in the distribution of genetic variation, with 70% found within populations across the studied populations (Fst values ranging from 0.05864 to 0.09673; φST = 0.55). The intrapopulational analysis revealed that one population (Bragança) showed significant evidence of population expansion, with the formation of 2 distinct phylogroups, suggesting the occurrence of a subspecies or at least a different population in this region. These results also suggest considerable heterogeneity for A. obscurus in the Amazon region.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pn73j/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53563","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53563","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24127548","doi:10.1093/jhered/est066"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pn73j"}}