{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-25T15:45:11Z","author":["Luijckx, Pepijn","Ebert, Dieter","Fienberg, Harris","Duneau, David"],"title":"Data from: Resistance to a bacterial parasite in the Crustacean Daphnia magna shows Mendelian segregation with dominance","host":"Luijckx P, Fienberg H, Duneau D, Ebert D (2012) Resistance to a bacterial parasite in the Crustacean Daphnia magna shows Mendelian segregation with dominance. Heredity 108: 547-551.","keywords":["host","parasite","resistance","Mendelian segregation"],"description":"The influence of host and parasite genetic background on infection outcome is a topic of great interest because of its pertinence to theoretical issues in evolutionary biology. In the present study we use a classical genetics approach to examine the mode of inheritance of infection outcome in the crustacean Daphnia magna when exposed to the bacterial parasite Pasteuria ramosa. In contrast to previous studies in this system we use a clone of P. ramosa, not field isolates, which allows for a more definitive interpretation of results. We test parental, F1, F2, backcross and selfed parental clones (total 284 genotypes) for susceptibility against a clone of P. ramosa using 2 different methods, infection trials and the recently developed attachment-test. We find that D. magna clones reliably exhibit either complete resistance or complete susceptibility to P. ramosa clone C1 and that resistance is dominant and inherited in a pattern consistent with Mendelian segregation of a single-locus with two alleles. The finding of a single host locus controlling susceptibility to P. ramosa suggests that the previously observed genotype-genotype interactions in this system have a simple genetic basis. This has important implications for the outcome of host-parasite coevolution. Our results add to the growing body of evidence that resistance to parasites in invertebrates is mostly coded by one or few loci with dominance.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6j1qv1m3/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35931","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35931","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2011.122","PMID:22167056"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6j1qv1m3"}}