{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-06T20:24:26Z","author":["Wang, Wen","Liu, Shuting","Luo, Yiping","Zhang, Yurong","Huang, Qingda"],"title":"Data from: Intraspecific scaling of the resting and maximum metabolic rates of the crucian carp (Carassius auratus)","host":"Huang Q, Zhang Y, Liu S, Wang W, Luo Y (2013) Intraspecific scaling of the resting and maximum metabolic rates of the crucian carp (Carassius auratus). PLoS ONE 8(12): e82837.","keywords":["Allometric Scaling","Metabolic Rate","Fish"],"description":"The question of how the scaling of metabolic rate with body mass (M) is achieved in animals is unresolved. Here, we tested the cell metabolism hypothesis and the organ size hypothesis by assessing the mass scaling of the resting metabolic rate (RMR), maximum metabolic rate (MMR), erythrocyte size, and the masses of metabolically active organs in the crucian carp (Carassius auratus). The M of the crucian carp ranged from 4.5 to 323.9 g, representing an approximately 72-fold difference. The RMR and MMR increased with M according to the allometric equations RMR = 0.212M0.776 and MMR = 0.753M0.785. The scaling exponents for RMR (br) and MMR (bm) obtained in crucian carp were close to each other. Thus, the factorial aerobic scope remained almost constant with increasing M. Although erythrocyte size was negatively correlated with both mass-specific RMR and absolute RMR adjusted to M, it and all other hematological parameters showed no significant relationship with M. These data demonstrate that the cell metabolism hypothesis does not describe metabolic scaling in the crucian carp, suggesting that erythrocyte size may not represent the general size of other cell types in this fish and the metabolic activity of cells may decrease as fish grows. The mass scaling exponents of active organs was lower than 1 while that of inactive organs was greater than 1, which suggests that the mass scaling of the RMR can be partly due to variance in the proportion of active/inactive organs in crucian carp. Furthermore, our results provide additional evidence supporting the correlation between locomotor capacity and metabolic scaling.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cr3p6/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56150","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56150","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24376588","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0082837"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.cr3p6"}}