{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-06-12T17:09:41Z","author":["Sithole, Hendrik","Mawdsley, Alice S.","Erwin, Terry L.","Mawdsley, Jonathan R."],"title":"Data from: A synopsis of the genus Cypholoba Chaudoir (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Anthiini) known to occur in the Republic of South Africa","host":"Mawdsley JR, Erwin TL, Sithole H, Mawdsley AS (2012) A synopsis of the genus Cypholoba Chaudoir (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Anthiini) known to occur in the Republic of South Africa. ZooKeys 181: 23-43.","keywords":["identification key","conservation","distribution","savanna and woodland ecosystems"],"description":"Nearly one third of the described species of Cypholoba Chaudoir (Coleoptera: Carabidae) are known to inhabit the Republic of South Africa. A key and diagnostic notes are provided for their identification, as well as notes about way of life for some of the species based on observations in the Kruger National Park. Fifteen species and subspecies of the genus are recorded from the Republic of South Africa; adult specimens of each species and subspecies are illustrated and information about the distribution of each species in the Republic of South Africa is summarized and mapped: Cypholoba alstoni (Péringuey), Cypholoba alveolata (Brême), Cypholoba amatonga Péringuey, Cypholoba fritschi (Chaudoir), Cypholoba gracilis gracilis (Dejean), Cypholoba gracilis scrobiculata (Bertoloni), Cypholoba gracilis zuluana Basilewsky, Cypholoba graphipteroides graphipteroides (Guérin-Méneville), Cypholoba leucospilota semilaevis (Chaudoir), Cypholoba macilenta (Olivier), Cypholoba notata (Perroud), Cypholoba oberthueri seruana Strohmeyer, Cypholoba opulenta (Boheman), Cypholoba rutata (Péringuey), and Cypholoba tenuicollis aenigma (Dohrn).","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ms5q038t/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38829","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38829","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22539909","doi:10.3897/zookeys.181.2984"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ms5q038t"}}