{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-19T14:13:57Z","author":["Winter, Alfred","Funkat, Gert","Kasch, Oksana","Schaaf, Michael","Josten, Christoph"],"title":"Data from: Analysis and prediction of effects of the Manchester Triage System on patient waiting times in an emergency department by means of agent-based simulation","host":"Schaaf M, Funkat G, Kasch O, Josten C, Winter A (2014) Analysis and prediction of effects of the Manchester Triage System on patient waiting times in an emergency department by means of agent-based simulation. GMS Medizinische Informatik, Biometrie und Epidemiologie 10(1): Doc02.","keywords":["manchester triage system","agent-based simulation","emergency department","emergency care"],"description":"A simulation of complex clinical processes is a challenging task and suitable methods need to be found which can capture the influence of relevant factors and their relationships. The Manchester triage system (MTS) is widely used in German emergency departments (ED), however the impact on patient waiting times remain difficult to predict. The purpose of this work is the assessment of MTS particularly with regard to the waiting times of different degrees of severity. The methodology of agent based simulation was found suitable for the ED domain and the agent based simulation tool SeSAm was chosen due to its intuitive user interface and easy adaption of the simulation models. Altogether four agent classes could be implemented based on the information derived from a process model. The model permits a dynamic simulation of the ED processes and a reliable assessment of patient waiting times. In addition, the implementation of a triage nurse allowed the simulation of the triage process and a direct comparison to the current state without a standardized triage procedure. Essential influencing factors (e.g. number of patients, manning level) were implemented and their effects on the ED processes and patient waiting times assessed. The simulation runs delivered correct results based on the underlying process model and the collected statistical data. The process flow and the waiting times of an ED could be mapped exactly. In all simulation runs the waiting times of high triage levels (MTS-levels 1 and 2) could be reduced. Especially patients of MTS-level 2 in the waiting area of the ED benefit significantly from the implementation of a standardized triage procedure and the associated permanent monitoring.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2n9g6/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.59373","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.59373","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.3205/mibe000151","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2n9g6"}}