{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-04-30T14:07:49Z","author":["Lynn, Eric A.","Buonaccorsi, Vincent P.","Kimbrell, Carol A.","Hyde, John R."],"title":"Data from: Comparative population genetic analysis of bocaccio rockfish Sebastes paucispinis using anonymous and gene-associated simple sequence repeat loci","host":"Buonaccorsi VP, Kimbrell CA, Lynn EA, Hyde JR (2012) Comparative population genetic analysis of bocaccio rockfish Sebastes paucispinis using anonymous and gene-associated simple sequence repeat loci. Journal of Heredity 103(3): 391-399.","keywords":["microsatellite","EST-SSR","marine fisheries","comparative genomics","threatened species","stock structure"],"description":"Comparative population genetic analyses of traditional and emergent molecular markers aid in determining appropriate use of new technologies. The bocaccio rockfish Sebastes paucispinis is a high-gene-flow marine species off the west coast of North America that experienced strong population decline over the past three decades. We used 18 anonymous and 13 gene associated simple sequence repeat loci (EST-SSRs) to characterize range-wide population structure with temporal replicates. No FST-outliers were detected using the LOSITAN program, suggesting that neither balancing nor divergent selection affected the loci surveyed. Consistent hierarchical structuring of populations by geography or year class was not detected regardless of marker class. The EST-SSRs were less variable than the anonymous SSRs, but no correlation between FST and variation or marker class was observed. General Linear Model analysis showed that low EST-SSR variation was attributable to low mean repeat number. Comparative genomic analysis with Gasterosteus aculeatus, Takifugu rubripes, and Oryzias latipes showed consistently lower repeat number in EST-SSRs than SSR loci that were not in ESTs. Purifying selection likely imposed functional constraints on EST-SSRs resulting in low repeat numbers that affected diversity estimates, but did not affect the observed pattern of population structure.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.42413173/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.42413173/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.37456","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.37456","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22490232","doi:10.1093/jhered/ess002"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.42413173"}}