{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-06-12T17:31:18Z","author":["Michel, Andy P.","Jun, Tae-Hwan","Mian, M. A. Rouf"],"title":"Data from: Genetic mapping of three quantitative trait loci for soybean aphid resistance in PI 567324","host":"Jun T, Mian MAR, Michel AP (2013) Genetic mapping of three quantitative trait loci for soybean aphid resistance in PI 567324. Heredity 111: 16-22.","description":"Host-plant resistance is an effective method for controlling soybean aphid (Aphis glycines Matsumura), the most damaging insect pest of soybean (Glycine max (L.) Merr.) in North America. Recently, resistant soybean lines have been discovered and at least four aphid resistance genes (Rag1, Rag2, Rag3 and rag4) have been mapped on different soybean chromosomes. However, the evolution of new soybean aphid biotypes capable of defeating host-plant resistance conferred by most single genes demonstrates the need for finding germplasm with multigenic resistance to the aphid. This study was conducted to map quantitative trait loci (QTL) for aphid resistance in PI 567324. We identified two major QTL (QTL_13_1 and QTL_13_2) for aphid resistance on soybean chromosome 13 using 184 recombinant inbred lines from a ‘Wyandot’ × PI 567324 cross. QTL_13_1 was located close to the previously reported Rag2 gene locus, and QTL_13_2 was close to the rag4 locus. A minor QTL (QTL_6_1) was also detected on chromosome 6, where no gene for soybean aphid resistance has been reported so far. These results indicate that PI 567324 possesses oligogenic resistance to the soybean aphid. The molecular markers closely linked to the QTL reported here will be useful for development of cultivars with oligogenic resistance that are expected to provide broader and more durable resistance against soybean aphids compared with cultivars with monogenic resistance.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.df47h/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.df47h/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46268","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46268","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.10","PMID:23486080"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.df47h"}}