{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-21T15:24:18Z","author":["French, Susannah S.","Brodie Jr., Edmund D.","Hopkins, Gareth R."],"title":"Data from: Potential for local adaptation in response to an anthropogenic agent of selection: effects of road deicing salts on amphibian embryonic survival and development","host":"Hopkins GR, French SS, Brodie Jr ED (2012) Potential for local adaptation in response to an anthropogenic agent of selection: effects of road deicing salts on amphibian embryonic survival and development. Evolutionary Applications 6(2): 384–392.","keywords":["Habitat Degradation","Natural Selection and Contemporary Evolution","Contemporary Evolution","Ecotoxicology"],"description":"The application of millions of tons of road deicing salts every winter in North America presents significant survival challenges to amphibians inhabiting road-side habitats. While much is known of the effects of NaCl on anuran tadpoles, less is known of effects on amphibian eggs, or any caudate life-stage. In addition, little is known of the effects of MgCl2, which is now the 2nd most commonly used road deicer. Most studies have considered amphibians to be helpless victims of deicing salts, and ignore the possibility of the evolution of local adaptation to this stressor. We attempt to address these knowledge gaps and explore this evolutionary potential by examining the effects of NaCl and MgCl2 on the survival and development of eggs from different female rough-skinned newts (Taricha granulosa) from the same population. We demonstrate that both salts, at environmentally relevant concentrations, severely affect the embryonic survival and development of this amphibian, but that the effects of the salt are dependent on the identity of the mother. This female x treatment interaction results in substantial variation in tolerance to road deicing salts among newt families, providing the raw material necessary for natural selection and the evolution of local adaptation in this amphibian.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.qn24m/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.qn24m/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42256","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42256","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/eva.12016","PMID:23467723"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.qn24m"}}