{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-02-15T18:02:29Z","author":["Saarma, Urmas","Soon, Villu"],"title":"Data from: Mitochondrial phylogeny of the Chrysis ignita (Hymenoptera: Chrysididae) species group based on simultaneous Bayesian alignment and phylogeny reconstruction","host":"Soon V, Saarma U (2011) Mitochondrial phylogeny of the Chrysis ignita (Hymenoptera: Chrysididae) species group based on simultaneous Bayesian alignment and phylogeny reconstruction. Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution 60(1): 13-20.","description":"The ignita species group within the genus Chrysis includes over 100 cuckoo wasp species, which all lead a parasitic lifestyle and exhibit very similar morphology. The lack of robust, diagnostic morphological characters has hindered phylogenetic reconstructions and contributed to frequent misidentification and inconsistent interpretations of species in this group. Therefore, molecular phylogenetic analysis is the most suitable approach for resolving the phylogeny and taxonomy of this group. We present a well-resolved phylogeny of the Chrysisignita species group based on mitochondrial sequence data from 41 ingroup and six outgroup taxa. Although our emphasis was on European taxa, we included samples from most of the distribution range of the C. ignita species group to test for monophyly. We used a continuous mitochondrial DNA sequence consisting of 16S rRNA, tRNAVal, 12S rRNA and ND4. The location of the ND4 gene at the 3′ end of this continuous sequence, following 12S rRNA, represents a novel mitochondrial gene arrangement for insects. Due to difficulties in aligning rRNA genes, two different Bayesian approaches were employed to reconstruct phylogeny: (1) using a reduced data matrix including only those positions that could be aligned with confidence; or (2) using the full sequence dataset while estimating alignment and phylogeny simultaneously. In addition maximum-parsimony and maximum-likelihood analyses were performed to test the robustness of the Bayesian approaches. Although all approaches yielded trees with similar topology, considerably more nodes were resolved with analyses using the full data matrix. Phylogenetic analysis supported the monophyly of the C. ignita species group and divided its species into well-supported clades. The resultant phylogeny was only partly in accordance with published subgroupings based on morphology. Our results suggest that several taxa currently treated as subspecies or names treated as synonyms may in fact constitute separate species. Our study provides a solid basis for further systematic investigations of this enigmatic insect group.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8984/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8984/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8984","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8984","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1016/j.ympev.2011.04.005","PMID:21524705"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8984"}}