{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-09-02T20:16:50Z","author":["Boissier, Jerome","Duval, David","Théron, Andre","Kieffer-Jaquinod, Sylvie","Pierce, Raymond J","Gourbal, Benjamin","Beltran, Sophie","Mitta, Guillaume","Grunau, Christoph"],"title":"Data from: Vertebrate host protective immunity drives genetic diversity and antigenic polymorphism in Schistosoma mansoni","host":"Beltran S, Gourbal B, Boissier J, Duval D, Kieffer-Jaquinod S, Pierce RJ, Grunau C, Théron A, Mitta G (2010) Vertebrate host protective immunity drives genetic diversity and antigenic polymorphism in Schistosoma mansoni. Journal of Evolutionary Biology 24(3): 554–572.","keywords":["concomitant immunity","mating strategy","genetic diversity","Host-parasite interaction","antigenic polymorphism"],"description":"Schistosomes are gonochoric blood parasites with a complex life cycle responsible for a disease of considerable medical and veterinary importance in tropical and subtropical regions. Understanding the evolution of schistosome genetic diversity is clearly of fundamental importance to interpreting schistosomiasis epidemiology and disease transmission patterns of this parasite. In this paper we have the putative role of the host immune system in the selection of male genetic diversity. We demonstrated the link between genetic dissimilarity and the protective effect among male worms. We then compared the proteomes of three male clones with different genotypes and differing by their capacity to protect against reinfection. The identified differences correspond mainly to antigens known or supposed to be involved in the induction of protective immunity. These results underline the role played by host immune system in the selection of schistosome genetic diversity that is linked to antigenic diversity. We discuss the evolutionary consequences in the context of schistosome infection.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.7968/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.7968/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.7968","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.7968","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1420-9101.2010.02190.x","PMID:21159003"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7968"}}