{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["0014-3820","Evolution"],"keywords":["Population Genetics","Oceanic islands","Gene Flow","Genetic Variation","Biogeography","Population Structure"],"host":"García-Verdugo C, Forrest AD, Fay MF, Vargas P (2010) The relevance of gene flow in metapopulation dynamics of an oceanic island endemic, Olea europaea subsp guanchica. Evolution 64(12): 3525-3536.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1767/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.1767","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T21:01:25Z","author":["Forrest, Alan D","Fay, Michael F","Vargas, Pablo","García-Verdugo, Carlos"],"title":"Data from: The relevance of gene flow in metapopulation dynamics of an oceanic island endemic, Olea europaea subsp guanchica","description":"Theoretical and empirical studies suggest that geographical isolation and extinction-recolonization dynamics are two factors causing strong genetic structure in metapopulations. Here, we investigated the effect of population age structure and isolation by distance in the patterns of genetic diversity in a tree species (Olea europaea subsp. guanchica) sporadically affected by volcanic events across the Canarian archipelago. Genetic variation was assessed at six nuclear microsatellites (nDNA) and six chloroplast fragments (cpDNA) in nine subpopulations sampled on four oceanic islands. Subpopulations occurring on more recent substrates were more differentiated than those on older substrates, but within-subpopulation genetic diversity was not significantly different between age groups for any type of marker. Contrary to the general trend for island systems, between-island differentiation was extremely low, and lower than differentiation between subpopulations on the same island. The pollen-to-seed ratio was close to one, two orders of magnitude lower than the average estimated for other wind-pollinated, animal-dispersed plants. Our results showed that population turnover and geographical isolation increased genetic differentiation relative to an island model at equilibrium, but overall genetic structure was unexpectedly weak for a species distributed among islands. This empirical study shows that extensive gene flow, particularly mediated by seeds, can ameliorate population subdivision resulting from extinction-recolonization dynamics and isolation by distance","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.1767","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01091.x","PMID:20666841"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1767"}}