{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-28T19:46:36Z","author":["Moore, Ignacio T.","Martin, Paul R.","Bonier, Frances","Eikenaar, Cas"],"title":"Data from: Extrapair paternity rates vary with latitude and elevation in Emberizid sparrows","host":"Bonier F, Eikenaar C, Martin PR, Moore IT (2013) Extrapair paternity rates vary with latitude and elevation in Emberizid sparrows. The American Naturalist 183(1): 54-61.","keywords":["Bird","Ecology: behavioral","Behavior: social","Mating systems","Behavior: reproductive","Reproduction: comparative","Parental care"],"description":"Mating systems can vary among species and populations and thus influence evolutionary trajectories, ecological traits, and population demography. The siring of offspring by an extrapair male, or extrapair paternity (EPP), is a widespread and varied phenomenon in all vertebrate classes. However, we do not understand all of the factors associated with variation in EPP rates. The breeding synchrony hypothesis suggests that EPP rates should increase with latitude and elevation, whereas the paternal care hypothesis predicts that EPP rates should decrease with elevation. To address these hypotheses, we investigated how population EPP rates vary over elevation and latitude in emberizid sparrows. In comparative analyses including the effects of phylogeny, the relationship between EPP rates and elevation depended on latitude. EPP rates were greater in higher-latitude populations. But within higher-latitude populations, EPP rates decreased with increasing elevation. These findings provide support for both the breeding synchrony and paternal care hypotheses, suggesting that in lower-latitude, higher-elevation populations, the need for male parental care does not outweigh the benefits of seeking extrapair fertilizations in populations with relatively synchronous breeding. In contrast, at higher-latitude, higher-elevation sites, the need for male parental care is greater and might drive lower rates of extrapair mating despite highly synchronous breeding.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.3h771/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.3h771/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53313","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53313","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/674130","PMID:24334735"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3h771"}}