{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Systematic Biology","keywords":["molecular evolution","ribosomal DNA","insect phylogeny","Combined analysis"],"host":"Flook PK, Klee S, Rowell CHF (1999) Combined molecular phylogenetic analysis of the Orthoptera (Arthropoda, Insecta) and implications for their higher systematics. Systematic Biology 48: 233-253.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.408/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.408","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-28T18:43:23Z","author":["Klee, S.","Flook, P. K.","Rowell, C. H. F."],"title":"Data from: Combined molecular phylogenetic analysis of the Orthoptera (Arthropoda, Insecta) and implications for their higher systematics","description":"A phylogenetic analysis of mitochondrial and nuclear rDNA sequences from species of all the superfamilies of the insect order Orthoptera (grasshoppers, crickets and relatives) confirmed that although mitochondrial sequences provided good resolution of the youngest superfamilies, nuclear rDNA sequences were necessary to separate the basal groups. To try to reconcile these data sets into a single fully resolved orthopteran phylogeny, we adopted consensus and combined data strategies. The consensus analysis produced a partially resolved tree, lacking several well-supported features of the individual analyses. However, this lack of resolution was explained by an examination of resampled data sets that identified the likely source of error as the relatively short length of the individual mitochondrial data partitions. In a subsequent comparison in which the mitochondrial sequences were initially combined, we observed less conflict. We then used two approaches to examine the validity of combining all of the data in a single analysis; comparative analysis of trees recovered from resampled data sets and the application of a randomization test. The results did not point to significant levels of heterogeneity in phylogenetic signal between the mitochondrial and nuclear data sets, and we therefore proceeded with a combined analysis. Reconstructing phylogenies under the minimum evolution and maximum likelihood optimality criteria, we examined monophyly of the major orthopteran groups using nonparametric and parametric bootstrap analysis and Kishino-Hasegawa tests. Our analysis suggests that phylogeny reconstruction under the ML criteria is the most discriminating approach for the combined sequences. The results indicate that the caeliferan Pneumoroidea and Pamphagoidea (as previously suggested) are polyphyletic. The Acridoidea is redefined to include all pamphagoid families other than the Pyrgomorphidae, which we propose should be accorded superfamily status.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.408","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1080/106351599260274","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.408"}}