{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["47:4, 545 - 567","Systematic Biology"],"keywords":["morphology","ndhF","rbcL","congruence tests","chloroplast DNA","incongruence"],"host":"Graham, Sean W. (1998) 'Phylogenetic Congruence and Discordance Among One Morphological and Three Molecular Data Sets fromPontederiaceae', Systematic Biology, 47:4, 545 - 567","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.116/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.116/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.116","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-28T19:10:15Z","author":["Eckenwalder, James E.","Graham, Sean W.","Morton, Brian R.","Kohn, Joshua R.","Barrett, Spencer C.H."],"title":"Data from: Phylogenetic Congruence and Discordance Among One Morphological and Three Molecular Data Sets from Pontederiaceae","description":"A morphological data set and three sources of data from the chloroplast genome (two genes and a restriction-site survey) were used to reconstruct the phylogenetic history of the Pickerelweed family Pontederiaceae. The chloroplast data are converging to a single tree, presumably the true chloroplast phylogeny of the family. Unrooted trees estimated from the three chloroplast data sets were identical or extremely similar in shape to each other, mostly robustly supported and there was no evidence of significant heterogeneity among them. The few topological differences seen among unrooted trees from each chloroplast data set are probably artifacts of sampling error on short branches. Despite well documented differences in rates of evolution for different characters in individual data sets, equally weighted parsimony therefore permits accurate reconstructions of chloroplast relationships in Pontederiaceae. A separate morphology-based data set yielded trees that were very different from the chloroplast trees. While there was substantial support by the morphological evidence for several major clades supported by chloroplast trees, most of the conflicting phylogenetic structure on the morphology trees was not robust. Nonetheless, several statistical tests of incongruence indicate significant heterogeneity between molecules and morphology. The source of this apparent incongruence appears to be a low ratio of phylogenetic signal to noise in the morphological data.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.116","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1080/106351598260572","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.116"}}