{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-12-14T20:03:12Z","author":["Sumida, Masayuki","Oumi, Shohei","Igawa, Takeshi","Katsuren, Seiki"],"title":"Data from: Population structure and landscape genetics of two endangered frog species of Genus Odorrana: different scenarios on two islands","host":"Igawa T, Oumi S, Katsuren S, Sumida M (2012)  Population structure and landscape genetics of two endangered frog species of Genus Odorrana: different scenarios on two islands. Heredity 110: 45-56.","keywords":["microsatellite","population genetics","endangered species","cost path analysis","gene flow","ecological niche modeling"],"description":"Isolation by distance and landscape connectivity are fundamental factors underlying speciation and evolution. To understand how landscapes affect gene flow and shape population structures, island species provide intrinsic study objects. We investigated the effects of landscapes on the population structure of the endangered frog species, Odorrana ishikawae and O. splendida, which each inhabit an island in southwest Japan. This was done by examining population structure, gene flow, and demographic history of each species by analyzing 12 microsatellite loci and exploring causal environmental factors through ecological niche modeling (ENM) and the cost-distance approach. Our results revealed that the limited gene flow and multiple population structure in O. splendida and the single population structure in O. ishikawae were maintained after divergence of the species through ancient vicariance between islands. We found that genetic distance correlated with geographic dist ance between populations of both species. Our landscape genetic analysis revealed that the connectivity of suitable habitats influences gene flow and leads to the formation of specific population structures. In particular, different degrees of topographical complexity between islands are the major determining factor for shaping contrasting population structures of two species. In conclusion, our results illustrate the diversification mechanism of organisms through the interaction with space and environment. Our results also present an ENM approach for identifying the key factors affecting demographic history and population structures of target species, especially endangered species.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n17d2/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.41786","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.41786","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2012.59","PMID:22990312"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n17d2"}}