{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-28T22:19:20Z","author":["Sota, Teiji","Tanabe, Tsutomu"],"title":"Data from: Both male and female novel traits promote the correlated evolution of genitalia between the sexes in an arthropod","host":"Tanabe T, Sota T (2013) Both male and female novel traits promote the correlated evolution of genitalia between the sexes in an arthropod. Evolution 68(2): 441–452.","keywords":["Sexual Conflict","Coevolution","Morphological Evolution","Selection - Sexual"],"description":"The correlated evolution of genitalia between sexes has been demonstrated in many taxa. However, it remains unclear whether female rather than male genitalia can play a key role in the correlated evolution of male and female genitalia. We conducted an extensive cross-population analysis of the divergence patterns of genital structures, weights of whole genital organs and the bodies of both sexes, and male genital length in a group of xystodesmid millipedes showing diverse genital morphologies. We demonstrate that the correlated evolution of male and female genitalia toward exaggerated states has occurred in the millipedes, which have evolved novel traits in both males (forceps-like gonopods) and females (retractable bellows). Enlargement and elongation of forceps-like gonopods may be advantageous in sperm competition, whereas enlargement and elongation of the bellows may facilitate acceptance/rejection of insemination for ensuring the female's fitness. These male and female genital parts have affected the correlated evolution in the opposite sex, resulting in diversification and exaggeration of genital morphology. Our study suggests that evolutionary novel traits in not only males but also in females could play an important role in the correlated evolution of genitalia between the sexes.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.h6t17/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.h6t17/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54567","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54567","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24116383","doi:10.1111/evo.12288"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h6t17"}}