{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-24T15:48:31Z","author":["Guérécheau, Aurélie","Flot, Jean-François","Bonhomme, François","Arnaud-Haond, Sophie","Adjeroud, Mehdi","Vidal-Dupiol, Jeremie"],"title":"Data from: Genetic diversity, clonality and connectivity in the scleractinian coral Pocillopora damicornis: a multi-scale analysis in an insular, fragmented reef system","host":"Adjeroud M, Guérécheau A, Vidal-Dupiol J, Flot J, Arnaud-Haond S, Bonhomme F (2013) Genetic diversity, clonality and connectivity in the scleractinian coral Pocillopora damicornis: a multi-scale analysis in an insular, fragmented reef system. Marine Biology 161(3): 531-541.","keywords":["microsatellite","asexual reproduction","scleractinian corals","genetic structuring","coral reefs"],"description":"Clonality and genetic structure of the coral Pocillopora damicornis sensu lato were assessed using five microsatellites in 12 populations from four islands of the Society Archipelago (French Polynesia) sampled in June 2008. The 427 analysed specimens fell into 132 multilocus genotypes (MLGs), suggesting that asexual reproduction plays an important role in the maintenance of these populations. A haploweb analysis of ITS2 sequences of each MLG was consistent with all of them being conspecific. Genetic differentiation was detected both between and within islands, but when a single sample per MLG was included in the analyses, the populations turned out to be nearly panmictic. These observations provide further evidence of the marked variability in reproductive strategies and genetic structure of P. damicornis throughout its geographic range; comparison with results previously obtained for the congeneric species Pocillopora meandrina underlines the importance of life history traits in shaping the genetic structure of coral populations.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.b5r86/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.b5r86/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.b5r86/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56563","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56563","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1007/s00227-013-2355-9","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.b5r86"}}