{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-23T14:35:31Z","author":["Joore, Ivo K. C. W.","Schim van der Loeff, Maarten Franciscus","de Vries, Henry J. C.","van Dam, Alje","van Rooijen, Martijn Sebastiaan","de Neeling, A. J."],"title":"Data from: Low prevalence of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus among men who have sex with men attending an STI clinic in Amsterdam, a cross-sectional study","host":"Joore IKCW, van Rooijen MS, Schim van der Loeff MF, de Neeling AJ, van Dam A, de Vries HJC (2013) Low prevalence of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus among men who have sex with men attending an STI clinic in Amsterdam, a cross-sectional study. BMJ Open 3: 002505.","keywords":["Infection control","Microbiology","Dermatology","Infectious diseases & infestations","Public health"],"description":"Objective: Community-associated methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (CA-MRSA) is common among men who have sex with men (MSM) in the USA. It is unknown whether this is also the case in Amsterdam, the Netherlands. Design: Cross-sectional study. Setting: Sexually transmitted infection outpatient low- threshold clinic, Amsterdam, the Netherlands. Participants: Between October 2008 and April 2010, a total of 211 men were included, in two groups: (1) 74 MSM with clinical signs of a skin or soft tissue infection (symptomatic group) and (2) 137 MSM without clinical signs of such infections (asymptomatic group). Primary outcome measures: S aureus and MRSA infection and/or colonisation. Swabs were collected from the anterior nasal cavity, throat, perineum, penile glans and, if present, from infected skin lesions. Culture for S aureus was carried out on blood agar plates and for MRSA on selective chromagar plates after enrichment in broth. If MRSA was found, the spa- gene was sequenced. Secondary outcome measures: Associated demographic characteristics, medical history, risk factors for colonisation with S aureus and high-risk sexual behaviour were collected through a self- completed questionnaire. Results: The prevalence of S aureus colonisation in the nares was 37%, the pharynx 11%, the perianal region 12%, the glans penis 10% and in skin lesions 40%. In multivariable analysis adjusting for age, anogenital S aureus colonisation was significantly associated with the symptomatic group (p=0.01) and marginally with HIV ( p=0.06). MRSA was diagnosed in two cases: prevalence 0.9% (95% CI 0.1% to 3.4%)). Neither had CA-MRSA strains. Conclusions: CA-MRSA among MSM in Amsterdam is rare. Genital colonisation of S aureus is not associated with high-risk sexual behaviour.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.569j0/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46234","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46234","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23468471","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-002505"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.569j0"}}