{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-09T15:11:31Z","author":["Ebert, Dieter","Routtu, Jarkko"],"title":"Data from: Genetic architecture of resistance in Daphnia hosts against two species of host-specific parasites","keywords":["host-parasite","NFDS","coevolution","QTL"],"description":"Understanding the genetic architecture of host resistance is key for understanding the evolution of host-parasite interactions. Evolutionary models often assume simple genetics based on few loci and strong epistasis. It is unknown, however, whether these assumptions apply to natural populations. Using a quantitative trait loci (QTL) approach, we explore the genetic architecture of resistance in the crustacean Daphnia magna to two of its natural parasites: the horizontally transmitted bacterium Pasteuria ramosa, and the horizontally and vertically transmitted microsporidium Hamiltosporidium tvaerminnensis. This two system have become models for studies on the evolution of host-parasite interactions. In the QTL panel used here, Daphnia's resistance to P. ramosa is controlled by a single major QTL (which explains 50% of the observed variation). Resistance to H. tvaerminnensis horizontal infections shows a signature of a quantitative trait based in multiple loci with we ak epistatic interactions (together explaining 38% variation). Resistance to H. tvaerminnensis vertical infections, however, shows only one QTL (explaining 13.5% variance) that co-localizes with one of the QTLs for horizontal infections. QTLs for resistance to Pasteuria and Hamiltosporidium do not co-localize. We conclude that the genetics of resistance in D. magna are drastically different for these two parasites. Furthermore, we infer that, based on these and earlier results, the mechanisms of coevolution differ strongly for the two host-parasite systems. Only the Pasteuria - Daphnia system being expected to follow the negative frequency dependent selection (Red Queen) model. How coevolution works in the Hamiltosporidium-Daphnia system remains unclear.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2260t/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70445","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70445","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2260t"}}