{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-07-06T14:40:39Z","author":["Lye, Gillian C","Lepais, Olivier","Goulson, Dave"],"title":"Data from: Reconstructing demographic events from population genetic data: the introduction of bumblebees to New Zealand","host":"Lye GC, Lepais O, Goulson D (2011) Reconstructing demographic events from population genetic data: the introduction of bumblebees to New Zealand. Molecular Ecology 20(14): 2888–2900.","keywords":["Population Genetics - Empirical","Conservation Genetics","Invasive Species","Insects"],"description":"Four British bumblebee species (Bombus terrestris, Bombus hortorum, Bombus ruderatus and Bombus subterraneus) became established in New Zealand following their introduction at the turn of the last century. Of these, two remain common in the UK (B. terrestris and B. hortorum), whilst two (B. ruderatus and B. subterraneus) have undergone marked declines, the latter being declared extinct in 2000. The presence of these bumblebees in New Zealand provides an unique system in which four related species have been isolated from their source population for over 100 years, providing a rare opportunity to examine the impacts of an initial bottleneck and introduction to a novel environment on their population genetics. We used microsatellite markers to compare modern populations of B. terrestris, B. hortorum and B. ruderatus in the UK and New Zealand and to compare museum specimens of British B. subterraneus with the current New Zealand population. We used Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) to estimate demographic parameters of the introduction history, notably to estimate the number of founders used in the initial introduction. Species-specific patterns derived from genetic analysis were consistent with predictions based on the presumed history of these populations; demographic events have left a marked genetic signature on all four species. Approximate Bayesian analyses suggest that the New Zealand population of B. subterraneus may have been founded by as few as two individuals, giving rise to low genetic diversity and marked genetic divergence from the (now extinct) UK population.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sk22v/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.18090","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.18090","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05139.x","PMID:21645159"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.sk22v"}}