{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-24T15:25:38Z","author":["Senior, A.","Westerdahl, H.","Nakagawa, S.","Kamiya, T.","O'Dwyer, K."],"title":"Data from: A quantitative review of MHC-based mating preference: the role of diversity and dissimilarity","keywords":["Mate choice","Meta-analysis","MHC"],"description":"A large body of literature is equivocal on causal processes through which selection operates on the Major Histocompatibility Complex genes (MHC). Besides their crucial immune functions, sexual selection hypotheses stipulate that MHC genes constitute a key molecular underpinning for mate choice in vertebrates. The last four decades saw growing empirical literature on the role of MHC diversity and dissimilarity in mate choice for a wide range of vertebrate animals, but with mixed support for its significance in natural populations. Using formal phylogenetic meta-analytic and meta-regression techniques, we quantitatively review the existing literature on MHC-dependent mating preferences in non-human vertebrates with a focus on the role of MHC diversity and dissimilarity. Overall, we found small, statistically non-significant, average effect sizes for both diversity- and dissimilarity-based mate choice (r = 0.113 and 0.064, respectively). However, meta-regression models revealed statistically significant support regarding female choice for diversity, and choice for dissimilarity (regardless of choosy sex) only when dissimilarity is characterised across multiple loci. Little difference was found among vertebrate taxa; however, the lack of statistical power meant statistically significant effects were limited to some taxa. We found little sign of publication bias, thus our results provide a fair representation of the current literature. In light of our quantitative assessment, interesting, yet underrepresented questions, methodological improvements, and fruitful future avenues of research are highlighted.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.288j7/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.288j7/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.288j7/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66008","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66008","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.288j7"}}