{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-28T20:01:57Z","author":["Ushimaru, Atushi","Dohzono, Ikumi","Kobayashi, Atsumi"],"title":"Data from: Does urbanization promote floral diversification? Implications from changes in herkogamy with pollinator availability in an urban-rural area","host":"Ushimaru A, Kobayashi A, Dohzono I (2014) Does urbanization promote floral diversification? Implications from changes in herkogamy with pollinator availability in an urban-rural area. The American Naturalist 184(2): 258-267.","keywords":["urbanization","floral diversification","plant-pollinator interaction"],"description":"Although land-use changes such as urbanization have dramatically altered plant-pollinator interactions, little is known about their effects on pollen limitation and floral traits. In this study, we examined pollinator visit frequency, reproductive success, and floral trait measurements in 12 populations of the annual andromonoecious Commelina communis in an urban-rural area. Pollinator and mate availability decreased significantly with developed land area around the study site. Most urbanized populations suffered from significant pollinator-limited male and/or female reproductive success. High fruit set in urbanized populations may suggest the presence of high reproductive assurance by selfing. The stigma height and degree of herkogamy significantly decreased with increased pollinator limitation. Petal length, anther height, and/or the pollen:ovule ratio tended to be low in pollinator- and mate-limited urban populations. One urban population with high pollinator availability had flowers with higher herkogamy and stigma height compared to rural populations. These results suggest that urbanization may provide diverse selective forces that could affect the phenotypic variation in floral traits.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.pd775/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.pd775/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.pd775/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.60117","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.60117","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25058285","doi:10.1086/676855"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pd775"}}