{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-08-16T15:49:53Z","author":["Eizirik, Eduardo","Smith, Heath B","Michalski, Fernanda","Vynne, Carly","Valdez, Fernanda Pedone","Zieminski, Chris","Norris, Darren","Metzger, Jean Paul","Wasser, Samuel K","Trinca, Cristine S","Kashivakura, Cyntia Kayo"],"title":"Data from: Successful carnivore identification with faecal DNA across a fragmented Amazonian landscape","host":"Michalski F, Valdez FP, Norris D, Zieminski C, Kashivakura CK, Trinca CS, Smith HB, Vynne C, Wasser SK, Metzger JP, Eizirik E (2011) Successful carnivore identification with faecal DNA across a fragmented Amazonian landscape. Molecular Ecology Resources 11(5): 862–871.","keywords":["Habitat Degradation","Mammals","Conservation Biology","Ecological Genetics","Wildlife Management"],"description":"The use of scat surveys to obtain DNA has been well documented in temperate areas, where DNA preservation may be more effective than in tropical forests. Samples obtained in the tropics are often exposed to high humidity, warm temperatures, frequent rain, and intense sunlight, all of which can rapidly degrade DNA. Despite these potential problems, we demonstrate successful DNA amplification and sequencing for faeces of carnivores collected in tropical conditions and quantify how sample condition and environmental variables influence the success of PCR amplification and species identification. Additionally the feasibility of genotyping nuclear microsatellites from jaguar (Panthera onca) faeces was investigated. From October 2007 to December 2008, 93 faecal samples were collected in the southern Brazilian Amazon. A total of eight carnivore species was successfully identified from 71% of all samples obtained. Information theoretic analysis revealed that the number of PCR attempts before a successful sequence was an important negative predictor across all three responses (success of species identification, success of species identification from the first sequence and PCR amplification success), whereas the relative importance of the other three predictors (sample condition, season, and distance from forest) varied between the three responses. Nuclear microsatellite amplification of DNA from jaguar faeces had lower success rates (15–44%) compared with those of the mtDNA marker. Our results show that DNA identification of carnivore species from faecal samples works efficiently in the Amazon forest and can provide data on species occurrence as well as a valuable tool for genetic, ecological and conservation studies.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.84220/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.18083","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.18083","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1755-0998.2011.03031.x","PMID:21676206"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.84220"}}