{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-12-12T16:47:58Z","author":["Mitchell-Olds, Thomas","Song, Bao-Hua","Rushworth, Catherine A.","Lee, Cheng-Ruei"],"title":"Data from: Boechera, a model system for ecological genomics","host":"Rushworth CA, Song B, Lee C, Mitchell-Olds T (2011) Boechera, a model system for ecological genomics. Molecular Ecology 20(23): 4843-4857.","keywords":["Population Genetics - Empirical","Evolution of Sex","Quantitative Genetics","Plant Mating Systems","Ecological Genetics","Life History Evolution"],"description":"The selection and development of a study system for evolutionary and ecological functional genomics (EEFG) depends on a variety of factors. Here we present the genus Boechera as an exemplary system with which to address ecological and evolutionary questions. Our focus on Boechera is based on several characteristics: 1) native populations in undisturbed habitats where current environments reflect historical conditions over several thousand years; 2) functional genomics benefitting from its close relationship to Arabidopsis thaliana; 3) inbreeding tolerance enabling development of recombinant inbred lines, near-isogenic lines, and positional cloning; 4) interspecific crosses permitting mapping for genetic analysis of speciation; 5) apomixis (asexual reproduction by seeds) in a genetically tractable diploid; and 6) broad geographic distribution in North America, permitting ecological genetics for a large research community. These characteristics, along with the current sequencing of three Boechera species by the Joint Genome Institute, position Boechera as a rapidly advancing system for EEFG studies.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.5s3kt727/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.5s3kt727/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.35205","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.35205","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05340.x","PMID:22059452"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5s3kt727"}}