{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-26T20:21:18Z","author":["Kim, Hyun Hee","Ryu, Kwang Bok","Park, Hye Mi","Yang, Tae Jin","Kim, Joo Hyung","Waminal, Nomar"],"title":"Data from: Karyotype analysis of Panax ginseng C.A. Meyer, 1843 (Araliaceae) based on rDNA loci and DAPI band distribution","host":"Waminal N, Park HM, Ryu KB, Kim JH, Yang TJ, Kim HH (2012) Karyotype analysis of Panax ginseng C.A. Meyer, 1843 (Araliaceae) based on rDNA loci and DAPI band distribution. Comparative Cytogenetics 6(4): 425-441.","keywords":["45S rDNA","5S rDNA","FISH","DAPI band"],"description":"Ginseng has long been considered a valuable plant owing to its medicinal properties; however, genomic information based on chromosome characterization and physical mapping of cytogenetic markers has been very limited. Dual-color FISH karyotype and DAPI banding analyses of Panax ginseng C. A. Meyer, 1843 were conducted using 5S and 45S rDNA probes. The somatic chromosome complement was 2n=48 with lengths from 3.3 µm to 6.3 µm. The karyotype was composed of 12 metacentric, 9 submetacentric, and 3 subtelocentric pairs. The 5S rDNA probe localized to the intercalary region of the short arm of pair 11, while the 45S rDNA was located at the secondary constriction of the subtelocentric satellited chromosome 14. DAPI bands were clearly observed for most chromosomes, with various signal intensities and chromosomal distributions that consequently improved chromosome identification. As a result, all 24 chromosomes could be distinguished and numbers were assigned to each chromosome for the first time. The results presented here will be useful for the on-going ginseng genome sequencing and further molecular-cytogenetic studies and breeding programs of ginseng.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.q1cb1/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.q1cb1/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.q1cb1/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.q1cb1/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.q1cb1/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.43621","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.43621","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24260682","doi:10.3897/compcytogen.v6i4.3740"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.q1cb1"}}