{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-07T18:10:00Z","author":["Tremblay, Johanne","Křen, Vladimir","Hamet, Pavel","Corbeil, Gilles","Krupková, Michaela","Kazdová, Ludmila","Šedová, Lucie","Křenová, Drahomira","Liška, Frantisek","Šeda, Ondrej"],"title":"Data from: Cd36-deficient congenic strains show improved glucose tolerance and distinct shifts in metabolic and transcriptomic profiles","host":"Šeda O, Šedová L, Liška F, Křenová D, Kazdová L, Tremblay J, Krupková M, Corbeil G, Hamet P, Křen V (2012) Cd36-deficient congenic strains show improved glucose tolerance and distinct shifts in metabolic and transcriptomic profiles. Heredity 109(1): 63–70.","description":"Deficiency of fatty acid translocase Cd36 has been shown to have a major role in the pathogenesis of metabolic syndrome in the spontaneously hypertensive rat (SHR). We have tested the hypothesis that the effects of Cd36 mutation on the features of metabolic syndrome are contextually dependent on genomic background. We have derived two new congenic strains by introgression of limited chromosome 4 regions of SHR origin, both including the defective Cd36 gene, into the genetic background of a highly inbred model of insulin resistance and dyslipidemia, polydactylous (PD) rat strain. We subjected standard diet-fed adult males of PD and the congenic PD.SHR4 strains to metabolic, morphometric and transcriptomic profiling. We observed significantly improved glucose tolerance and lower fasting insulin levels in PD.SHR4 congenics than in PD. One of the PD.SHR4 strains showed lower triglyceride concentrations across major lipoprotein fractions combined with higher levels of low-density lipoprotein cholesterol compared with the PD progenitor. The hepatic transcriptome assessment revealed a network of genes differentially expressed between PD and PD.SHR4 with significant enrichment by members of the circadian rhythmicity pathway (Arntl (Bmal1), Clock, Nfil3, Per2 and Per3). In summary, the introduction of the chromosome 4 region of SHR origin including defective Cd36 into the PD genetic background resulted in disconnected shifts of metabolic profile along with distinct changes in hepatic transcriptome. The synthesis of the current results with those obtained in other Cd36-deficient strains indicates that the eventual metabolic effect of a deleterious mutation such as that of SHR-derived Cd36 is not absolute, but rather a function of complex interactions between environmental and genomic background, upon which it operates.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.9f8q91q3/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.9f8q91q3/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38197","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38197","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2012.14","PMID:22473311"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9f8q91q3"}}