{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-14T17:05:14Z","author":["L贸pez de Heredia, Unai","Collada, Carmen","L贸pez, Rosana","Emerson, Brent C.","Gil, Luis"],"title":"Data from: Signatures of volcanism and aridity in the evolution of an insular pine (Pinus canariensis Chr. Sm. Ex DC in Buch)","host":"L贸pez de Heredia U, L贸pez R, Collada C, Emerson BC, Gil L (2014) Signatures of volcanism and aridity in the evolution of an insular pine (Pinus canariensis Chr. Sm. Ex DC in Buch).  Heredity 113(3): 240-249.","keywords":["Common garden","survival","growth"],"description":"Oceanic islands of volcanic origin provide useful templates for the study of evolution because they are subjected to recurrent perturbations that generate steep environmental gradients that may promote adaptation. Here we combine population genetic data from nuclear genes with the analysis of environmental variation and phenotypic data from common gardens to disentangle the confounding effects of demography and selection to identify the factors of importance for the evolution of the insular pine P. canariensis. Eight nuclear genes were partially sequenced in a survey covering the entire species range, and phenotypic traits were measured in four common gardens from contrasting environments. The explanatory power of population substrate age and environmental indices were assessed against molecular and phenotypic diversity estimates. In addition, neutral genetic variability (FST) and the genetic differentiation of phenotypic variation (QST) were compared in order to identify the evolutionary forces acting on these traits. Two key factors in the evolution of the species were identified: (1) recurrent volcanic activity has left an imprint in the genetic diversity of the nuclear genes; (2) aridity in southern slopes promotes local adaptation in the driest localities of P. canariensis, despite high levels of gene flow among populations.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.j774r/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.59496","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.59496","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24619181","doi:10.1038/hdy.2014.22"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.j774r"}}