{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-09T18:50:27Z","author":["Zhang, Chi","Yang, Ziheng","Rannala, Bruce"],"title":"Data from: Robustness of compound Dirichlet priors for Bayesian inference of branch lengths","host":"Zhang C, Rannala B, Yang Z (2012) Robustness of compound Dirichlet priors for Bayesian inference of branch lengths. Systematic Biology 61(5): 779-784.","keywords":["MrBayes","branch lengths","Bayesian phylogenetics","compound Dirichlet prior"],"description":"We modified the phylogenetic program MrBayes 3.1.2 to incorporate the compound Dirichlet priors for branch lengths proposed recently by Rannala et al. (2011 Mol. Biol. Evol. in press) as a solution to the problem of branch length overestimation in Bayesian phylogenetic inference. The compound Dirichlet prior specifies a fairly diffuse prior on the tree length (the sum of branch lengths) and uses a Dirichlet distribution to partition the tree length into branch lengths. Six problematic datasets originally analyzed by Brown et al. (2010 Syst. Biol. 59: 145-161) are re-analyzed using the modified version of MrBayes to investigate properties of Bayesian branch length estimation using the new priors. While the default exponential priors for branch lengths produced extremely long trees, the compound Dirichlet priors produced posterior estimates that are much closer to the maximum likelihood estimates. Furthermore, the posterior tree lengths were quite robust to changes in the paramter values in the compound Dirichlet priors, for example, when the prior mean of tree length changed over several orders of magnitude. Our results suggest that the compound Dirichlet priors may be useful for correcting branch length overestimation in phylogenetic analyses of empirical datasets.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.j1kn5tq6/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.j1kn5tq6/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.j1kn5tq6/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.37322","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.37322","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/sysbio/sys030","PMID:22328570"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.j1kn5tq6"}}