{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["0003-0147","The American Naturalist"],"keywords":["Macroecology","Species diversity","Modeling: individual based","Paleoecology","Metacommunities"],"host":"Tomašových A, Kidwell SM (2010) The effects of temporal resolution on species turnover and on testing metacommunity models. American Naturalist 175: 587-606.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.1172/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.1172/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.1172/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.1172","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T20:50:51Z","author":["Kidwell, Susan M.","Tomašových, Adam"],"title":"Data from: The effects of temporal resolution on species turnover\nand on testing metacommunity models","description":"Patterns of low temporal turnover in species composition found within\nlong paleoecological time series contrast with the high turnover\npredicted by dispersal-limited neutral metacommunity models and thus have been used to support non-neutral models. However, predictions assume temporal resolution on the scale of a season or year whereas\nindividual fossil assemblages are typically time-averaged to decadal\nor centennial time scales. Here, we simulate the effects of time\naveraging by building time-averaged assemblages from local\ndispersal-limited non-averaged (living) assemblages and compare the\npredicted species turnover with observed patterns in mollusk and\nostracod fossil records. Time averaging substantially reduces temporal\nturnover such that neutral predictions converge with those of\ntrade-off and density-dependent models, and tends to decrease species\ndominance and increase the proportion of rare species. Observed\nturnover rates are comparable to an appropriately scaled neutral model: patterns of high community stability can be produced or\nreinforced by time averaging alone. The community attributes of local\ntime-averaged assemblages approach those of the metacommunity.\nTime-averaged assemblages are thus unlikely to capture attributes\narising from processes operating at small spatial scales, but should\ndo well at capturing the turnover and diversity parameters of\nmetacommunities, and thus will be a valuable basis for analyzing the\nlarge-scale processes that determine metacommunity evolution.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.1172","isReferencedBy":["PMID:20302427","doi:10.1086/651661"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1172"}}