{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-17T14:38:48Z","author":["Barthel, Kathleen","Baldwin, Ian T.","Schuman, Meredith C."],"title":"Data from: Herbivory-induced volatiles function as defenses increasing fitness of the native plant Nicotiana attenuata in nature","host":"Schuman MC, Barthel K, Baldwin IT (2012) Herbivory-induced volatiles function as defenses increasing fitness of the native plant Nicotiana attenuata in nature. eLife 1: e00007.","keywords":["molecular ecology","plant defense","tritrophic interactions","GLVs","herbivore-induced plant volatiles","animal behavior","field ecology","HIPVs","plant volatiles","chemical ecology","PIs","green leaf volatiles","trypsin protease inhibitors"],"description":"From an herbivore’s first bite, plants release herbivory-induced plant volatiles (HIPVs) which can attract enemies of herbivores. However, other animals and competing plants can intercept HIPVs for their own use, and it remains unclear whether HIPVs serve as an indirect defense by increasing fitness for the emitting plant. In a two-year field study, HIPV-emitting N. attenuata plants produced twice as many buds and flowers as HIPV-silenced plants, but only when native Geocoris spp. predators reduced herbivore loads (by 50%) on HIPV-emitters. In concert with HIPVs, plants also employ antidigestive trypsin protease inhibitors (TPIs), but TPI-producing plants were not fitter than TPI-silenced plants. TPIs weakened a specialist herbivore’s behavioral evasive responses to simulated Geocoris spp. attack, indicating that TPIs function against specialists by enhancing indirect defense.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/20","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/21","doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f/12"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.41933","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.41933","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23066503","doi:10.7554/eLife.00007"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gs45f"}}