{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-06T14:34:48Z","author":["Ruiz-Trillo, Iñaki","Sebé-Pedrós, Arnau","Grau-Bové, Xavier"],"title":"Data from: A genomic survey of HECT ubiquitin ligases in eukaryotes reveals independent expansions of the HECT system in several lineages.","host":"Grau-Bové X, Sebé-Pedrós A, Ruiz-Trillo I (2013) A genomic survey of HECT ubiquitin ligases in eukaryotes reveals independent expansions of the HECT system in several lineages. Genome Biology and Evolution 5(5): 833-847.","description":"The post-translational modification of proteins by the ubiquitination pathway is an important regulatory mechanism in eukaryotes. To date, however, studies on the evolutionary history of the proteins involved in this pathway have been restricted to E1 and E2 enzymes, while E3 studies have been focused mainly in metazoans and plants. To have a wider perspective, here we perform a genomic survey of the HECT family of E3 ubiquitin-protein ligases, an important part of this post-translational pathway, in genomes from representatives of all major eukaryotic lineages. We classify eukaryotic HECTs and reconstruct, by phylogenetic analysis, the putative repertoire of these proteins in the last eukaryotic common ancestor (LECA). Furthermore, we analyse the diversity and complexity of protein domain architectures of HECTs along the different extant eukaryotic lineages. Our data show that LECA had six different HECTs and that protein expansion and N-terminal domain diversification shaped HECT evolution. Our data reveal that the genomes of animals and unicellular holozoans considerably increased the molecular and functional diversity of their HECT system compared to other eukaryotes. Other eukaryotes, such as the Apusozoa Thecanomas trahens or the Heterokonta Phytophthora infestans independently expanded their HECT repertoire. In contrast, plant, excavate, rhodophyte, chlorophyte and fungal genomes have a more limited enzymatic repertoire. Our genomic survey and phylogenetic analysis clarifies the origin and evolution of different HECT families among eukaryotes and provides a useful phylogenetic framework for future evolutionary studies of this regulatory pathway.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mt620/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.48976","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.48976","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23563970","doi:10.1093/gbe/evt052"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mt620"}}