{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-01-12T16:52:12Z","author":["Chenoweth, Stephen F.","Rundle, Howard D."],"title":"Data from: Stronger convex (stabilizing) selection on homologous sexual display traits in females than in males: a multipopulation comparison in Drosophila serrata","host":"Rundle HD, Chenoweth SF (2010) Stronger convex (stabilizing) selection on homologous sexual display traits in females than in males: a multipopulation comparison in Drosophila serrata. Evolution 65(3): 893–899.","keywords":["quadratic selection","sexual selection","mutual mate choice","nonlinear selection","Cuticular hydrocarbons"],"description":"Mutual mate choice for homologous sexual display traits has been demonstrated in Mutual mate choice for homologous sexual display traits has been demonstrated in several recent studies yet little attention has been given to quantitative comparison of the strength and form of mate preferences between the sexes. Such comparisons may provide important insight into the evolution of mate choice for honest signals. In particular, because females generally provide the majority of resources for initial offspring development, female displays may trade-off with fecundity, causing preference evolution to differ between the sexes. Recent theory suggests that adaptive male preferences for honest displays in females are possible under certain conditions and may result in preferences that are convex (i.e. stabilizing) in form. We compared sexual selection on a suite of contact pheromones arising from mutual mate choice using nine separate geographic populations of Drosophila serrata. We show that the convex selection is stronger on females than on males overall in these populations, and that convex selection is the predominate form of nonlinear selection on females but not males.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8633/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8633","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8633","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21361917","doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01158.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8633"}}