{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-06T18:06:07Z","author":["Davidoff, Kyla R.","Lohmann, Kenneth J.","Fuxjager, Matthew J.","Mangiamele, Lisa A."],"title":"Data from: The geomagnetic environment in which sea turtle eggs incubate affects subsequent magnetic navigation behavior of hatchlings","host":"Fuxjager MJ, Davidoff KR, Mangiamele LA, Lohmann KJ (2014) The geomagnetic environment in which sea turtle eggs incubate affects subsequent magnetic navigation behavior of hatchlings. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 281(1791): 20141218.","keywords":["ontogeny","sea turtle","magnetic orientation and navigation","magnetoreception","magnetic field"],"description":"Loggerhead sea turtle hatchlings (Caretta caretta) use regional magnetic fields as open-ocean navigational markers during trans-oceanic migrations. Little is known, however, about the ontogeny of this behaviour. As a first step towards investigating whether the magnetic environment in which hatchlings develop affects subsequent magnetic orientation behaviour, eggs deposited by nesting female loggerheads were permitted to develop in situ either in the natural ambient magnetic field or in a magnetic field distorted by magnets placed around the nest. In orientation experiments, hatchlings that developed in the normal ambient field oriented approximately south when exposed to a field that exists near the northern coast of Portugal, a direction consistent with their migratory route in the northeastern Atlantic. By contrast, hatchlings that developed in a distorted magnetic field had orientation indistinguishable from random when tested in the same north Portugal field. No differences existed between the two groups in orientation assays involving responses to orbital movements of waves or sea-finding, neither of which involves magnetic field perception. These findings, to our knowledge, demonstrate for the first time that the magnetic environment present during early development can influence the magnetic orientation behaviour of a neonatal migratory animal.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.4gv6t/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.4gv6t/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.4gv6t/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67271","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67271","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25100699","doi:10.1098/rspb.2014.1218"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.4gv6t"}}