{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-14T17:52:28Z","author":["Gonzalez, Elena G.","Pedraza-Lara, Carlos","Doadrio, Ignacio"],"title":"Data from: Genetic diversity and population history of the endangered killifish Aphanius baeticus","host":"Gonzalez EG, Pedraza-Lara C, Doadrio I (2014) Genetic diversity and population history of the endangered killifish Aphanius baeticus. Journal of Heredity 105(5): 597-610.","keywords":["Conservation genetics and biodiversity","secondary water fishes","conservation","Population structure and phylogeography","Pleistocene glaciations"],"description":"The secondary freshwater fish fauna of the western-Iberian Peninsula basin is primarily restricted to local coastal streams, and man-made salt evaporation ponds, etc., which are susceptible to periodical flood and drought events. Despite its uniqueness in ecological adaptation to high saltwater tolerance, very little is known about this fauna’s population dynamics and evolutionary history. The killifish, Aphanius baeticus (Cyprinodontidae) is an endemic species restricted to river basins on Spain’s southern Atlantic coastline, considered as “Endangered.” In this study, the genetic structure, diversity and historical demography of A. baeticus were analyzed using mitochondrial (cytochrome b, N = 131) and nuclear (4 out of 19 microsatellites tested, N = 288) markers across its distribution range. The phylogenetic and networking reconstruction revealed subtle phylogeographic structuring. A scattered expansion at the beginning of the interglacial periods, coupled with posterior events of extinction and colonization caused by periodical cycles of flooding, could explain the absence of well-defined phylogenetic relationships among populations. Moreover, very low genetic diversity values and a weak population differentiation were detected. We proposed that dispersals allowed by periodic floods connecting river drainages may have promoted a wide genetic exchange among populations and could have contributed to the current genetic relatedness of these populations.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1qs5c/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64018","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64018","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24939890","doi:10.1093/jhered/esu034"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1qs5c"}}