{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-12-12T20:08:49Z","author":["Garant, Dany","Perret, Philippe","Porlier, Melody","Charmantier, Anne"],"title":"Data from: Habitat-linked population genetic differentiation in the Blue tit Cyanistes caeruleus","host":"Porlier M, Garant D, Perret P, Charmantier A (2012) Habitat-linked population genetic differentiation in the Blue tit Cyanistes caeruleus. Journal of Heredity 103(6): 781-791.","keywords":["Environmental heterogeneity","Gene flow","Microsatellites","Population structure","Dispersal","Landscape genetics"],"description":"Although the recent emergence of the field of landscape genetics has led to several studies investigating the effects of habitat composition between populations on genetic differentiation, much less is known on the impact of within-habitat ecological characteristics on levels of gene flow and genetic differentiation among populations. Using data on 840 individuals sampled in 8 sites in Corsica and 1 in southern France and analyzed at 10 microsatellite loci, we assessed the spatial and temporal population genetic structure of blue tits (Cyanistes caeruleus) in Corsica and identified the ecological factors, both between- and within-sampling sites, responsible for the observed genetic structure. We found temporally stable fine-scale genetic structure within Corsica, with genetic differentiation values among populations corresponding to ~25% of levels observed between Corsica and the mainland. This structure was not explained by the geographic distance among populations or by the presence of physical barriers but was instead related to local habitat types (deciduous or evergreen oaks). Our results are thus consistent with previously documented phenotypic differences among habitats in morphological and reproductive traits. These findings suggest that although individuals have high dispersal ability, local adaptation might reduce gene flow among populations located in different habitats.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.5bd5r/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.5bd5r/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.41143","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.41143","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23087385","doi:10.1093/jhered/ess064"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5bd5r"}}