{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-20T20:07:50Z","author":["Ferrand, Nuno","Sousa, Vitor C.","Hey, Jody","Carneiro, Miguel"],"title":"Data from: Identifying loci under selection against gene flow in isolation with migration models","host":"Sousa VC, Carneiro M, Ferrand N, Hey J (2013) Identifying loci under selection against gene flow in isolation with migration models. Genetics 194(1): 211-233.","keywords":["Isolation with migration","Demographic history","Coalescent","Natural selection","MCMC"],"description":"When divergence occurs in the presence of gene flow, there can arise an interesting dynamic in which selection against gene flow, at sites associated with population-specific adaptations or genetic incompatibilities, can cause net gene flow to vary across the genome. Loci linked to sites under selection may experience reduced gene flow and may experience genetic bottlenecks by the action of nearby selective sweeps. Data from histories such as these may be poorly fitted by conventional neutral model approaches to demographic inference, which treat all loci as equally subject to forces of genetic drift and gene flow. To allow for demographic inference in the face of such histories, as well as the identification of loci affected by selection, we developed an isolation-with-migration model that explicitly provides for variation among genomic regions in migration rates and/or rates of genetic drift. The method allows for loci to fall into any of multiple groups, each characterized by a different set of parameters, thus relaxing the assumption that all loci share the same demography. By grouping loci, the method can be applied to data with multiple loci and still have tractable dimensionality and statistical power. We studied the performance of the method using simulated data, and we applied the method to study the divergence of two subspecies of European rabbits (Oryctolagus cuniculus).","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.vr7bb/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47104","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47104","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1534/genetics.113.149211","PMID:23457232"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.vr7bb"}}