{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-05T13:16:15Z","author":["Salvioli, Stefano","Franceschi, Claudio","Capri, Miriam","Termanini, Alberto","Bellavista, Elena","Tieri, Paolo"],"title":"Data from: Charting the NF-κB pathway interactome map","host":"Tieri P, Termanini A, Bellavista E, Salvioli S, Capri M, Franceschi C (2012) Charting the NF-κB pathway interactome map. PLoS ONE 7(3): e32678.","description":"Inflammation is part of a complex physiological response to harmful stimuli and pathogenic stress. The five components of the Nuclear Factor κB (NF-κB) family are prominent mediators of inflammation, acting as key transcriptional regulators of hundreds of genes. Several signaling pathways activated by diverse stimuli converge on NF-κB activation, resulting in a regulatory system characterized by high complexity. It is increasingly recognized that the number of components that impinges upon phenotypic outcomes of signal transduction pathways may be higher than those taken into consideration from canonical pathway representations. Scope of the present analysis is to provide a wider, systemic picture of the NF-κB signaling system. Data from different sources such as literature, functional enrichment web resources, protein-protein interaction and pathway databases have been gathered, curated, integrated and analyzed in order to reconstruct a single, comprehensive picture of the proteins that interact with, and participate to the NF-κB activation system. Such a reconstruction shows that the NF-κB interactome is substantially different in quantity and quality of components with respect to canonical representations. The analysis highlights that several neglected but topologically central proteins may play a role in the activation of NF-κB mediated responses. Moreover the interactome structure fits with the characteristics of a bow tie architecture. This interactome is intended as an open network resource available for further development, refinement and analysis.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ng730/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.43024","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.43024","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22403694","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0032678"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ng730"}}