{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-28T19:52:34Z","author":["Norris, D. Ryan","Griswold, Cortland K.","Betini, Gustavo S."],"title":"Data from: Density-mediated carry-over effects explain variation in breeding output across time in a seasonal population","host":"Betini GS, Griswold CK, Norris DR (2013) Density-mediated carry-over effects explain variation in breeding output across time in a seasonal population. Biology Letters 9(5): 20130582.","keywords":["Seasonality","Density-dependence"],"description":"In seasonal environments, where density dependence can operate throughout the annual cycle, vital rates are typically considered to be a function of the number of individuals at the beginning of each season. However, variation in density in the previous season could also cause surviving individuals to be in poor physiological condition, which could carry over to influence individual success in the following season. We examine this hypothesis using replicated populations of Drosophila melanogaster, the common fruitfly, over 23 non-overlapping generations with distinct breeding and non-breeding seasons. We found that the density at the beginning of the non-breeding season negatively affected the fresh weight of individuals that survived the non-breeding season and resulted in a 25% decrease in per capita breeding output among those that survived to the next season to breed. At the population level, per capita breeding output was best explained by a model that incorporated density at the beginning of the previous non-breeding season (carry-over effect, COE) and density at the beginning of the breeding season. Our results support the idea that density-mediated COEs are critical for understanding population dynamics in seasonal environments.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.nh43g/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.nh43g/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51834","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51834","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rsbl.2013.0582","PMID:23925837"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.nh43g"}}