{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-24T19:57:08Z","author":["Voelker, Gary","Mode, Nicolle A.","Drovetski, Sergei V.","Lopes, Ricardo J.","Aghayan, Sargis A.","Mata, Vanessa A.","Harvey, Johanna A."],"title":"Data from: Does the niche-breadth or trade-off hypothesis explain the abundance-occupancy relationship in avian haemosporidia?","host":"Drovetski SV, Aghayan SA, Mata VA, Lopes RJ, Mode NA, Harvey JA, Voelker G (2014) Does the niche-breadth or trade-off hypothesis explain the abundance-occupancy relationship in avian haemosporidia? Molecular Ecology 23(13): 3322–3329.","keywords":["host specialization","Host Parasite Interactions","abundance-occupancy relationship","blood parasites","Birds"],"description":"Two hypotheses have been proposed to explain the abundance-occupancy relationship (AOR) in parasites. The niche-breadth hypothesis suggests that host generalists are more abundant and efficient at colonizing different host communities than specialists. The trade-off hypothesis argues that host specialists achieve high density across their hosts’ ranges, whereas generalists incur the high cost of adaptation to diverse immuno-defense systems. We tested these hypotheses using 386 haemosporidian cytochrome-b lineages (1894 sequences) recovered from 2318 birds of 103 species sampled in NW Africa, NW Iberia, W Greater Caucasus, and Transcaucasia. The number of regions occupied by lineages was associated with their frequency suggesting the presence of AOR in avian Haemosporidia. However, neither hypothesis provided a better explanation for the AOR. Although, the host-generalist Plasmodium SGS1 was over 3 times more abundant than other widespread lineages, both host specialists and generalists were successful in colonizing all study regions and achieved overall high prevalence.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.r8bj6/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.r8bj6/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61416","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61416","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12744","PMID:24689968"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.r8bj6"}}