{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-01T18:48:08Z","author":["Cruz, Alexander","Ortega, Catherine P.","Kleist, Nathan J.","Francis, Clinton D."],"title":"Data from: Noise pollution alters ecological services: enhanced pollination and disrupted seed dispersal","host":"Francis CD, Kleist NJ, Ortega CP, Cruz A (2012) Noise pollution alters ecological services: enhanced pollination and disrupted seed dispersal. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 279(1739): 2727-2735.","keywords":["ecological service","Anthropogenic noise","seed dispersal","pollination","human disturbance","birds"],"description":"Noise pollution is a novel, widespread environmental force that has recently been shown to alter the behavior and distribution of birds and other vertebrates, yet whether noise has cumulative, community-level consequences by changing critical ecological services is unknown. Herein, we examined the effects of noise pollution on pollination and seed dispersal and seedling establishment within a study system that isolated the effects of noise from confounding stimuli common to human-altered landscapes. Using observations, vegetation surveys and pollen transfer and seed removal experiments, we found that effects of noise pollution can reverberate through communities by disrupting or enhancing these ecological services. Specifically, noise pollution indirectly increased artificial flower pollination by hummingbirds, but altered the community of animals that prey upon and disperse Pinus edulis seeds, potentially explaining reduced P. edulis seedling recruitment in noisy areas. Despite evidence that some ecological services, such as pollination, may benefit indirectly due to noise, declines in seedling recruitment for key dominant species like P. edulis may have dramatic long-term effects on ecosystem structure and diversity. Because the extent of noise pollution is growing, this study emphasizes that investigators should evaluate the ecological consequences noise alongside other human-induced environmental changes that are reshaping human-altered landscapes worldwide.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.6d2ps7s7/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.6d2ps7s7/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.6d2ps7s7/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38076","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38076","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1098/rspb.2012.0230","PMID:22438504"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.6d2ps7s7"}}