{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-02T15:52:59Z","author":["Zhang, Tao","Xue, Dong-Xiu","Liu, Jin-Xian","Wang, Hai-Yan"],"title":"Data from: Population genetic structure and demographic history of Atrina pectinata based on mitochondrial DNA and microsatellite markers","host":"Xue D, Wang H, Zhang T, Liu J (2014) Population genetic structure and demographic history of Atrina pectinata based on mitochondrial DNA and microsatellite markers. PLoS ONE 9(5): e95436.","keywords":["Demographic History","Microsatellite Markers","Population Genetic Structure"],"description":"The pen shell, Atrina pectinata, is one of the commercial bivalves in East Asia and thought to be recently affected by anthropogenic pressure (habitat destruction and/or fishing pressure). Information on its population genetic structure is crucial for the conservation of A. pectinata. Considering its long pelagic larval duration and iteroparity with high fecundity, the genetic structure for A. pectinata could be expected to be weak at a fine scale. However, the unusual oceanography in the coasts of China and Korea suggests potential for restricted dispersal of pelagic larvae and geographical differentiation. In addition, environmental changes associated with Pleistocene sea level fluctuations on the East China Sea continental shelf may also have strongly influenced historical population demography and genetic diversity of marine organisms. Here, partial sequences of the mitochondrial Cytochrome c oxidase subunit I (COI) gene and seven microsatellite loci were used to estimate population genetic structure and demographic history of seven samples from Northern China coast and one sample from North Korea coast. Despite high levels of genetic diversity within samples, there was no genetic differentiation among samples from Northern China coast and low but significant genetic differentiation between some of the Chinese samples and the North Korean sample. A late Pleistocene population expansion, probably after the Last Glacial Maximum, was also demonstrated for A. pectinata samples. No recent genetic bottleneck was detected in any of the eight samples. We concluded that both historical recolonization (through population range expansion and demographic expansion in the late Pleistocene) and current gene flow (through larval dispersal) were responsible for the weak level of genetic structure detected in A. pectinata.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.52hn0/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.61983","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.61983","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.52hn0"}}