{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-15T18:30:12Z","author":["Mukherjee, Debarati","Ray, Sanghamitra"],"title":"Data from: A new Hyperodapedon (Archosauromorpha, Rhynchosauria) from the Upper Triassic of India: implications on Rynchosaur phylogeny","host":"Mukherjee D, Ray S (2014) A new Hyperodapedon (Archosauromorpha, Rhynchosauria) from the Upper Triassic of India: implications on Rynchosaur phylogeny. Palaeontology, online in advance of print.","keywords":["anatomy","postcranial","cranial"],"description":"A new species of the rhynchosaur genus Hyperodapedon, namely H. tikiensis, is described from well-preserved skeletal elements that were collected from the Upper Triassic Tiki Formation of India. Hyperodapedon tikiensis is diagnosed on the basis of several cranial and postcranial features including longer than wide basipterygoid process, crest-shaped maxillary cross section lateral to the main longitudinal groove, deeply excavated neural arches of mid-dorsal vertebrae, long scapular blade, a pronounced deltopectoral crest, proximal humeral end much broader than distal end, iliac length greater than iliac height, equal pre- and postacetabular iliac lengths and circular femoral cross section. Two distinct morphotypes of the maxillary tooth plates can be discerned, which are attributed to ontogenetic variations. A maximum-parsimony analysis was carried out to show that the order Rhynchosauria is characterized by nine cranial and one postcranial character states. The analysis reveals that Otischalkia elderae is invalid and the basal forms, Howesia and Mesosuchus, are closely related. The Mid-Triassic genus Ammorhynchus is more derived and forms a sister group to the Late Triassic subfamily Hyperodapedontinae. Isalorhynchus and Teyumbaita are basal to the pandemic genus Hyperodapedon. Twenty-four characters that are not homoplasious document major patterns of skeletal evolution in rhynchosaurs. From laterally oriented scapula and slender propodials, the postcranial skeleton evolved into a more robust form as is evident from nearly vertical scapula and increase in the robustness of the propodials. Shortening of the femur is noted in the derived Late Triassic forms as exemplified in Hyperodapedon gordoni, Hyperodapedon huxleyi and H. tikiensis.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.gk880/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.gk880/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.gk880/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.gk880/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.60915","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.60915","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/pala.12113","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gk880"}}