{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-21T14:36:42Z","author":["Taylor, Douglas R.","Fields, Peter D.","McCauley, David E.","McAssey, Edward V."],"title":"Data from: Patterns of cyto-nuclear linkage disequilibrium in Silene latifolia: genomic heterogeneity and temporal stability","host":"Fields PD, McCauley DE, McAssey EV, Taylor DR (2013) Patterns of cyto-nuclear linkage disequilibrium in Silene latifolia: genomic heterogeneity and temporal stability. Heredity 112(2): 99–104.","keywords":["atp1 SNP","microsatellite","linkage disequilibrium","cyto-nuclear"],"description":"Non-random association of alleles in the nucleus and cytoplasmic organelles, or cyto-nuclear linkage disequilibrium (LD), is both an important component of a number of evolutionary processes and a statistical indicator of others. The evolutionary significance of cyto-nuclear LD will depend on both its magnitude and how stable those associations are through time. Here, we use a longitudinal population genetic data set to explore the magnitude and temporal dynamics of cyto-nuclear disequilibria through time. We genotyped 135 and 170 individuals from 16 and 17 patches of the plant species Silene latifolia in Southwestern VA, sampled in 1993 and 2008, respectively. Individuals were genotyped at 14 highly polymorphic microsatellite markers and a single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in the mitochondrial gene, atp1. Normalized LD (D′) between nuclear and cytoplasmic loci varied considerably depending on which nuclear locus was considered (ranging from 0.005–0.632). Four of the 14 cyto-nuclear associations showed a statistically significant shift over approximately seven generations. However, the overall magnitude of this disequilibrium was largely stable over time. The observed origin and stability of cyto-nuclear LD is most likely caused by the slow admixture between anciently diverged lineages within the species’ newly invaded range, and the local spatial structure and metapopulation dynamics that are known to structure genetic variation in this system.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7c730/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51409","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51409","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.79","PMID:24002238"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7c730"}}