{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"8;8;2013","keywords":["circadian rhythm","urban ecology","conservation","behavior","urbanisation","vocal communication","birdsong","morning chorus","habitat fragmentation","nightscape"],"host":"Nordt A, Klenke R (2013) Sleepless in town – drivers of the temporal shift in dawn song in urban European Blackbirds. PLoS ONE 8(8): e71476.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.vg75p/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53074","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2013-08-19T19:21:47Z","author":["Klenke, Reinhard","Nordt, Anja"],"title":"Data from: Sleepless in town – drivers of the temporal shift in dawn song in urban European Blackbirds","description":"Organisms living in urban environments are exposed to different environmental conditions compared to their rural conspecifics. Especially anthropogenic noise and artificial night light are closely linked to urbanization and pose new challenges to urban species. Songbirds are particularly affected by these factors, because they rely on the spread of acoustic information and adjust their behaviour to the rhythm of night and day, e.g. time their dawn song according to changing light intensities. Our aim was to clarify the specific contributions of artificial night light and traffic noise on the timing of dawn song of urban European Blackbirds (Turdus merula). We investigated the onset of blackbird dawn song along a steep urban gradient ranging from an urban forest to the city centre of Leipzig, Germany. This gradient of anthropogenic noise and artificial night light was reflected in the timing of dawn song. In the city centre, blackbirds started their dawn song up to 5 hours earlier compared to those in semi-natural habitats. We found traffic noise to be the driving factor of the shift of dawn song into true night, although it was not completely separable from the effects of ambient night light. We additionally included meteorological conditions into the analysis and found an effect on the song onset. Cloudy and cold weather delayed the onset, but cloud cover was assumed to reflect night light emissions, thus, amplified sky luminance and increased the effect of artificial night light. Beside these temporal effects, we also found differences in the spatial autocorrelation of dawn song onset showing a much higher variability in noisy city areas than in rural parks and forests. These findings indicate that urban hazards such as ambient noise and light pollution show a manifold interference with naturally evolved cycles and have significant effects on the activity patterns of urban blackbirds.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53074","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0071476","PMID:23940759"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.vg75p"}}