{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-11-07T18:05:08Z","author":["Johansson, Magnus","Töpel, Mats","Elväng, Annelie","Bertrand, Yann","Melik, Wessam"],"title":"Data from: First dating of a recombination event in mammalian tick-borne flaviviruses","host":"Bertrand Y, Töpel M, Elväng A, Melik W, Johansson M (2012) First dating of a recombination event in mammalian tick-borne flaviviruses. PLoS ONE, 7(2): e31981.","keywords":["Bayesian dating","phylogeny","recombination","Louping ill virus","Tick-borne encephalitis virus","network","mammalian tick-borne flavivirus group"],"description":"The mammalian tick-borne flavivirus group (MTBFG) contains viruses associated with important human and animal diseases such as encephalitis and hemorrhagic fever. In contrast to mosquito-borne flaviviruses where recombination events are frequent, the evolutionary dynamic within the MTBFG was believed to be essentially clonal. This assumption was challenged with the recent report of several homologous recombinations within the Tick-borne encephalitis virus TBEV. We performed a thorough analysis of publicly available genomes in this group and found no compelling evidence for the previously identified recombinations. However, our results show for the first time that demonstrable recombination (i.e., with large statistical support and strong phylogenetic evidences) has occurred in the MTBFG, more specifically within the Louping ill virus lineage. Putative parents, recombinant strains and breakpoints were further tested for statistical significance using phylogenetic methods. We investigated the time of divergence between the recombinant and parental strains in a Bayesian framework. The recombination was estimated to have occurred during a window period of 282 to 76 years before the present. By unravelling the temporal setting of the event, we adduce hypotheses","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/19","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/32","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/31","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/14","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/17","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/18","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/15","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/16","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/36","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/35","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/34","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/33","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/21","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/20","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/27","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/26","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/29","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/28","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/23","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/22","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/25","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd/24"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.37480","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.37480","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22384119","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0031981"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.504636cd"}}