{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-09-09T16:07:24Z","author":["Kamler, Jan F.","Oh, Annie","Macdonald, David W.","Gray, Melissa M."],"title":"Data from: Genetic structure, spatial organization, and dispersal in two populations of bat-eared foxes","host":"Kamler JF, Gray MM, Oh A, Macdonald DW (2013) Genetic structure, spatial organization, and dispersal in two populations of bat-eared foxes. Ecology and Evolution 3(9): 2892–2902.","keywords":["philopatry","home range overlap","density","group size"],"description":"We incorporated radio-telemetry data with genetic analysis of bat-eared foxes (Otocyon megalotis) from individuals in 32 different groups to examine relatedness and spatial organization in two populations in South Africa that differed in density, home-range sizes, and group sizes. Kin clustering occurred only for female dyads in the high-density population. Relatedness was negatively correlated with distance only for female dyads in the high-density population, and for male and mixed-sex dyads in the low-density population. Home-range overlap of neighboring female dyads was significantly greater in the high compared to low-density population, whereas overlap within other dyads was similar between populations. Amount of home-range overlap between neighbors was positively correlated with genetic relatedness for all dyad-site combinations, except for female and male dyads in the low-density population. Foxes from all age and sex classes dispersed, although females (mostly adults) dispersed farther than males. Yearlings dispersed later in the high-density population, and overall exhibited a male-biased dispersal pattern. Our results indicated that genetic structure within populations of bat-eared foxes was sex-biased, and was interrelated to density and group sizes, as well as sex-biases in philopatry and dispersal distances. We conclude that a combination of male-biased dispersal rates, adult dispersals, and sex-biased dispersal distances likely helped to facilitate inbreeding avoidance in this evolutionarily unique species of Canidae.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.85066/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.50903","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.50903","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1002/ece3.683","PMID:24101981"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.85066"}}