{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-08T17:43:47Z","author":["Reichert, Sophie","Criscuolo, François","Massemin, Sylvie","Rojas, Emilio R.","Robin, J.","Zahn, Sandrine"],"title":"Data from: Maternal telomere length inheritance in the king penguin","host":"Reichert S, Rojas ER, Zahn S, Robin J, Criscuolo F, Massemin S (2014) Maternal telomere length inheritance in the king penguin. Heredity, online in advance of print.","keywords":["telomeres","king penguin","birds","inheritance"],"description":"Telomeres are emerging as a biomarker for ageing and survival, and are likely important in shaping life-history trade-offs. In particular, telomere length with which one starts in life has been linked to lifelong survival, suggesting that early telomere dynamics are somehow related to life-history trajectories. This result highlights the importance of determining the extent to which telomere length is inherited, as a crucial factor determining early life telomere length. Given the scarcity of species for which telomere length inheritance has been studied, it is pressing to assess the generality of telomere length inheritance patterns. Further, information on how this pattern changes over the course of growth in individuals living under natural conditions should provide some insight on the extent to which environmental constraints also shape telomere dynamics. To fill this gap partly, we followed telomere inheritance in a population of king penguins (Aptenodytes patagonicus). We tested for paternal and maternal influence on chick initial telomere length (10 days old after hatching), and how these relationships changed with chick age (at 70, 200 and 300 days old). Based on a correlative approach, offspring telomere length was positively associated with maternal telomere length early in life (at 10 days old). However, this relationship was not significant at older ages. These data suggest that telomere length in birds is maternally inherited. Nonetheless, the influence of environmental conditions during growth remained an important factor shaping telomere length, as the maternal link disappeared with chicks’ age.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.4407g/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64978","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64978","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25052413","doi:10.1038/hdy.2014.60"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.4407g"}}