{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-22T18:47:48Z","author":["Shedrawi, George","Field, Stuart N.","Willis, Bette L","Bourne, David G.","Schaffelke, Britta","Lamb, Joleah B.","Pollock, F. Joseph","Heron, Scott F."],"title":"Data from: Sediment and turbidity associated with offshore dredging increase coral disease prevalence on nearby reefs","host":"Pollock FJ, Lamb JB, Field SN, Heron SF, Schaffelke B, Shedrawi G, Bourne DG, Willis BL (2014) Sediment and turbidity associated with offshore dredging increase coral disease prevalence on nearby reefs. PLoS ONE 9(7): e102498.","keywords":["coastal development","dredging","coral disease","sedimentation","turbidity","Coral health","reef monitoring","climate change"],"description":"In recent decades, coral reef ecosystems have declined to the extent that reefs are now threatened globally. While many water quality parameters have been proposed to contribute to reef declines, little evidence exists conclusively linking specific water quality parameters with increased disease prevalence in situ. Here we report evidence from in situ coral health surveys confirming that chronic exposure to dredging-associated sediment plumes significantly increase the prevalence of white syndromes, a devastating group of globally important coral diseases. Coral health surveys were conducted along a dredging-associated sediment plume gradient to assess the relationship between sedimentation, turbidity and coral health. Reefs exposed to the highest number of days under the sediment plume (296 to 347 days) had two-fold higher levels of disease, largely driven by a 2.5-fold increase in white syndromes, and a six-fold increase in other signs of compromised coral health relative to reefs with little or no plume exposure (0 to 9 days). Multivariate modeling and ordination incorporating sediment exposure level, coral community composition and cover, predation and multiple thermal stress indices provided further confirmation that sediment plume exposure level was the main driver of elevated disease and other compromised coral health indicators. This study provides the first evidence linking dredging-associated sedimentation and turbidity with elevated coral disease prevalence in situ. Our results may help to explain observed increases in global coral disease prevalence in recent decades and suggest that minimizing sedimentation and turbidity associated with coastal development will provide an important management tool for controlling coral disease epizootics.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.19np6/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66149","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66149","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0102498","PMID:25029525"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.19np6"}}