{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-02T20:21:21Z","author":["Schnittler, Martin","Pannell, John R.","Korbecka, Grażyna","Pfeiffer, Tanja","Roschanski, Anna M."],"title":"Data from: Characterization of microsatellite loci and reliable genotyping in a polyploid plant, Mercurialis perennis (Euphorbiaceae)","host":"Pfeiffer T, Roschanski AM, Pannell JR, Korbecka G, Schnittler M (2011) Characterization of microsatellite loci and reliable genotyping in a polyploid plant, Mercurialis perennis (Euphorbiaceae). Journal of Heredity 102(4): 479-488.","keywords":["loci characterization","SSR markers","polyploidy","genotyping errors","microsatellites"],"description":"For many applications in population genetics, codominant simple sequence repeats (SSRs)\nmay have substantial advantages over dominant anonymous markers such as AFLPs. In high\npolyploids, however, allele dosage of SSRs cannot easily be determined and alleles are not\neasily attributable to potentially diploidized loci. Here, we argue that SSRs may nonetheless be\nbetter than AFLPs for polyploid taxa if they are analyzed as effectively dominant markers,\nbecause they are more reliable and more precise. We describe the transfer of SSRs developed\nfor diploid Mercurialis huetii to the clonal dioecious M. perennis. Primers were tested on a set of\n54 male and female plants from natural decaploid populations. Eight of 65 tested loci produced\npolymorphic fragments. Binary profiles from four different scoring routines were used to define multilocus lineages (MLLs). Allowing for fragment differences within one MLL, all analyses\nrevealed the same 14 MLLs, without conflicting with merigenet, sex or plot assignment. For semiautomatic scoring, a combination of as few as two of the four most polymorphic loci resulted in unambiguous discrimination of clones. Our study demonstrates that microsatellite fingerprinting of polyploid plants is a cost-efficient and reliable alternative to AFLPs, not least\nbecause fewer loci are required than for diploids.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8887/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8887","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8887","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/jhered/esr024","PMID:21576288"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8887"}}