{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-26T18:43:44Z","author":["Deng, DeXiang","Zhang, MingZhi","Tang, ZaiXiang","Zhang, YongHong","Xu, ChenWu","Wang, XueFeng"],"title":"Data from: The maternal cytoplasmic environment may be involved in the viability selection of gametes and zygotes","host":"Tang Z, Wang X, Zhang M, Zhang Y, Deng D, Xu C (2012) The maternal cytoplasmic environment may be involved in the viability selection of gametes and zygotes. Heredity 110(4): 331–337.","description":"Segregation distortion is the phenomenon whereby the observed genotypic frequencies of a locus fall outside the expected Mendelian segregation ratio, and it is increasingly recognised as a potentially powerful evolutionary force. The main reason for segregation distortion is a difference in the viability of gametes and zygotes caused by viability loci in the segregating progeny. However, the maternal cytoplasm may also be involved in the viability selection of gametes and zygotes. The objectives of this study were to map the segregation distortion loci (SDL) in maize and to test the hypothesis that the viability of gametes and zygotes may also be associated with the maternal cytoplasmic environment. In the present study, a reciprocal mating design was conducted to generate an F2-segregating population. A linkage map was constructed with 126 microsatellite markers. A whole-genome scan was performed to detect the SDL in segregating populations with different maternal cytoplasm environments. Altogether, 14 SDL with strong LOD (logarithm (base 10) of odds) supports were identified in the specifically designed F2 populations. Interestingly, we found dramatic changes in the genotypic frequencies of the SDL in the two maternal cytoplasmic backgrounds, which indicated a change in the viability of gametes and zygotes in different cytoplasmic environments. Furthermore, in the JB cytoplasmic background, most of the detected SDL and complete distortion markers exhibited similar bias patterns favouring the Y53 alleles. These results suggested that selfish cytoplasmic elements may have an important role in shaping the patterns of segregation distortion in F2 populations through selective viability of gametes and zygotes.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s1674/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42920","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42920","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23169560","doi:10.1038/hdy.2012.89"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s1674"}}