{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-06-12T17:17:06Z","author":["Bartlett, Justin S.","Lambkin, Christine L."],"title":"Data from: Bush Blitz aids description of three new species and a new genus of Australian beeflies (Diptera, Bombyliidae, Exoprosopini)","host":"Lambkin CL, Bartlett JS (2011) Bush Blitz aids description of three new species and a new genus of Australian beeflies (Diptera, Bombyliidae, Exoprosopini). ZooKeys 150: 231-280.","keywords":["Scratchpads","Morphbank","cybertaxonomy","taxonomic revision","phylogenetic analysis"],"description":"Bush Blitz is a three-year multimillion dollar program to document the plants and animals in hundreds of properties across Australia’s National Reserve System. The core focus is on nature discovery – identifying and describing new species of plants and animals. The Bush Blitz program has enabled the collection and description of beeflies (Diptera, Bombyliidae) from surveys in Western Australia and Queensland. Three new species of Australian beeflies belonging to the Exoprosopini are described; Palirika mackenziei Lambkin, sp. n., Palirika culgoafloodplainensis Lambkin, sp. n., and Larrpana bushblitz Lambkin, sp. n. Phylogenetic analysis of 40 Australian exoprosopine species belonging to the Balaana generic-group Lambkin & Yeates, 2003 supports the placement of the three new species into existing genera, and the erection and description of the new genus Ngalki Lambkin, gen. n. for Ngalki trigonium (Lambkin & Yeates, 2003), comb. n. Revised keys are provided for the genera of the Australian Balaana genus-group and the species of Palirika Lambkin & Yeates, 2003 and Larrpana Lambkin & Yeates, 2003. With the description of the three new species and the transferral of Munjua trigona Lambkin & Yeates, 2003 into the new genus Ngalki Lambkin, gen. n., three genera are rediagnosed; Munjua Lambkin & Yeates, 2003, Palirika and Larrpana.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.5j64k/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.5j64k/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.5j64k/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.5j64k/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34861","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34861","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22207816","doi:10.3897/zookeys.150.1881"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5j64k"}}