{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-04-30T19:18:53Z","author":["Fleming, Ian A.","Ward, Eric J.","Westley, Peter A. H."],"title":"Data from: Fine-scale local adaptation in an invasive freshwater fish has evolved in contemporary time","host":"Westley PAH, Ward EJ, Fleming IA (2012) Fine-scale local adaptation in an invasive freshwater fish has evolved in contemporary time. Proceedings of the Royal Society B 280(1751): 20122327.","keywords":["contemporary evolution","Local adaptation","invasive species","reciprocal transplant","immigrant inviability"],"description":"Adaptive evolutionary change in only a few generations can increase the ability of non-native invasive species to spread, and yet adaptive divergence is rarely assessed in recently established populations. In this paper, we experimentally test for evidence of fine-scale local adaptation in juvenile survival and growth among three populations of an invasive freshwater fish with reciprocal transplants and common-garden experiments. Despite intrinsic differences in habitat quality, in two out of three populations we detected evidence of increased survival in ‘home’ vs. ‘away’ environments with a Bayesian occupancy model fitted to mark-recapture data. We found support for the ‘local vs. foreign’ criterion of local adaptation as 14 out of 15 pairwise comparisons of performance were consistent with local adaptation (p < 0.001). Patterns in growth were less clear, though we detected evidence of location and population-level effects. Although the agents of divergent ecological selection are not known in this system, our results combine to indicate that adaptive divergence – reflected by higher relative survival of local individuals – can occur in a small number of generations and only a few kilometers apart on the landscape.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pc14j/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44015","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44015","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23193126","doi:10.1098/rspb.2012.2327"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pc14j"}}