{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-03T18:29:28Z","author":["Andersson, Gerhard","Carlbring, Per","Hassmén, Peter","Umefjord, Göran","Ström, Morgan","Uckelstam, Carl-Johan"],"title":"Data from: Internet-delivered therapist-guided physical activity for mild to moderate depression: a randomized controlled trial","host":"Ström M, Uckelstam C, Andersson G, Hassmén P, Umefjord G, Carlbring P (2013) Internet-delivered therapist-guided physical activity for mild to moderate depression: a randomized controlled trial. PeerJ 1: e178.","keywords":["treatment","Physical activity","psychotherapy","RCT","internet","depression"],"description":"Objective: The main hypothesis, and the objective of the study, was to test if the participants allocated to the treatment group would show a larger reduction in depressive symptoms than those in the control group. Methods: This study was a randomized nine week trial of an Internet-administered treatment based on guided physical exercise for Major Depressive Disorder (MDD). A total of 48 participants with mild to moderate depression, diagnosed using the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis I Disorders , were randomized either to a treatment intervention or to a waiting-list control group. The main outcome measure for depression was the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II), and physical activity level was measured using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ). The treatment program consisted of nine text modules, and included therapist guidance on a weekly basis. Results: The results showed significant reductions of depressive symptoms in the treatment group compared to the control group, with a moderate between-group effect size (Cohen’s d = 0.67; 95 % confidence interval: 0.09-1.25). No difference was found between the groups with regards to increase of physical activity level. For the treatment group, the reduction in depressive symptoms persisted at six months follow-up. Conclusions: Physical activity as a treatment for depression can be delivered in the form of guided Internet-based self-help. Trial Registration: The trial was registered at ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT01573130).","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.c6q65/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.c6q65/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54431","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54431","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24109561","doi:10.7717/peerj.178"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.c6q65"}}