{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-05T19:08:42Z","author":["Malone, John H.","Ribado, Jessica","Moriarty Lemmon, Emily Claire"],"title":"Data from: Sensory drive does not explain reproductive character displacement of male acoustic signals in the Upland Chorus Frog (Pseudacris feriarum)","host":"Malone JH, Ribado J, Moriarty Lemmon EC (2014) Sensory drive does not explain reproductive character displacement of male acoustic signals in the Upland Chorus Frog (Pseudacris feriarum). Evolution 68(5): 1306–1319.","keywords":["Speciation","Behavior","Adaptation","Reproductive Isolation","Selection - Sexual","Signaling/Courtship"],"description":"Biotic and abiotic factors have been proposed to explain patterns of reproductive character displacement, but which factor is most important to character displacement of acoustic signals is not clear. Male vocalizations of the frog Pseudacris feriarum are known to undergo reproductive character displacement in areas of sympatry with P. brimleyi and P. nigrita. Despite evidence for reinforcement as an important mechanism, local adaptation via sensory drive might explain this pattern because Pseudacris breed in different habitat types and mating signals are exposed to a variety of environments. We tested the sensory drive hypothesis by playing synthesized vocalizations representing the spectrum of variation in P. feriarum at 12 different study sites. If sensory drive has occurred, then vocalizations should transmit better in the site of origin or at ecologically similar sites. We found that variation in acoustic signals did not produce better transmission in particular sites, the effect of site was uniform, and acoustic signals often transmitted better in habitats external to their origin. Ecological variation among habitats did not explain signal degradation. Our playback experiments, ecological analyses, and comparisons of different habitat types provide no support for sensory drive as a process promoting reproductive character displacement in this system. Reinforcement is the more likely primary mechanism.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.67md0/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.58721","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.58721","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/evo.12366","PMID:24475782"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.67md0"}}