{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-05-02T17:54:35Z","author":["Xin, Mingming","Wang, Xiangfeng","Ma, Chuang","Feldmann, Kenneth A."],"title":"Data from: Machine learning-based differential network analysis: a study of stress-responsive transcriptomes in Arabidopsis thaliana","host":"Ma C, Xin M, Feldmann KA, Wang X (2014) Machine learning-based differential network analysis: a study of stress-responsive transcriptomes in Arabidopsis thaliana. The Plant Cell 26(2): 520-537.","keywords":["abiotic/environmental stress","systems biology","gene coexpression network","machine learning","transcriptome analysis","differential network","bioinformatics","random forest"],"description":"Machine learning (ML) is an intelligent data mining technique that builds a prediction model based on the learning of prior knowledge to recognize patterns in large-scale data sets. We present an ML-based methodology for transcriptome analysis via comparison of gene coexpression networks, implemented as an R package called machine learning–based differential network analysis (mlDNA) and apply this method to reanalyze a set of abiotic stress expression data in Arabidopsis thaliana. The mlDNA first used a ML-based filtering process to remove nonexpressed, constitutively expressed, or non-stress-responsive “noninformative” genes prior to network construction, through learning the patterns of 32 expression characteristics of known stress-related genes. The retained “informative” genes were subsequently analyzed by ML-based network comparison to predict candidate stress-related genes showing expression and network differences between control and stress networks, based on 33 network topological characteristics. Comparative evaluation of the network-centric and gene-centric analytic methods showed that mlDNA substantially outperformed traditional statistical testing–based differential expression analysis at identifying stress-related genes, with markedly improved prediction accuracy. To experimentally validate the mlDNA predictions, we selected 89 candidates out of the 1784 predicted salt stress–related genes with available SALK T-DNA mutagenesis lines for phenotypic screening and identified two previously unreported genes, mutants of which showed salt-sensitive phenotypes.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.58279","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.58279","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24520154","doi:10.1105/tpc.113.121913"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.41b9g"}}