{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-07-18T18:28:29Z","author":["Touzet, Pascal","Van Rossum, Fabienne","Le Cadre, Solenn","Lahiani, Emna","Dufay, Mathilde","Castric, Vincent","Charlesworth, Deborah"],"title":"Data from: Disentangling the effects of mating systems and mutation rates on cytoplamic diversity in gynodioecious Silene nutans and dioecious Silene otites","host":"Lahiani E, Dufay M, Castric V, Le Cadre S, Charlesworth D, Van Rossum F, Touzet P (2013) Disentangling the effects of mating systems and mutation rates on cytoplamic diversity in gynodioecious Silene nutans and dioecious Silene otites. Heredity 111(2): 157-164.","keywords":"mating system evolution","description":"Many flowering plant species exhibit a variety of distinct sexual morphs, the two most common cases being the co- occurrence of females and males (dioecy) or the co-occurrence of hermaphrodites and females (gynodioecy). In this study we compared DNA sequence variability of the three genomes (nuclear, mitochondrial and chloroplastic) of a gynodioecious species, Silene nutans, with that of a closely related dioecious species, Silene otites. In the light of theoretical models, we expect cytoplasmic diversity to differ between the two species due to the selective dynamics that acts on cytoplasmic genomes in gynodioecious species: under an epidemic scenario, the gynodioecious species is expected to exhibit lower cytoplasmic diversity than the dioecious species, while the opposite is expected in the case of balancing selection maintaining sterility cytoplasms in the gynodioecious species. We found no difference between the species for nuclear gene diversity, but, for the cytoplasmic loci, the gynodioecious S. nutans had more haplotypes, and higher nucleotide diversity, than the dioecious relative, S. otites, even though the latter has a relatively high rate of mitochondrial synonymous substitutions, and therefore presumably a higher mutation rate. Therefore, since the mitochondrial mutation rate cannot account for the higher cytoplasmic diversity found in S. nutans, our findings support the hypothesis that gynodioecy in S. nutans has been maintained by balancing selection rather than by epidemic-like dynamics.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s/10"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47314","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47314","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23591518","doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.32"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.gd93s"}}