{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-08-25T17:29:25Z","author":["Maes, Gregory E","Rijnsdorp, Adriaan D","Cuveliers, Els L","Volckaert, Filip A M","Larmuseau, Maarten H D"],"title":"Data from: Temporal genetic stability and high effective population size despite fisheries-induced life-history trait evolution in the North Sea sole.","host":"Cuveliers EL, Volckaert FAM, Rijnsdorp AD, Larmuseau MHD, Maes GE (2011) Temporal genetic stability and high effective population size despite fisheries-induced life-history trait evolution in the North Sea sole. Molecular Ecology 20(17): 3555-3568.","keywords":["fishery","genetic diversity","historical DNA","effective population size","microsatellites"],"description":"Heavy fishing and other anthropogenic influences can have profound impact on a species’ resilience to harvesting. Besides the decrease of the census and effective population size, strong declines in mature adults and recruiting individuals may lead to almost irreversible genetic changes in life-history traits. Here, we investigated the evolution of genetic diversity and effective population size in the heavily exploited sole (Solea solea), through the analysis of historical DNA from a collection of 1379 sole (Solea solea) otoliths dating back from 1957. Despite documented shifts in life-history traits, neutral genetic diversity inferred from 11 microsatellite markers showed a remarkable stability over a period of 50 years of heavy fishing. Using simulations and corrections for fisheries induced demographic variation, both point and temporal estimates of effective population size (Ne) were always higher than 1000, suggesting that despite the severe census size decrease over a 50 year period of harvesting, genetic drift is probably not strong enough to significantly decrease the neutral diversity of this species in the North Sea. However the ratio of effective population size to the census size (Ne/Nc) was very small (10-5), suggesting that overall only few adults contribute to the next generation. The high Ne level together with the low Ne/Nc ratio is most likely caused by a combination of an equalized reproductive output of younger cohorts, a decrease in generation time and a large variance in reproductive success typical for marine species. Because strong evolutionary changes in age and size at first maturation have been observed for sole, changes in adaptive genetic variation should be further monitored to detect the evolutionary consequences of human-induced selection.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.5dg56/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.5dg56/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.33772","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.33772","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05196.x","PMID:21790820"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.5dg56"}}