{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-10-03T18:23:12Z","author":["Hedin, Marshal","Derkarabetian, Shahan"],"title":"Data from: Integrative taxonomy and species delimitation in harvestmen: a revision of the western North American genus Sclerobunus (Opiliones: Laniatores: Travunioidea)","host":"Derkarabetian S, Hedin M (2014) Integrative taxonomy and species delimitation in harvestmen: a revision of the western North American genus Sclerobunus (Opiliones: Laniatores: Travunioidea). PLoS ONE 9(8): e104982.","keywords":["integrative taxonomy","species trees","molecular phylogenetics","morphometrics","alpha taxonomy","species delimitation"],"description":"Alpha taxonomy, and specifically the delimitation of species, is becoming increasingly objective and integrative. The use of coalescent-based methods applied to genetic data is providing new tools for the discovery and delimitation of species. Here, we use an integrative approach via a combination of discovery-based multivariate morphological analyses to detect potential new species. These potential species are then used as a priori species in hypothesis-driven validation analyses with genetic data. This research focuses on the harvestmen genus Sclerobunus found throughout the mountainous regions of western North America. Based on our analyses, we conduct a revision of Sclerobunus resulting in synonymy of Cyptobunus with Sclerobunus including transfer of S. cavicolens comb. nov. and elevation of both subspecies of S. ungulatus: S. ungulatus comb. nov. and S. madhousensis comb. nov., stat. nov. The three subspecies of S. robustus are elevated, S. robustus, S. glorietus stat. nov., and S. idahoensis stat. nov. Additionally, five new species of Sclerobunus are described from New Mexico and Colorado, including S. jemez sp. nov., S. klomax sp. nov., S. skywalkeri sp. nov., S. speoventus sp. nov., and S. steinmanni sp. nov. Several of the newly described species are single-cave endemics, and our findings suggest that further exploration of western North American cave habitats will likely yield additional new species.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.hj6r1/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.hj6r1/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.hj6r1/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67211","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67211","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25144370","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0104982"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.hj6r1"}}