{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"8;6;2013","keywords":["recruitment","marine benthic invertebrates","deep sea","gorgonian coral"],"host":"Lacharité M, Metaxas A (2013) Early life history of deep-water gorgonian corals may limit their abundance. PLoS ONE 8(6): e65394.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.30kt0/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.57853","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2013-12-17T19:17:59Z","author":["Metaxas, Anna","Lacharité, Myriam"],"title":"Data from: Early life history of deep-water gorgonian corals may limit their abundance","description":"Deep-water gorgonian corals are long-lived organisms found worldwide off continental margins and seamounts, usually occurring at depths of ~200–1,000 m. Most corals undergo sexual reproduction by releasing a planktonic larval stage that disperses; however, recruitment rates and the environmental and biological factors influencing recruitment in deep-sea species are poorly known. Here, we present results from a 4-year field experiment conducted in the Gulf of Maine (northwest Atlantic) at depths of more than 650 m that document recruitment for 2 species of deep-water gorgonian corals, Primnoa resedaeformis and Paragorgia arborea. The abundance of P. resedaeformis recruits was high, and influenced by the structural complexity of the recipient habitat, but very few recruits of P. arborea were found. We suggest that divergent reproductive modes (P. resedaeformis as a broadcast spawner and P. arborea as a brooder) may explain this pattern. Despite the high recruitment of P. resedaeformis, severe mortality early on in the benthic stage of this species may limit the abundance of adult colonies. Most recruits of this species (more than 80%) were at the primary polyp stage, and less than 1% of recruits were at stage of 4 polyps or more. We propose that biological disturbance, possibly by the presence of suspension-feeding brittle stars, and limited food supply in the deep sea may cause this mortality. Our findings reinforce the vulnerability of these corals to anthropogenic disturbances, such as trawling with mobile gear, and the importance of incorporating knowledge on processes during the early life history stages in conservation decisions.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.57853","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0065394","PMID:23762358"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.30kt0"}}