{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":["Journal of Heredity","0022-1503"],"keywords":["population genetics","phylogeography","jacks"],"host":"Santos SR, Xiang Y, Tagawa AW (2010) Population structure and comparative phylogeography of jack species (Caranx ignobilis and C. melampygus) in the high Hawaiian Islands. Journal of Heredity 102(1): 47-54.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1868/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.1868","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T19:18:15Z","author":["Tagawa, Annette W","Xiang, Yu","Santos, Scott R"],"title":"Data from: Population structure and comparative phylogeography of jack species (Caranx ignobilis and C. melampygus) in the high Hawaiian Islands","description":"Members of the family Carangidae are top-level predators and highly prized food and sport fishes. Although ecologically and economically important, little is known about the biology of numerous species in the family. This is particularly true of the jacks Caranx ignobilis and C. melampygus, which have experienced recent population reductions around the high Hawaiian Islands due to overfishing. Previous studies have documented territorial tendencies as well as cases of long-distance excursions in both species, suggesting populations may exhibit a range of structure at the genetic level. To explore this possibility, mitochondrial (mtDNA) ATPase6 and ATPase8 gene sequence variation was assessed from 91 individuals (33 C. ignobilis and 58 C. melampygus) spanning the islands of Kauai, Oahu, Molokai, Maui and Hawai‘i. While a total of 20 distinct haplotypes (eight for C. ignobilis; 12 for C. melampygus) were recovered, no evidence of population structure was found for either species across the examined geographic range. However, distinct demographic patterns were identified, implying differing evolutionary histories and/or population dynamics. Additionally, ~6% of the examined C. ignobilis were C. ignobilis x C. melampygus hybrids since they harbored mitochondrial haplotypes typical of C. melampygus. These hybrids contribute to measurable gene flow between the species and may play a significant role in the evolution of the genus.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.1868","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/jhered/esq101","PMID:20881031"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1868"}}