{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-10T19:28:23Z","author":["Crawford, Andrew J.","Flechas, Sandra V.","Medina, Edgar M.","Restrepo, Silvia","Amezquita, Adolfo","Cardenas, Martha E.","Sarmiento, Carolina"],"title":"Data from: Characterization of the first Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis isolate from the Colombian Andes, an amphibian biodiversity hotspot","host":"Flechas SV, Medina EM, Crawford AJ, Sarmiento C, Cardenas ME, Amezquita A, Restrepo S (2013) Characterization of the first Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis isolate from the Colombian Andes, an amphibian biodiversity hotspot. EcoHealth 10: 72-76.","keywords":["pathogen","epizootic","chytridiomycosis","chytrid fungus","multi-locus genotyping"],"description":"The pathogenic chytrid fungus, Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis (Bd), constitutes a significant threat to more than 790 amphibian species occurring in Colombia. To date there is no molecular or morphological description of strains infecting Colombian populations. Here we report the genetic and morphological characterization of the first Colombian isolate of Bd (strain EV001). Our goals were threefold: (1) to characterize the morphology of EV001 using light and scanning electron microscopy, (2) to genotype this strain by direct sequencing of 17 polymorphic nuclear markers developed previously, and (3) to compare our findings with published reports on strains from other areas of the globe. We found that EV001 is morphologically consistent with previously described strains. Multi-locus genotyping suggested that EV001 is grouped genetically with Panamanian strains and is most similar to JEL203 isolated from a captive individual. This finding fills an important gap in our knowledge of Neotropical strains of Bd and provides a baseline for further evolutionary and functional analyses.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1b68v/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.43289","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.43289","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23529763","doi:10.1007/s10393-013-0823-9"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1b68v"}}