{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-08-23T19:31:47Z","author":["Rodríguez-Ramilo, Silvia T.","Wang, Jinliang"],"title":"Data from: The effect of close relatives on unsupervised Bayesian clustering algorithms in population genetic structure analysis","host":"Rodríguez-Ramilo ST, Wang J (2012) The effect of close relatives on unsupervised Bayesian clustering algorithms in population genetic structure analysis. Molecular Ecology Resources 12(5): 873-884.","keywords":["molecular markers","close relatives","family structure","STRUCTURE software","subpopulation"],"description":"The inference of population genetic structures is essential in many research areas in population genetics, conservation biology and evolutionary biology. Recently, unsupervised Bayesian clustering algorithms have been developed to detect a hidden population structure from genotypic data, assuming among others that individuals taken from the population are unrelated. Because of this hypothesis, markers in a sample taken from a subpopulation can be considered to be in Hardy-Weinberg and linkage equilibrium. However, close relatives might be sampled from the same subpopulation, and consequently, might cause Hardy-Weinberg and linkage disequilibrium and thus bias a population genetic structure analysis. In this study, we used simulated and real data to investigate the impact of close relatives in a sample on Bayesian population structure analysis. We also showed that, when close relatives were identified by a pedigree reconstruction approach and removed, the accuracy of a population genetic structure analysis can be greatly improved. The results indicate that unsupervised Bayesian clustering algorithms cannot be used blindly to detect genetic structure in a sample with closely related individuals. Rather, when closely related individuals are suspected to be frequent in a sample, these individuals should be first identified and removed before conducting a population structure analysis.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.668tn571/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38570","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38570","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22639868","doi:10.1111/j.1755-0998.2012.03156.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.668tn571"}}