{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-24T16:56:54Z","author":["Alvarez, Nadir","Zamudio, Sergio","Arrigo, Nils","Jorgensen, Tove H.","Emerson, Brent C.","Mastretta-Yanes, Alicia","Piñero, Daniel"],"title":"Data from: Gene duplication, population genomics and species-level differentiation within a tropical mountain shrub","host":"Mastretta-Yanes A, Zamudio S, Jorgensen TH, Arrigo N, Alvarez N, Piñero D, Emerson BC (2014) Gene duplication, population genomics and species-level differentiation within a tropical mountain shrub. Genome Biology and Evolution, online in advance of print.","keywords":["GBS","RAD-seq","paralogy","de novo assembly","gene duplication"],"description":"Gene duplication leads to paralogy, which complicates the de novo assembly of genotyping-by-sequencing (GBS) data. The issue of paralogous genes is exacerbated in plants, because they are particularly prone to gene duplication events. Paralogs are normally filtered from GBS data before undertaking population genomics or phylogenetic analyses. However, gene duplication plays an important role in the functional diversification of genes and it can also lead to the formation of postzygotic barriers. Using populations and closely related species of a tropical mountain shrub, we examine: (1) the genomic differentiation produced by putative orthologs, and (2) the distribution of recent gene duplication among lineages and geography. We find high differentiation among populations from isolated mountain peaks and species-level differentiation within what is morphologically described as a single species. The inferred distribution of paralogs among populations is congruent with taxonomy and shows that GBS could be used to examine recent gene duplication as a source of genomic differentiation of non-model species.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.n3jk5/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.n3jk5/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.n3jk5/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70750","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70750","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/gbe/evu205","PMID:25223767"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n3jk5"}}