{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-02-17T17:31:35Z","author":["Galián, José A.","Rosato, Marcela","Rosselló, Josep A."],"title":"Data from: Partial sequence homogenization in the 5S multigene families may generate sequence chimeras and spurious results in phylogenetic reconstructions","host":"Galián JA, Rosato M, Rosselló JA (2013) Partial sequence homogenization in the 5S multigene families may generate sequence chimeras and spurious results in phylogenetic reconstructions. Systematic Biology 63(2): 219-230.","keywords":["phylogeny","concerted evolution","multigene families","5S rDNA","Medicago"],"description":"Multigene families have provided opportunities for evolutionary biologists to assess molecular evolution processes and phylogenetic reconstructions at deep and shallow systematic levels. However, the use of these markers is not free of technical and analytical challenges. Many evolutionary studies that used the nuclear 5S rDNA gene family rarely used contiguous 5S coding sequences due to the routine use of head-to-tail PCR primers that are anchored to the coding region. Moreover, the 5S coding sequences have been concatenated with independent, adjacent gene units in many studies, creating simulated chimeric genes as the raw data for evolutionary analysis. This practice is based on the tacitly assumed, but rarely tested, hypothesis that strict intra-locus concerted evolution processes are operating in 5S rDNA genes, without any empirical evidence as to whether it holds for the recovered data. The potential pitfalls of analysing the patterns of molecular evolution and reconstructing phylogenies based on these chimeric genes have not been assessed to date. Here, we compared the sequence integrity and phylogenetic behaviour of entire versus concatenated 5S coding regions from a real data set obtained from closely related plant species (Medicago, Fabaceae). Our results suggest that within arrays sequence homogenization is partially operating in the 5S coding region, which is traditionally assumed to be highly conserved. Consequently, concatenating 5S genes increases haplotype diversity, generating novel chimeric genotypes that most likely do not exist within the genome. In addition, the patterns of gene evolution are distorted, leading to incorrect haplotype relationships in some evolutionary reconstructions.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.3074s/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.3074s/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.56847","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.56847","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/sysbio/syt101","PMID:24335430"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3074s"}}