{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-09-20T19:42:39Z","author":["Best, Megan","Klitgaard, Anne Birgitte","Rapp, Hans Tore","Tendal, Ole Secher","Thollesson, Mikael","Cárdenas, Paco"],"title":"Data from: Taxonomy, biogeography and DNA barcodes of Geodia species (Porifera, Demospongiae, Tetractinellida) in the Atlantic boreo-arctic region","host":"Cárdenas P, Rapp HT, Klitgaard AB, Best M, Thollesson M, Tendal OS (2013) Taxonomy, biogeography and DNA barcodes of Geodia species (Porifera, Demospongiae, Tetractinellida) in the Atlantic boreo-arctic region. Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society 169(2): 251–311.","keywords":["sponge grounds","amphi-Atlantic","biogeography","deep-sea"],"description":"Geodia species north of 60°N in the Atlantic appeared in the literature for the first time when Bowerbank described Geodia barretti and G. macandrewii in 1858 from western Norway. Since then, a number of species have been based on material from various parts of the region: G. simplex, Isops phlegraei, I. pallida, I. sphaeroides, Synops pyriformis, G. parva, G. normani, G. atlantica, Sidonops mesotriaena (now called G. hentscheli), and G. simplicissima. In addition to these 12 nominal species, four species described from elsewhere are claimed to have been identified in material from the northeast Atlantic, namely G. nodastrella and G. cydonium (and its synonyms Cydonium muelleri and Geodia gigas). In this paper, we revise the boreo-arctic Geodia species using morphological, molecular, and biogeographical data. We notably compare northwest and northeast Atlantic specimens. Biological data (reproduction, biochemistry, microbiology, epibionts) for each species are also reviewed. Our results show that there are six valid species of boreo-arctic Atlantic Geodia while other names are synonyms or mis-identifications. Geodia barretti, G. atlantica, G. macandrewii, and G. hentscheli are well established and widely distributed. The same goes for Geodia phlegraei, but this species shows a striking geographical and bathymetric variation, which led us to recognize two species, G. phlegraei and G. parva (here resurrected). Some Geodia are arctic species (G. hentscheli, G. parva), while others are typically boreal (G. atlantica, G. barretti, G. phlegraei, G. macandrewii). No morphological differences were found between specimens from the northeast and northwest Atlantic, except for G. parva. The Folmer cytochrome oxidase subunit I (COI) fragment is unique for every species and invariable over their whole distribution range, except for G. barretti which had two haplotypes. 18S is unique for four species but cannot discriminate G. phlegraei and G. parva. Two keys to the boreo-arctic Geodia are included, one based on external morphology, the other based on spicule morphology.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.td8sb/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.td8sb/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49386","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49386","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/zoj.12056","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.td8sb"}}