{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-05T19:18:49Z","author":["Han, Sang-Hoon","Jin, Mei-Lei","Nunome, Mitsuo","Aplin, K. P.","Maryanto, Ibnu","Yonekawa, Hiromichi","Vogel, Peter","Ikeda, Hidetoshi","Tsuchiya, Kimiyuki","Kryukov, Alexey P.","Moriwaki, Kazuo","Kinotshita, Ghota","Shiroishi, T.","Suzuki, Hitoshi"],"title":"Data from: Evolutionary and dispersal history of Eurasian wild mice Mus musculus clarified by more extensive geographic sampling of mitochondrial DNA","host":"Suzuki H, Nunome M, Kinotshita G, Aplin KP, Vogel P, Kryukov AP, Jin M, Han S, Maryanto I, Tsuchiya K, Ikeda H, Shiroishi T, Yonekawa H, Moriwaki K (2013) Evolutionary and dispersal history of Eurasian wild mice Mus musculus clarified by more extensive geographic sampling of mitochondrial DNA. Heredity 111(5): 375–390.","keywords":["phylogeography","control region","house mouse","cytochrome b","mitochondrial DNA"],"description":"We examined sequence variation of mitochondrial DNA control region and cytochrome b gene of the house mouse (Mus musculus sensu lato) drawn from ca. 200 localities, with 290 new samples drawn primarily from previously unsampled portions of their Eurasian distribution and with the objective of further clarifying evolutionary episodes of this species before and after the onset of human-mediated long-distance dispersals. Phylogenetic analysis of the expanded data detected five equally distinct clades, with geographic ranges of northern Eurasia (musculus, MUS), India and Southeast Asia (castaneus, CAS), Nepal (unspecified), western Europe (domesticus, DOM), and Yemen (gentilulus). Our results confirm previous suggestions of Southwestern Asia as the likely place of origin of M. musculus and the region of Iran, Afghanistan, Pakistan, and northern India, specifically as the ancestral homeland of CAS. The divergence of the subspecies lineages and of internal sublineage differentiation within CAS were estimated to be 0.37-0.47 and 0.14-0.23 million years ago (mya), respectively, assuming a split of M. musculus and Mus spretus at 1.7 mya. Of four CAS sublineages detected, only one extends to eastern parts of India, Southeast Asia, Indonesia, Philippines, South China, Northeast China, Primorye, Sakhalin and Japan, implying a dramatic range expansion of CAS out of its homeland during an evolutionary short time, perhaps associated with the spread of agricultural practices. Multiple and non-coincident eastward dispersal events of MUS sublineages to distant geographic areas, such as northern China, Russia, and Korea, are inferred, with the possibility of several different routes.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/13","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49474","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49474","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1038/hdy.2013.60","PMID:23820581"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rf161"}}