{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-20T18:23:31Z","author":["Merkel, Kevin","Mundry, Roger","Boesch, Christophe","Leendertz, Fabian H.","Blasse, Anja","Goffe, Adeelia S.","Calvignac-Spencer, Sébastien"],"title":"Data from: Mother-offspring transmission and age-dependent accumulation of simian foamy virus in wild chimpanzees","host":"Blasse A, Calvignac-Spencer S, Merkel K, Goffe AS, Boesch C, Mundry R, Leendertz FH (2013) Mother-offspring transmission and age-dependent accumulation of simian foamy virus in wild chimpanzees. Journal of Virology 87(9): 5193-5204.","keywords":["chimpanzee","super-infection","vertical transmission","simian foamy virus"],"description":"Simian foamy viruses (SFVs) are thought to infect virtually any adult non-human primate (NHP). While much data have accumulated about patterns of co-divergence with their hosts and cross-species transmission events, little is known about the modalities of SFV transmission within NHP species, especially in the wild. Here we provide a detailed investigation of the dynamics of SFV circulation in a wild community of Western chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes verus). We demonstrate that mother–offspring (vertical) SFV transmission is common and hypothesize that it accounts for a number of primary infections. We also show that multiple infections with several chimpanzee specific SFV strains (i.e., super-infection) commonly happen in adult chimpanzees, which might point at adult-specific aggressive behaviors as a lifelong source of SFV infection. Our data give evidence for complex SFV dynamics in wild chimpanzees, even at a single community scale, and show that linking wild NHP social interactions and their microorganisms’ dynamics is feasible.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.bb8r6/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.46442","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.46442","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1128/JVI.02743-12","PMID:23449796"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.bb8r6"}}