{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-06-11T02:18:49Z","author":["Rifkin, Joanna L.","Nunn, Charles L.","Garamszegi, László Z."],"title":"Data from: Do animals living in larger groups experience greater parasitism? A meta-analysis","host":"Rifkin JL, Nunn CL, Garamszegi LZ (2012) Do animals living in larger groups experience greater parasitism? A meta-analysis. The American Naturalist 180(1): 70-82.","keywords":["Phylogeny","Interactions: host/parasite","Evolution: host/parasite","Ecology: behavioral","Epidemiology","Behavior: social","Interactions: host/pathogen"],"description":"Parasitism is widely viewed as the primary cost of sociality and a constraint on group size, yet studies report varied associations between group size and parasitism. Using the largest database of its kind, we performed a meta-analysis of 69 studies of the relationship between group size and parasite risk, as measured by parasitism and immune defenses. We predicted a positive correlation between group size and parasitism with organisms that show contagious and environmental transmission, and a negative correlation for searching parasites, parasitoids, and possibly vector-borne parasites (based on the encounter-dilution effect). Overall, we found a positive effect of group size (r=0.187) that varied in magnitude across transmission modes and measures of parasite risk, with only weak indications of publication bias. Among different groups of hosts, we found a stronger relationship between group size and parasite risk in birds than in mammals, which may be driven by ecological and social factors. A meta-regression showed that effect sizes increased with maximum group size. Phylogenetic meta-analyses revealed no evidence for phylogenetic signal in the strength of the group size-parasitism relationship. We conclude that group size is a weak predictor of parasite risk except in species that live in large aggregations, such as colonial birds, where effect sizes are larger.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.v5007p45/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5007p45/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5007p45/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.v5007p45/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38014","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38014","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/666081","PMID:22673652"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v5007p45"}}