{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-02-16T16:14:52Z","author":["Whitlock, Michael C.","MacLellan, Kelsie","Kwan, Lucia","Rundle, Howard D."],"title":"Data from: Dietary stress does not strengthen selection against single deleterious mutations in Drosophila melanogaster","host":"MacLellan K, Kwan L, Whitlock MC, Rundle HD (2011) Dietary stress does not strengthen selection against single deleterious mutations in Drosophila melanogaster. Heredity 108: 203–210.","keywords":["deleterious mutations","sexual selection","fitness","mutation load","stress","mating success"],"description":"Stress is generally thought to increase the strength of selection, although empirical results are mixed and general conclusions are difficult because data are limited. Here we compare the fitness effects of nine independent recessive mutations in Drosophila melanogaster in a high- and low-dietary-stress environment, estimating the strength of selection on these mutations arising from both a competitive measure of male reproductive success and productivity (female fecundity and the subsequent survival to adulthood of her offspring). The effect of stress on male reproductive success has not been addressed previously for individual loci and is of particular interest with respect to the alignment of natural and sexual selection. Our results do not support the hypothesis that stress increases the efficacy of selection arising from either fitness component. Results concerning the alignment of natural and sexual selection were mixed, although data are limited. In the low-stress environment, selection on mating success and productivity were concordant for five of nine mutations (four out of four when restricted to those with significant or near-significant productivity effects), whereas in the high-stress environment, selection aligned for seven of nine mutations (two out of two when restricted to those having significant productivity effects). General conclusions as to the effects of stress on the strength of selection and the alignment of natural and sexual selection await data from additional mutations, fitness components and stressors.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.84g54/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.84g54/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.84g54/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34055","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34055","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21792225","doi:10.1038/hdy.2011.60"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.84g54"}}