{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-08-15T16:25:06Z","author":["Polak, Michal","Grieshop, Karl"],"title":"Data from: The precopulatory function of male genital spines in Drosophila ananassae [Doleschall] (Diptera: Drosophilidae) revealed by laser surgery","host":"Grieshop K, Polak M (2012) The precopulatory function of male genital spines in Drosophila ananassae [Doleschall] (Diptera: Drosophilidae) revealed by laser surgery. Evolution 66(8): 2637-2645.","keywords":["Sexual selection","Adaptive function","Copulation success","Laser ablation","Functional morphology","Animal genitalia"],"description":"That male genital morphology evolves via postcopulatory sexual selection is a widely held view. In contrast, the pre-copulatory sexual selection hypothesis for genital evolution has received less attention. Here, we test the hypothesis that male genital spines of Drosophila ananassae promote competitive male copulation success. Using laser surgery to manipulate trait size, we demonstrate that incremental reductions of spine length progressively reduce male copulation success: males without spines failed entirely to copulate because of an inability to couple the genitalia together, whereas males with halfway ablated and blunted spines suffered reductions in copulation success of 87% and 13%, respectively. The decrease in copulation success resulting from spine length reduction was markedly stronger in sexually competitive environments than in non-competitive environments, and females expressed resistance behaviors similarly toward competing male treatments, demonstrating directly the role of genital spines in promoting competitive copulation success. Because these spines are widespread within Drosophila, as are other genital traits with pre-copulatory functions among animals, pre-copulatory sexual selection may have a more pervasive role in genital evolution than previously recognized.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g0v6h003/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38482","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38482","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01638.x","PMID:22834760"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g0v6h003"}}