{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-31T14:34:24Z","author":["Collevatti, Rosane G.","Guimarães Jr., Paulo R.","Brancalion, Pedro H.","Galetti, Mauro","Guevara, Roger","Labecca, Fábio","Pires, Mathias M.","Ribeiro, Thiago","Von Matter, Sandro","Leite, Abraão B.","Carvalho, Carolina S.","Côrtes, Marina C.","Ribeiro, Milton C.","Rodrigo, Fadini","Jordano, Pedro"],"title":"Data from: Functional extinction of birds drives rapid evolutionary changes in seed size.","host":"Galetti M, Guevara R, Côrtes MC, Rodrigo F, Von Matter S, Leite AB, Labecca F, Ribeiro T, Carvalho CS, Collevatti RG, Pires MM, Guimarães Jr PR, Brancalion PH, Ribeiro MC, Jordano P (2013) Functional extinction of birds drives rapid evolutionary changes in seed size. Science 340(6136): 1086-1090.","keywords":["defaunation","fragmentation","phenotypic selection","mutualism","seed dispersal","frugivory","evolution","rainforest"],"description":"Local extinctions have cascading effects on ecosystem functions, yet little is known about the potential for the rapid evolutionary change of species in human-modified scenarios. We show that the functional extinction of large-gape seed dispersers in the Brazilian Atlantic forest is associated with the consistent reduction of seed size of a keystone palm species. Among 22 palm populations, areas deprived of large avian frugivores for several decades present smaller seeds than non-defaunated forests, with negative consequences for palm regeneration. Coalescence and phenotypic selection models indicate that seed size reduction most likely occurred within the last 100 years, associated with human-driven fragmentation. The fast-paced defaunation of large vertebrates is most likely causing unprecedented changes in the evolutionary trajectories and community composition of tropical forests.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.2pm42/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.2pm42/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.2pm42/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.48475","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.48475","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1126/science.1233774","PMID:23723235"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2pm42"}}