{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-10-01T19:02:40Z","author":["Matosiuk, Maciej","Sheremetyeva, Irina N.","Borkowska, Anetta","Saveljev, Alexander P.","Sheremetyev, Ilya S."],"title":"Data from: Evolutionary neutrality of mtDNA introgression: evidence from complete mitogenome analysis in roe deer","host":"Matosiuk M, Sheremetyeva IN, Sheremetyev IS, Saveljev AP, Borkowska A (2014) Evolutionary neutrality of mtDNA introgression: evidence from complete mitogenome analysis in roe deer. Journal of Evolutionary Biology, online in advance of print.","keywords":["roe deer","introgression","mitogenomics","Even-toed ungulates","hybridization","Natural selection"],"description":"Introgressive hybridization offers a unique platform for studying the molecular basis of natural selection acting on mitogenomes. Most of the mtDNA protein-coding genes are extremely conserved; however, some of the observed variations have potentially adaptive significance. Here, we evaluated whether the evolution of mtDNA in closely related roe deer species affected by widespread mtDNA introgression is neutral or adaptive. We characterized and compared 16 complete mitogenomes of European (Capreolus capreolus) and Siberian (C. pygargus) roe deer, including four of Siberian origin introgressed into European species. The average sequence divergence of species-specific lineages was estimated at 2.8% and varied across gene classes. Only 21 of 315 fixed differences identified in protein-coding genes represented nonsynonymous changes. Only three of them were determined to have arisen in the C. pygargus lineage since the time to the most recent common ancestor (TMRCA) of both Capreolus species, reflecting a decelerated evolutionary ratio. The almost four-fold higher dN/dS ratio described for the European roe deer lineage is constrained by overall purifying selection, especially pronounced in the ND4 and ND5 genes. We suggest that the highly divergent C. capreolus lineage could have maintained a capability for genomic incorporation of the well-preserved and almost ancestral type of mtDNA present in C. pygargus. Our analyses did not indicate any signs of positive selection for Siberian roe deer mtDNA, suggesting that the present widespread introgression is evolutionarily neutral.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.tm8k3/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.tm8k3/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.tm8k3/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.tm8k3/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.70072","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.70072","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25262616","doi:10.1111/jeb.12491"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.tm8k3"}}