{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-12T20:05:17Z","author":["True, John R.","Jung, Lawrence","Lachance, Joseph"],"title":"Data from: Genetic background and GxE interactions modulate the penetrance of a naturally occurring wing mutation in Drosophila melanogaster","host":"Lachance J, Jung L, True JR (2013) Genetic background and GxE interactions modulate the penetrance of a naturally occurring wing mutation in Drosophila melanogaster. G3: Genes - Genomes - Genetics 3(11): 1893-1901.","keywords":["incomplete penetrance","Drosophila melanogaster","genotype-by-environment interactions","vesiculated","epistasis"],"description":"Many genes involved in producing complex traits are incompletely penetrant. One such example is vesiculated, an X-linked gene in Drosophila melanogaster that results in wing defects. To examine the genetic architecture of a complex trait (wings containing vesicles), we placed a naturally occurring variant into multiple autosomal backgrounds and quantified penetrance and expressivity at a range of developmental temperatures. We found significant epistasis, genotype-by-environment interactions, and maternal effects. Sex and temperature effects were modulated by genetic background. The severity of wing phenotypes also varied across different genetic backgrounds and expressivity was positively correlated with penetrance. We also found evidence of naturally segregating suppressors of vesiculated. These suppressors were present on both the 2nd and 3rd chromosomes, and complex interactions were observed. Taken together, these findings indicate that multiple genetic and environmental factors modulate the phenotypic effects of a naturally occurring vesiculated allele.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1h2h0/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54257","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54257","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24002866","doi:10.1534/g3.113.007831"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1h2h0"}}