{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-06-09T16:04:06Z","author":["Cattley, Sonia","Belov, Katherine","Barrs, Vanessa R.","O'Brien, Stephen J.","David, Victor","Kirby, Katherine","Morris, Katrina M.","Beatty, Julia A.","Menotti-Raymond, Marilyn"],"title":"Data from: Development of MHC-linked microsatellite markers in the domestic cat and their use to evaluate MHC diversity in domestic cats, cheetahs and Gir lions.","host":"Morris KM, Kirby K, Beatty JA, Barrs VR, Cattley S, David V, O'Brien SJ, Menotti-Raymond M, Belov K (2014) Development of MHC-linked microsatellite markers in the domestic cat and their use to evaluate MHC diversity in domestic cats, cheetahs and Gir lions. Journal of Heredity  105(4): 493-505.","keywords":["Population structure and phylogeography","disease","MHC"],"description":"Diversity within the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) reflects the immunological fitness of a population. MHC-linked microsatellite markers provide a simple and inexpensive method for studying MHC diversity in large scale studies. We have developed six MHC-linked microsatellite markers in the domestic cat and used these, in conjunction with five neutral microsatellites, to assess MHC diversity in domestic mixed breed (n = 129) and purebred Burmese (n = 61) cat populations in Australia. The MHC of outbred Australian cats is polymorphic (average allelic richness = 8.52) while the Burmese population has much significantly lower MHC diversity (average allelic richness = 6.81; P<0.01). The MHC-linked microsatellites along with MHC cloning and sequencing demonstrated moderate MHC diversity in cheetahs (n = 13) and extremely low diversity in Gir lions (n = 13). Our MHC-linked microsatellite markers have potential future use in diversity and disease studies in other populations and breeds of cats as well as in wild felid species.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.7mt1t/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.7mt1t/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.7mt1t/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.7mt1t/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.59413","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.59413","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1093/jhered/esu017","PMID:24620003"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7mt1t"}}