{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-30T17:01:21Z","author":["Fuhrman, Margaret","Jarvik, Jonathan W.","Murphy, Robert F.","Osuna-Highley, Elvira","Kangas, Joshua D.","Glory-Afshar, Estelle","Berget, Peter B.","Coelho, Luis Pedro","Naik, Armaghan W.","Simha, Ramanuja"],"title":"Data from: Determining the subcellular location of new proteins from microscope images using local features","host":"Coelho LP, Kangas JD, Naik AW, Osuna-Highley E, Glory-Afshar E, Fuhrman M, Simha R, Berget PB, Jarvik JW, Murphy RF (2013) Determining the subcellular location of new proteins from microscope images using local features. Bioinformatics 29(18): 2343-2349.","keywords":["green fluorescent protein (GFP)","fluorescent microscopy","bioinformatics","computational biology","subcellular location","bioimage informatics"],"description":"Motivation: Evaluation of previous systems for automated determination of subcellular location from microscope images has been done using datasets in which each location class consisted of multiple images of the same representative protein. Here, we frame a more challenging and useful problem where previously unseen proteins are to be classified. Results: Using CD-tagging, we generated two new image datasets for evaluation of this problem, which contain several different proteins for each location class. Evaluation of previous methods on these new datasets showed that it is much harder to train a classifier that generalizes across different proteins than one that simply recognizes a protein it was trained on. We therefore developed and evaluated additional approaches, incorporating novel modifications of local features techniques. These extended the notion of local features to exploit both the protein image and any reference markers that were imaged in parallel. With these, we obtained a large accuracy improvement in our new datasets over existing methods. Additionally, these features help achieve classification improvements for other previously studied datasets.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70/8"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51891","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51891","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23836142","doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt392"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2vm70"}}