{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-03-26T17:26:12Z","author":["Hulse, Gary Kenneth","Reece, Albert Stuart"],"title":"Data from: Reduction in arterial stiffness and vascular age by naltrexone-induced interruption of opiate agonism","host":"Reece AS, Hulse GK (2013) Reduction in arterial stiffness and vascular age by naltrexone-induced interruption of opiate agonism. BMJ Open 3: e002610.","keywords":["opiates","opiate agonism","antagonists","ageing","atherosclerosis","reversal"],"description":"Objective: To prospectively assess if opiate antagonist treatment or the opiate-free status could reverse opiate-related vasculopathy. Design: Longitudinal Open Observational, Serial “N of One”, over 6.5 years under various treatment conditions: opiate dependence, naltrexone and opiate-free. Setting: Primary care, Australia. Participants: 20 opiate dependent patients (16 males: 16 cases of buprenorphine 4.11+1.17mg, two of methadone 57.5+12.5mg and two of heroin 0.75+0.25g). Intervention: Studies of Central Arterial Stiffness and vascular reference age (RA) were performed longitudinally by SphygmoCor Pulse Wave Analysis (AtCor, Sydney). Primary Outcomes: Primary outcome was vascular age and arterial stiffness accrual under different treatment conditions. Results: The mean chronological age (CA) was 33.62+2.03 years.  The opiate-free condition was associated with a lower apparent vascular age both in itself (males: P=0.0402, females: P=0.0360) and in interaction with time (males: P=0.0001; females: P=0.0004), and confirmed with other measures of arterial stiffness.  The mean modelled RA was 38.82, 37.73 and 35.05 years in the opiate, naltrexone and opiate-free conditions respectively.  The opiate-free condition was superior to opiate agonism after full multivariate adjustment (P=0.0131), with modelled RA/CA of 1.0173, 0.9563, and 0.8985 (reductions of 6.1% and 11.9% respectively). Conclusions: Data demonstrate that opiate-free status improves vascular age and arterial stiffness in previous chronic opiate users..  The role of opiate antagonist treatment in achieving these outcomes requires future clarification and offers hope of novel therapeutic remediation.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pj160/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47017","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47017","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23524044","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002610"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.pj160"}}