{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-10T06:30:04Z","author":["Dill, Allen J.","Jacobson, Dave P.","Kurth, Ryon","O'Malley, Kathleen G.","Banks, Michael A."],"title":"Data from: Adaptive genetic markers discriminate migratory runs of Chinook salmon (Oncorhynchus tshawytscha) amid continued gene flow","host":"O'Malley KG, Jacobson DP, Kurth R, Dill AJ, Banks MA (2013) Adaptive genetic markers discriminate migratory runs of Chinook salmon (Oncorhynchus tshawytscha) amid continued gene flow. Evolutionary Applications 6(8): 1184–1194.","keywords":["Fisheries Management","Population Genetics - Empirical","Conservation Genetics","Conservation Biology","Ecological Genetics","Life History Evolution","Captive Populations","Hybridization"],"description":"Neutral genetic markers are routinely used to define distinct units within species that warrant discrete management. Human-induced changes to gene flow however may reduce the power of such an approach. We tested the efficiency of adaptive vs. neutral genetic markers in differentiating temporally divergent migratory runs of Chinook salmon (Oncorhynchus tshawytscha) amid high gene flow owing to artificial propagation and habitat alteration. We compared seven putative migration timing genes to ten microsatellite loci in delineating three migratory groups of Chinook in the Feather River, CA: offspring of fall run hatchery broodstock that returned as adults to freshwater in fall (fall run), spring run offspring that returned in spring (spring run), and fall run offspring that returned in spring (FRS). We found evidence for significant differentiation between the fall and federally-listed threatened spring groups based on divergence at three circadian clock genes (OtsClock1b, OmyFbxw11 and Omy1009UW), but not neutral markers. We thus demonstrate the importance of genetic marker choice in resolving complex life history types. These findings directly impact conservation management strategies and add to previous evidence from Pacific and Atlantic salmon indicating that circadian clock genes influence migration timing.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.r28v2/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51978","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51978","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24478800","doi:10.1111/eva.12095"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.r28v2"}}