{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-06-24T17:40:23Z","author":["Brady, Seán G.","Rightmyer, Molly G.","Griswold, Terry"],"title":"Data from: Phylogeny and systematics of the bee genus Osmia (Hymenoptera: Megachilidae) with emphasis on North American Melanosmia: subgenera, synonymies, and nesting biology revisited","host":"Rightmyer MG, Griswold T, Brady SG (2013) Phylogeny and systematics of the bee genus Osmia (Hymenoptera: Megachilidae) with emphasis on North American Melanosmia: subgenera, synonymies, and nesting biology revisited. Systematic Entomology 38(3): 561–576.","description":"The predominantly Holarctic bee genus Osmia Panzer is species-rich and behaviourally diverse. A robust phylogeny of this genus is important for understanding the evolution of the immense variety of morphological and behavioural traits exhibited by this group. We infer a phylogeny of Osmia using DNA sequence data obtained from three nuclear genes (elongation factor 1-α, LW-rhodopsin and CAD) and the mitochondrial gene COI. Our taxon sampling places special attention on North American members of the subgenus Melanosmia Schmiedeknecht; we discuss the novel placement of a number of species traditionally assigned to O. (Melanosmia) and examine the relative support for alternative classifications of this species-rich subgenus. We use this new phylogeny to guide a reassessment of morphological and behavioural characters within Osmia. Our results provide support for the recognition of Osmia (Hapsidosmia), subgen.n., a monotypic subgenus containing Osmia iridis Cockerell & Titus. We synonymize Osmia (Mystacosmia) Snelling under O. (Melanosmia), syn.n. We synonymize Osmia (Acanthosmioides) Ashmead under O. (Melanosmia), syn.n., propose ‘odontogaster species group’ as a replacement for the subgeneric name Acanthosmioides, and refine the morphological characters that serve to diagnose the species group. We additionally propose ‘nigrifrons species group’ for a clade within O. (Melanosmia) containing most species formerly placed in Osmia (Centrosmia) Robertson. We demonstrate more cohesive patterns of nest substrate use in the nigrifrons and odontogaster species groups than was previously believed to occur, reconsider character polarity of aspects of the female mandible, and show that a large number of morphological characters have evolved convergently within the genus. In order to facilitate discussion of relevant taxa, we propose the following 15 new synonymies: O. bakeri Sandhouse under O. melanopleura Cockerell; O. crenulaticornis Michener under O. pinorum Cockerell; O. claremontensis Michener under O. sedula Sandhouse; O. cockerelli Sandhouse under O. dakotensis Michener; O. francisconis White under O. enixa Sandhouse; O. hurdi White under O. austromaritima Michener; O. sladeni Sandhouse under O. nifoata Cockerell; O. titusi Cockerell under O. phenax Cockerell; O. subtrevoris Cockerell, O. physariae Cockerell, and O. erecta Michener under O. giliarum Cockerell; and O. universitatis Cockerell, O. integrella Cockerell, O. amala Cockerell, and O. metitia Cockerell under O. nigrifrons Cresson, syn.n. We remove O. wyomingensis Michener from synonymy with O. nifoata Cockerell, stat.n., and O. pinorum Cockerell from synonymy with O. physariae Cockerell, stat.n.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.jd5ff/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.jd5ff/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.jd5ff/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.45787","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.45787","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/syen.12013","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.jd5ff"}}