{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-30T16:49:05Z","author":["Dirlewanger, Elisabeth","Dondini, Luca","Le Dantec, Loïck","Audergon, Jean-Marc","Quéro-Garcia, José","Letourmy, Philippe","Illa, Eudald","Arus, Pere","Tartarini, Stefano","Ruiz, David","Lambert, Patrick","Quilot-Turion, Bénédicte"],"title":"Data from: Comparison of the genetic determinism of two key phenological traits, flowering and maturity dates, in three Prunus species: peach, apricot and sweet cherry","host":"Lambert P, Ruiz D, Dondini L, Illa E, Audergon J, Tartarini S, Letourmy P, Dirlewanger E, Quéro-Garcia J, Le Dantec L, Quilot-Turion B, Arus P (2012) Comparison of the genetic determinism of two key phenological traits, flowering and maturity dates, in three Prunus species: peach, apricot and sweet cherry. Heredity 109: 280-292.","keywords":["Candidate gene","flowering date","Phenology","QTL","maturity date"],"description":"The present study investigates the genetic determinism of flowering and maturity dates, two traits highly affected by global climate change. Flowering and maturity dates were evaluated on five progenies from three Prunus species, peach, apricot and sweet cherry, during three to eight years. Quantitative trait locus (QTL) detection was performed separately for each year and also by integrating data from all years together. High heritability estimates were obtained for flowering and maturity dates. Several QTLs for flowering and maturity dates were highly stable, detected each year of evaluation, suggesting that they were not affected by climatic variations. For flowering date, major QTLs were detected on linkage groups (LG) 4 for apricot and sweet cherry and on LG6 for peach. QTLs were identified on LG2, LG3, LG4 and LG7 for the three species. For maturity date, a major QTL was detected on LG4 in the three species. Using the peach genome sequence data, candidate genes underlying the major QTLs on LG4 and LG6 were investigated and key genes were identified. Our results provide a basis for the identification of genes involved in flowering and maturity dates that could be used to develop cultivar ideotypes adapted to future climatic conditions.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.h29j4/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.h29j4/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40442","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40442","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22828898","doi:10.1038/hdy.2012.38"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.h29j4"}}