{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"62;5;2008","keywords":["population divergence","herbivorous insects","speciation genetics","reproductive isolation","divergent natural selection","AFLPs"],"host":"Egan SP, Nosil P, Funk DJ (2008) Selection and genomic differentiation during ecological speciation: isolating the contributions of host association via a comparative genome scan of Neochlamisus bebbianae leaf beetles. Evolution 62(5): 1162-1181.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.ng09t/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.ng09t/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34774","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-23T15:32:52Z","author":["Egan, Scott P.","Funk, Daniel J.","Nosil, Patrik"],"title":"Data from: Selection and genomic differentiation during ecological speciation: isolating the contributions of host association via a comparative genome scan of Neochlamisus bebbianae leaf beetles","description":"This study uses a comparative genome scan to evaluate the contributions of host plant related divergent selection to genetic differentiation and ecological speciation in maple- and willow-associated populations of Neochlamisus bebbianae leaf beetles. For each of 15 pairwise population comparisons, we identified \"outlier loci\" whose strong differentiation putatively reflects divergent selection. Of 447 AFLP loci, 15% were outliers across multiple population comparisons, and low linkage disequilibrium indicated that these outliers derived from multiple regions of the genome. Outliers were further classified as \"host-specific\" if repeatedly observed in \"different-host\" population comparisons but never in \"same-host\" comparisons. Outliers exhibiting the opposite pattern were analogously classified as \"host-independent.\" Host-specific outliers represented 5% of all loci and were more frequent than host-independent outliers, thus revealing a large role for host-adaptation in population genomic differentiation. Evidence that host-related selection can promote divergence despite gene flow was provided by population trees. These were structured by host-association when datasets included host-specific outliers, but not when based on neutral loci, which united sympatric populations. Lastly, three host-specific outliers were highly differentiated in all nine different-host comparisons. Because host-adaptation promotes reproductive isolation in these beetles, these loci provide promising candidate gene regions for future molecular studies of ecological speciation.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34774","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2008.00352.x","PMID:18298645"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ng09t"}}