{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-23T18:25:41Z","author":["Maia, Rafael","Simons, Mirre","Verhulst, Simon","Leenknegt, Bas"],"title":"Data from: Carotenoid-dependent signals and the evolution of plasma carotenoid levels in birds","keywords":["Bird","Selection: sexual"],"description":"Sexual selection has resulted in a wide array of ornaments used in mate choice, and such indicator traits signal quality honestly when they bear costs, precluding cheating. Carotenoid-dependent coloration has attracted considerable attention in this context, because investing carotenoids in coloration has to be traded off against its physiological functions; carotenoids are antioxidants and increase immunocompetence. This trade-off is hypothesized to underlie the honesty of carotenoid-dependent coloration, signaling the \"handicap\" of allocating carotenoids away from somatic maintenance towards sexual display. Utilizing recent advances in modeling adaptive evolution, we used a comparative approach to investigate the evolution of plasma carotenoid levels using a species-level phylogeny of 178 bird species. We find that the evolutionary optimum for carotenoid levels is higher in lineages that evolved carotenoid-dependent coloration, with strong attraction towards this optimum. Hence carotenoids do not appear limiting given that higher carotenoid levels readily evolve in response to the evolution of carotenoid-dependent coloration. These findings challenge the assumption that carotenoids are a scarce resource, and thus the hypothesis that physiological resource value of carotenoids underlies honesty of carotenoid-dependent traits. Therefore the comparative evidence suggests that other factors such as the acquisition and incorporation of carotenoids are involved in maintaining signal honesty.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.kg007/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68170","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68170","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.kg007"}}