{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-12T17:34:41Z","author":["Chadee, Dave D.","Severson, David W.","Hickner, Paul V.","Mori, Akio"],"title":"Data from: Composite linkage map and enhanced genome map for Culex pipiens complex mosquitoes","host":"Hickner PV, Mori A, Chadee DD, Severson DW (2013) Composite linkage map and enhanced genome map for Culex pipiens complex mosquitoes. Journal of Heredity 104(5): 649-655.","keywords":["supercontigs","genome assembly","SSR","house mosquito","composite linkage map"],"description":"We report here the development of 65 novel microsatellite loci and construction of a composite genetic linkage map for Culex pipiens complex mosquitoes. Microsatellites were identified by in silico screening of the Culex quinquefasciatus genome assembly. Cross-species utility of 73 microsatellites for population studies in C. pipiens sensu stricto and C. quinquefasciatus was evaluated by genotyping a subset of samples collected in Indiana, United States, and Point Fortin, Trinidad. Allele frequencies of 67 microsatellites were within Hardy–Weinberg expectations in both population subsets. A composite linkage map was constructed based on restriction fragment length polymorphism and microsatellite polymorphisms in 12 independent F1 intercross mapping populations. The composite map consists of 61 marker loci totaling 183.9 cM distributed across the 3 linkage groups. These loci cover 29.5, 88.8, and 65.6 cM on chromosomes I–III, respectively, and allow for assignment of 10.4% of the genome assembly and 13.5% of the protein coding genes to chromosome position. Our results suggest that these microsatellites will be useful for mapping and population studies of 2 pervasive species in the C. pipiens complex. Moreover, the composite map presented here will serve as a basis for the construction of high-resolution genetic and physical maps, as well as detection of quantitative trait loci to aid in the investigation of complex genetic traits influencing phenotypes of interest.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rd465/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51338","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51338","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23846985","doi:10.1093/jhered/est040"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.rd465"}}