{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-08-30T20:33:08Z","author":["Utter, Fred M.","Blankenship, Scott M.","Limborg, Morten T.","Seeb, James E.","Young, Sewall F.","Hansen, Mette H. H.","Seeb, Lisa W."],"series":"2;;2012","title":"Data from: Signatures of natural selection among lineages and habitats in Oncorhynchus mykiss","host":"Limborg MT, Blankenship SM, Young SF, Utter FM, Seeb LW, Hansen MHH, Seeb JE (2012) Signatures of natural selection among lineages and habitats in Oncorhynchus mykiss. Ecology and Evolution 2(1): 1–18.","description":"Recent advances in molecular interrogation techniques now allow unprecedented genomic inference about the role of adaptive genetic divergence in wild populations. We used high-throughput genotyping to screen a genome-wide panel of 276 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) for the economically and culturally important salmonid Oncorhynchus mykiss. Samples included 805 individuals from 11 anadromous and resident populations from the northwestern United States and British Columbia, and represented two major lineages including paired populations of each life history within single drainages of each lineage. Overall patterns of variation affirmed clear distinctions between lineages and in most instances, isolation by distance within them. Evidence for divergent selection at eight candidate loci included significant landscape correlations, particularly with temperature. High diversity of two nonsynonymous mutations within the peptide-binding region of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class II (DAB) gene provided signatures of balancing selection. Weak signals for potential selection between sympatric resident and anadromous populations were revealed from genome scans and allele frequency comparisons. Our results suggest an important adaptive role for immune-related functions and present a large genomic resource for future studies.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v74b8/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42106","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42106","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22408722","doi:10.1002/ece3.59"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.v74b8"}}