{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-09-24T13:21:26Z","author":["Surget-Groba, Yann","Kay, Kathleen M."],"title":"Data from: Restricted gene flow within and between rapidly diverging neotropical plant species","host":"Kay KM, Surget-Groba Y (2013) Restricted gene flow within and between rapidly diverging neotropical plant species. Molecular Ecology 22(19): 4931–4942.","keywords":["Speciation","Population Genetics - Empirical","Angiosperms","Hybridization"],"description":"Speciation involves the evolution of traits and genetic differences that contribute to reproductive isolation and the cessation of gene flow, and studying closely related species and divergent populations gives insight into how these phenomena proceed. Here, we document patterns of gene flow within and between two members of a rapid Neotropical species radiation, Costus pulverulentus and Costus scaber (Costaceae). These species co-occur in the tropical rainforest and share pollinators, but are reproductively isolated by a series of prezygotic barriers, some of which show evidence of reinforcement at sympatric sites. Here, we genotype microsatellite markers in plants from eight sites that span the geographical range of both species, including four sympatric sites. We also genotype putative hybrids found at two sympatric sites. We find high levels of genetic isolation among populations within each species and low but detectable levels of introgression between species at sympatric sites. Putative hybrids identified by morphology are consistent with F1 or more advanced hybrids. Our results highlight the effectiveness of prezygotic isolating mechanisms at maintaining species boundaries in young radiations and provide empirical data on levels of gene flow consistent with reinforcement.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8q34c/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8q34c/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.8q34c/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.8q34c/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.51664","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.51664","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12442","PMID:23952304"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8q34c"}}