{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-09-06T15:42:05Z","author":["Neiman, Maurine","Jokela, Jukka","Paczesniak, Dorota","Larkin, Katelyn"],"title":"Data from: Discordance between nuclear and mitochondrial genomes in sexual and asexual lineages of the freshwater snail Potamopyrgus antipodarum","host":"Paczesniak D, Jokela J, Larkin K, Neiman M (2013) Discordance between nuclear and mitochondrial genomes in sexual and asexual lineages of the freshwater snail Potamopyrgus antipodarum. Molecular Ecology 22(18): 4695-4710.","keywords":["parthenogenetic","polyploidy","SNP","mating systems","selective sweep"],"description":"The presence and extent of mitonuclear discordance in coexisting sexual and asexual lineages provides insight into 1) how and when asexual lineages emerged, and 2) the spatial and temporal scales at which the ecological and evolutionary processes influencing the evolution of sexual and asexual reproduction occur. Here, we used nuclear single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers and a mitochondrial gene to characterize phylogeographic structure and the extent of mitonuclear discordance in Potamopyrgus antipodarum. This New Zealand freshwater snail is often used to study the evolution and maintenance of sex because obligately sexual and obligately asexual individuals often coexist. While our data indicate that sexual and asexual P. antipodarum sampled from the same lake population are often genetically similar, suggesting recent origin of these asexuals from sympatric sexual P. antipodarum, we also found significantly more population structure in sexuals vs. asexuals. This latter result suggests that some asexual lineages originated in other lakes and/or in the relatively distant past. When comparing mitochondrial and nuclear population genetic structure, we discovered that one mitochondrial haplotype (‘1A’) was rare in sexuals, but common and widespread in asexuals. Haplotype 1A frequency and nuclear genetic diversity were not associated, suggesting that the commonness of this haplotype cannot be attributed entirely to genetic drift and pointing instead to a role for selection.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.j18pv/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.j18pv/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.50549","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.50549","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12422","PMID:23957656"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.j18pv"}}