{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"Biology Letters","keywords":["baboons","hybridization"],"host":"Roberts TE, Davenport TRB, Hildebrandt KBP, Jones T, Stanley WT, Sargis EJ, Olson LE (2010) The biogeography of introgression in the critically endangered African monkey Rungweceubs kipunji. Biology Letters 6: 233-237.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.1096/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.1096","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-08-02T20:18:31Z","author":["Davenport, Tim R. B.","Hildebrandt, Kyndall B. P.","Stanley, William T.","Sargis, Eric J.","Jones, Trevor","Roberts, Trina E.","Olson, Link E."],"title":"Data from: The biogeography of introgression in the critically endangered African monkey Rungweceubs kipunji","description":"In the four years since its original description, the taxonomy of the kipunji (Rungwecebus kipunji), a geographically restricted and critically endangered African monkey, has been the subject of much debate, and recent research suggesting that the first voucher specimen of Rungwecebus has baboon mitochondrial DNA has intensified the controversy.  We show that Rungwecebus from a second region of Tanzania has a distinct mitochondrial haplotype that is basal to a clade containing all Papio species and the original Rungwecebus voucher, supporting the placement of Rungwecebus as the sister taxon of Papio and its status as a separate genus.  We suggest that the Rungwecebus population in the Southern Highlands has experienced geographically localized mitochondrial DNA introgression from Papio, while the Ndundulu population retains the true Rungwecebus mitochondrial genome.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.1096","isReferencedBy":["PMID:19906681","doi:10.1098/rsbl.2009.0741"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.1096"}}