{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-01-18T17:20:39Z","author":["Ronikier, Michał","Coldea, Gheorghe","Korbecka, Grażyna","Marhold, Karel","Garraud, Luc","Cristea, Vasile","Colli, Licia","Cieślak, Elżbieta","Gutermann, Walter","Zimmermann, Niklaus E.","Perico, Giovanni","Holderegger, Rolf","Küpfer, Philippe","Prosser, Filippo","Gugerli, Felix","Ajmone Marsan, Paolo","Wraber, Tone","Bona, Enzo","Kagalo, Alexander A.","Letz, Dominik Roman","Manel, Stéphanie","Steinmann, Katharina","Winkler, Manuela","Pellecchia, Marco","Bovio, Maurizio","Ahlmer, Wolfgang","Tribsch, Andreas","Piękoś-Mirkowa, Halina","van Loo, Marcela","Moilanen, Atte","Alvarez, Nadir","Dalmas, Jean-Pierre","Schüpfer, Fanny","Taberlet, Pierre","Niño, Fernando","Puşcaş, Mihai","Choler, Philippe","Niklfeld, Harald","Mansion, Guilhelm","Englisch, Thorsten","Jogan, Nejc","Schönswetter, Peter","Lequette, Benoît","Gielly, Ludovic","Scheuerer, Martin","Paun, Ovidiu","Selvaggi, Alberto","Gaudeul, Myriam","Wohlgemuth, Thomas","Mirek, Zbigniew","Schneeweiss, Gerald M.","Thiel-Egenter, Conny","Martini, Fabrizio","Schratt-Ehrendorfer, Luise","Frajman, Božo","IntraBioDiv Consortium,","Negrini, Riccardo"],"title":"Data from: Genetic diversity in widespread species is not congruent with species richness in alpine plant communities","host":"Taberlet P, Zimmermann NE, Englisch T, Tribsch A, Holderegger R, Alvarez N, Niklfeld H, Coldea G, Mirek Z, Moilanen A, Ahlmer W, Ajmone Marsan P, Bona E, Bovio M, Choler P, Cieślak E, Colli L, Cristea V, Dalmas J, Frajman B, Garraud L, Gaudeul M, Gielly L, Gutermann W, Jogan N, Kagalo AA, Korbecka G, Küpfer P, Lequette B, Letz DR, Manel S, Mansion G, Marhold K, Martini F, Negrini R, Niño F, Paun O, Pellecchia M, Perico G, Piękoś-Mirkowa H, Prosser F, Puşcaş M, Ronikier M, Scheuerer M, Schneeweiss GM, Schönswetter P, Schratt-Ehrendorfer L, Schüpfer F, Selvaggi A, Steinmann K, Thiel-Egenter C, van Loo M, Winkler M, Wohlgemuth T, Wraber T, Gugerli F, IntraBioDiv Consortium (2012) Genetic diversity in widespread species is not congruent with species richness in alpine plant communities. Ecology Letters 15(12): 1439-1448.","keywords":["biodiversity conservation","species richness","genetic diversity","alpine vascular plants"],"description":"The Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) aims at the conservation of all three levels of biodiversity, i.e. ecosystems, species and genes. Genetic diversity represents evolutionary potential and is important for ecosystem functioning. Unfortunately, genetic diversity in natural populations is hardly considered in conservation strategies because it is difficult to measure and has been hypothesized to co-vary with species richness. This means that species richness is taken as a surrogate of genetic diversity in conservation planning, though their relationship has not been properly evaluated. We tested whether the genetic and species levels of biodiversity co-vary, using a large-scale and multi-species approach. We chose the high-mountain flora of the Alps and the Carpathians as study systems and demonstrate that species richness and genetic diversity are not correlated. Species richness thus cannot act as a surrogate for genetic diversity. Our results have important consequences for implementing the CBD when designing conservation strategies.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s4q6s/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.42148","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.42148","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/ele.12004","PMID:23006492"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.s4q6s"}}