{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-04T14:13:50Z","author":["Giraud, Isabelle","Grandjean, Frédéric","Bech, Nicolas","Valette, Victorien","Cordaux, Richard"],"title":"Data from: Isolation and characterization of microsatellite loci for the isopod crustacean Armadillidium vulgare and transferability in terrestrial isopods","host":"Giraud I, Valette V, Bech N, Grandjean F, Cordaux R (2013) Isolation and characterization of microsatellite loci for the isopod crustacean Armadillidium vulgare and transferability in terrestrial isopods. PLoS ONE 8(10): e76639.","description":"Armadillidium vulgare is a terrestrial isopod (Crustacea, Oniscidea) which harbors Wolbachia bacterial endosymbionts. A. vulgare is the major model for the study of Wolbachia-mediated feminization of genetic males in crustaceans. As a consequence of their impact on host sex determination mechanisms, Wolbachia endosymbionts are thought to significantly influence A. vulgare evolution on various grounds, including population genetic structure, diversity and reproduction strategies. To provide molecular tools for examining these questions, we isolated microsatellite loci through 454 pyrosequencing of a repeat-enriched A. vulgare genomic library. We selected 14 markers and developed three polymorphic microsatellite multiplex kits. We tested the kits on two A. vulgare natural populations and found high genetic variation, thereby making it possible to investigate the impact of Wolbachia endosymbionts on A. vulgare nuclear variation at unprecedented resolution. In addition, we tested the transferability of these kits by cross-species amplification in five other terrestrial isopod species harboring Wolbachia endosymbionts. The microsatellite loci showed good transferability in particular in Armadillidium nasatum and Chaetophiloscia elongata, for which these markers represent promising tools for future genetic studies.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.md545/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53445","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53445","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0076639","PMID:24098543"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.md545"}}