{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-03-19T18:47:41Z","author":["Pelletreau, Karen N.","Coats, Vanessa C.","Rumpho, Mary E."],"title":"Data from: Amplicon pyrosequencing reveals the soil microbial diversity associated with invasive Japanese barberry (Berberis thunbergii DC.)","host":"Coats VC, Pelletreau KN, Rumpho ME (2013) Amplicon pyrosequencing reveals the soil microbial diversity associated with invasive Japanese barberry (Berberis thunbergii DC.). Molecular Ecology 23(6): 1318–1332.","keywords":["Bacteria","Metagenomics","Invasive Species","Bioinfomatics/Phyloinfomatics","Angiosperms"],"description":"The soil microbial community acts as a reservoir of microbes that directly influences the structure and composition of the aboveground plant community, promotes plant growth, increases stress tolerance and mediates local patterns of nutrient cycling. Direct interactions between plants and rhizosphere-dwelling microorganisms occur at, or near, the surface of the root. Upon introduction and establishment, invasive plants modify the soil microbial communities and soil biochemistry affecting bioremediation efforts and future plant communities. Here, we used tag-encoded FLX amplicon 454 pyrosequencing (TEFAP) to characterize the bacterial and fungal community diversity in the rhizosphere of Berberis thunbergii DC. (Japanese barberry) from invasive stands in coastal Maine to investigate effects of soil type, soil chemistry and surrounding plant cover on the soil microbial community structure. Acidobacteria, Actinobacteria, Proteobacteria and Verrucomicrobia were the dominant bacterial phyla, whereas fungal communities were comprised mostly of Ascomycota and Basidiomycota phyla members, including Agaricomycetes and Sordariomycetes. Bulk soil chemistry had more effect on the bacterial community structure than the fungal community. An effect of geographic location was apparent in the rhizosphere microbial communities, yet it was less significant than the effect of surrounding plant cover. These data demonstrate a high degree of spatial variation in the rhizosphere microbial communities of Japanese barberry with apparent effects of soil chemistry, location and canopy cover on the microbial community structure.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.68k7g/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54570","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54570","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24118303","doi:10.1111/mec.12544"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.68k7g"}}