{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-12T17:44:07Z","author":["Li, Ling","Yao, Hai-Mu","Zhao, Luo-Sha","Zhang, Xiao-Juan","Wan, You-Dong","Shen, De-Liang","Sun, Tong-Wen","Zhang, Jin-Ying"],"title":"Data from: Long-term follow-up results in patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) with drug-eluting stents: results from a single high-volume PCI center","host":"Yao H, Wan Y, Zhang X, Shen D, Zhang J, Li L, Zhao L, Sun T (2014) Long-term follow-up results in patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) with drug-eluting stents: results from a single high-volume PCI center. BMJ Open 4(8): e004892.","keywords":["Coronary intervention","Clinical trials","Cardiology","Myocardial infarction"],"description":"Objective: To assess both short and long-term prognosis in consecutive patients with coronary heart disease (CHD) treated with drug-eluting stents (DES) in a high-volume percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) center. Design: Observational cohort study. Setting: A hospital in the Henan province, China, between 2009 and 2011. Participants: A total of 2,533 patients were enrolled. Patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) treated with urgent PCI accounted for 3.9% of cases; patients with STEMI treated with delayed PCI accounted for 20.5% of cases; patients with stable angina (SA) accounted for 16.5% of cases; and patients with non-ST elevation acute coronary syndromes (NSTE-ACS) accounted for 58.6% of cases. Primary outcomes: Death, major adverse cardiac and cerebrovascular events (MACCE: death/myocardial infarction/stroke), and target vessel revascularization. Results: Follow-up after a median of 29.8 months was obtained for 2,533 patients (92.6%). The mortality rate during hospitalization was highest in the urgent PCI group (p <0.001). During follow-up, although the incidences of death and MACCE were highest in the urgent PCI group, no significant differences were observed between the different groups. The incidences of cardiac death and myocardial infarction were significantly higher in the paclitaxel-eluting stent (PES) group than in the sirolimus-eluting stent (SES) group. Independent predictors of death during follow-up were: age, left ventricular ejection function (LVEF) < 40%, diabetes mellitus, prior coronary artery bypass graft (CABG), and chronic total occlusion. Conclusions: PCI patients with STEMI had the worst hospital and long-term prognosis. The mortality rate after hospital increased markedly in NSTE-ACS patients. SES seems to be more effective than PES.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.13d31/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.13d31/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.67560","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.67560","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2014-004892","PMID:25113554"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.13d31"}}