{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-22T13:02:06Z","author":["Kitson, James J. N.","Strasberg, Dominique","Florens, F. B. Vincent","Warren, Ben H.","Emerson, Brent C.","Baider, Claudia"],"title":"Data from: Molecular characterisation of trophic ecology within an island radiation of insect herbivores (Curculionidae: Entiminae: Cratopus).","host":"Kitson JJN, Warren BH, Florens FBV, Baider C, Strasberg D, Emerson BC (2013) Molecular characterisation of trophic ecology within an island radiation of insect herbivores (Curculionidae: Entiminae: Cratopus). Molecular Ecology 22(21): 5441–5455.","keywords":["Phylogeography","Species Interactions","Population Genetics - Empirical","Natural Selection and Contemporary Evolution","Adaptation","Insects"],"description":"The phytophagous beetle family Curculionidae is the most species-rich insect family known, with much of this diversity having been attributed to both co-evolution with food plants and host-shifts at key points within the early evolutionary history of the group. Less well understood is the extent to which patterns of host use vary within or among related species, largely because of the technical difficulties associated with quantifying this. Here we develop a recently characterised molecular approach to quantify diet within and between two closely related species of weevil occurring primarily within dry forests on the island of Mauritius. Our aim is to quantify dietary variation across populations and assess adaptive and non-adaptive explanations for this, and to characterise the nature of a trophic shift within an ecologically distinct population within one of the species. We find that our study species are polyphagous, consuming a much wider range of plants than would be suggested by the literature. Our data suggest that local diet variation is largely explained by food availability, and locally specialist populations consume food plants that are not phylogenetically novel, but do appear to represent a novel preference. Our results demonstrate the power of molecular methods to unambiguously quantify dietary variation across populations of insect herbivores, providing a valuable approach to understanding trophic interactions within and among local plant and insect herbivore communities.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.ss427/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.ss427/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.ss427/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.50246","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.50246","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24112379","doi:10.1111/mec.12477"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.ss427"}}