{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-14T16:13:01Z","author":["Sanchez, Sophie","Molnar, Julia L.","Hutchinson, John R.","Tafforeau, Paul","Pierce, Stephanie E.","Ahlberg, Per E.","Clack, Jennifer A."],"title":"Data from: Vertebral architecture in the earliest stem tetrapods","host":"Pierce SE, Ahlberg PE, Hutchinson JR, Molnar JL, Sanchez S, Tafforeau P, Clack JA (2013) Vertebral architecture in the earliest stem tetrapods. Nature 494(7536): 226–229.","keywords":["Tetrapod","vertebrae","evolution"],"description":"The construction of the vertebral column has been used as a key anatomical character in defining and diagnosing early tetrapod groups. Rhachitomous vertebrae - in which there is a dorsally placed neural arch and spine, an anteroventrally placed intercentrum and paired, posterodorsally placed pleurocentra - have long been considered the ancestral morphology for tetrapods. Nonetheless, very little is known about vertebral anatomy in the earliest stem tetrapods, as most specimens remain trapped in surrounding matrix, obscuring important anatomical features. Here we describe the three-dimensional vertebral architecture of the Late Devonian stem tetrapod Ichthyostega using propagation phase contrast x-ray synchrotron microtomography (PPC-SRµCT). Our scans reveal a diverse array of new morphological, and associated developmental and functional, characteristics, including a possible posterior-to-anterior vertebral ossification sequence and the first evolutionary appearance of ossified sternal elements. However, one of the most intriguing features relates to the positional relationships between the vertebral elements, with the pleurocentra being unexpectedly sutured/fused to the intercentra that directly succeed them - implying a 'reverse' rhachitomous design. Comparison of Ichthyostega with two other stem tetrapods, Acanthostega and Pederpes, shows that 'reverse' rhachitomous vertebrae may be the ancestral condition for limbed vertebrates. This study fundamentally revises our current understanding of vertebral column evolution in the earliest tetrapods and raises questions about the presumed vertebral architecture of tetrapodomorph fish and later, more crownward, tetrapods.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.0003s/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44529","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44529","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23334417","doi:10.1038/nature11825"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.0003s"}}