{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-08-24T19:40:38Z","author":["Baviera, Cosimo","Frati, Francesco","Lo Paro, Giuseppe","Stroscio, Stefania","Nardi, Francesco"],"title":"Data from: Colonization of the Aeolian Islands by Pimelia rugulosa rugulosa Germar, 1824 (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae) inferred from the genetic structure of populations: geological and environmental relations.","host":"Stroscio S, Baviera C, Frati F, Lo Paro G, Nardi F (2011) Colonization of the Aeolian Islands by Pimelia rugulosa rugulosa Germar, 1824 (Coleoptera, Tenebrionidae) inferred from the genetic structure of populations: geological and environmental relations. Biological Journal of the Linnean Society 104(1): 29-37.","keywords":["Mediterranean","phylogeography","volcanism","mitochondrial cox2","insects distribution","island biogeography"],"description":"The darkling beetle Pimelia rugulosa rugulosa Germar, 1824 was selected to investigate the process of colonization in a volcanic archipelago and the role of volcanism in determining spatial patterns of genetic variability. Analyses were conducted in the Aeolian Islands, located in the central Mediterranean directly off the Sicilian coast. Genetic variability and geographic structure were studied in individuals from each island of the archipelago based on sequences of the cytochrome c oxidase subunit 2 mitochondrial gene; a network approach was employed to identify haplotype lineages. A strong genetic structure, with no haplotype sharing among islands, was observed. Six separate lineages were identified that independently colonized different islands of the archipelago from the mainland and differentiated locally to form small haplogroups. Variability of observed haplogroups is correlated with island age and a positive correlation between tenebrionid diversity and mitotype diversity is reported. Some, yet undescribed, catastrophic event is hypothesized to explain the depletion of a substantial part of genetic as well as biological diversity in the island of Filicudi.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9073/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.9073","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.9073","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1111/j.1095-8312.2011.01701.x","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.9073"}}