{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-03-28T17:01:44Z","author":["Buffenstein, Rochelle","Casper, Diana","Kristan, Deborah M.","Gelfond, Jonathan A.","Mele, James","Huchon, Dorothee","Edrey, Yael H.","Nevo, Eviatar"],"title":"Data from: Sustained high levels of neuregulin-1 in the longest-lived rodents; a key determinant of rodent longevity","host":"Edrey YH, Casper D, Huchon D, Mele J, Gelfond JA, Kristan DM, Nevo E, Buffenstein R (2011) Sustained high levels of neuregulin-1 in the longest-lived rodents; a key determinant of rodent longevity. Aging Cell 11(2): 213-222.","keywords":["naked mole-rat","maximum lifespan","Spalax","Neuregulin-1","Aging","Phylogenetic tree","ErbB4","neurotrophic factors","cerebellum"],"description":"Naked mole-rats (Heterocephalus glaber), the longest-lived rodents, live 7-10 times longer than similarly–sized mice and exhibit normal activities for ∼75% of their lives. Little is known about the mechanisms that allow them to delay the aging process and live so long. Neuregulin-1 (NRG-1) signaling is critical for normal brain function during both development and adulthood. We hypothesized that long-lived species will maintain higher levels of NRG-1 and that this contributes to their sustained brain function and concomitant maintenance of normal activity. We monitored the levels of NRG-1 and its receptor ErbB4 in H. glaber at different ages ranging from 1 day to 26 years and found that levels for NRG-1 and ErbB4 were sustained throughout development and adulthood. In addition, we compared seven rodent species with widely divergent (4-32y) maximum lifespan potential (MLSP) and found that at a physiologically-equivalent age, the longer-lived rodents had higher levels of NRG-1 and ErbB4. Moreover, phylogenetic independent contrast analyses revealed that this significant strong correlation between MLSP and NRG-1 levels was independent of phylogeny. These results suggest that NRG-1 is an important factor contributing to divergent species MLSP through its role in maintaining neuronal integrity.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.3h3f3380/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.3h3f3380/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.3h3f3380/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.36954","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.36954","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22103690","doi:10.1111/j.1474-9726.2011.00772.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3h3f3380"}}