{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-11-06T16:32:51Z","author":["Buckling, Angus","Inglis, R. Fredrik","Brown, Sam Paul"],"title":"Data from: Spite versus cheats: competition among social strategies shapes virulence in Pseudomonas aeruginosa","host":"Inglis RF, Brown SP, Buckling A (2012) Spite versus cheats: competition among social strategies shapes virulence in Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Evolution 66(11): 3472–3484.","keywords":["bacteriocin","kin selection","social evolution","strong reciprocity","virulence","siderophore"],"description":"Social interactions have been shown to play an important role in bacterial evolution and virulence. The majority of empirical studies conducted have only considered social traits in isolation, yet numerous social traits, such as the production of spiteful bacteriocins (anti-competitor toxins) and iron-scavenging siderophores (a public good) by the opportunistic pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa, are frequently expressed simultaneously. Crucially, both bacteriocin production and siderophore cheating can be favoured under the same competitive conditions, and we develop theory and carry out experiments to determine how the success of a bacteriocin-producing genotype is influenced by social cheating of susceptible competitors and the resultant impact on disease severity (virulence). Consistent with our theoretical predictions, we find that the spiteful genotype is favoured at higher local frequencies when competing against public good cheats. Furthermore, the relationship between spite frequency and virulence is significantly altered when the spiteful genotype is competed against cheats compared with cooperators. These results confirm the ecological and evolutionary importance of considering multiple social traits simultaneously. Moreover, our results are consistent with recent theory regarding the invasion conditions for strong reciprocity (helping cooperators and harming non-cooperators).","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.dn367/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.dn367/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.dn367/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.dn367/3"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.39580","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.39580","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01706.x","PMID:23106711"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.dn367"}}