{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-02-07T14:45:45Z","author":["Matzke, Nicholas J.","Gillespie, Rosemary G.","Wood, Hannah Marie","Griswold, Charles E."],"title":"Data from: Treating fossils as terminal taxa in divergence time estimation reveals ancient vicariance patterns in the palpimanoid spiders","host":"Wood HM, Matzke NJ, Gillespie RG, Griswold CE (2012) Treating fossils as terminal taxa in divergence time estimation reveals ancient vicariance patterns in the palpimanoid spiders. Systematic Biology 62(2): 264-284.","keywords":["molecular clock","total evidence","vicariance","Pangaea","Gondwana","fossils","biogeography","divergence time estimation"],"description":"Incorporation of fossils into biogeographic studies can have a profound effect on the conclusions that result, particularly when fossil ranges are nonoverlapping with extant ranges. This is the case in archaeid spiders, where there are known fossils from the Northern Hemisphere, yet all living members are restricted to the Southern Hemisphere. To better understand the biogeographic patterns of archaeid spiders and their palpimanoid relatives, we estimate a dated phylogeny using a relaxed clock on a combined molecular and morphological data set. Dating information is compared with treating the archaeid fossil taxa as both node calibrations and as noncontemporaneous terminal tips, both with and without additional calibration points. Estimation of ancestral biogeographic ranges is then performed, using likelihood and Bayesian methods to take into account uncertainty in phylogeny and in dating. We find that treating the fossils as terminal tips within a Bayesian framework, as opposed to dating the phylogeny based only on molecular data with the dates coming from node calibrations, removes the subjectivity involved in assigning priors, which has not been possible with previous methods. Our analyses suggest that the diversification of the northern and southern archaeid lineages was congruent with the breakup of Pangaea into Laurasia and Gondwanaland. This analysis provides a rare example, and perhaps the most strongly supported, where a dated phylogeny confirms a biogeographical hypothesis based on vicariance due to the breakup of the ancient continental plates.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/11","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d/7"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.43974","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.43974","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23192838","doi:10.1093/sysbio/sys092"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.7231d"}}