{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2011-09-02T17:08:13Z","author":["Tango, Jazzlyn M.","Ong, Perry S.","Basiao, Zubaida U.","Pagulayan, Roberto C.","Quilang, Jonas P.","Aquilino, Sean Vincent L.","Fontanilla, Ian Kendrich C."],"title":"Data from: DNA barcoding of the ichthyofauna of Taal Lake, Philippines","host":"Aquilino SVL, Tango JM, Fontanilla IKC, Pagulayan RC, Basiao ZU, Ong PS, Quilang JP (2011) DNA barcoding of the ichthyofauna of Taal Lake, Philippines. Molecular Ecology Resources 11(4): 612-619.","keywords":["COI","Fish","DNA Barcoding"],"description":"This study represents the first molecular survey of the ichthyofauna of Taal Lake and the first DNA barcoding attempt in Philippine fishes. Taal Lake, the third largest lake in the Philippines, is considered a very important fisheries resource and is home to the world’s only freshwater sardine, Sardinella tawilis. However, over-exploitation and introduction of exotic fishes have caused a massive decline in the diversity of native species as well as overall productivity of the lake. In this study, 118 individuals of 23 native, endemic, and introduced fishes of Taal Lake were barcoded using the partial DNA sequence of the mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase I (COI) gene. These species belong to 21 genera, 17 families and 9 orders. Divergence of sequences within and between species was determined using Kimura 2-parameter (K2P) distance model and a neighbor-joining tree was generated with 1000 bootstrap replications using the K2P model. All COI sequences for each of the 23 species were clearly discriminated among genera. The average within species, within genus, within family, and within order percent genetic divergence was 0.60%, 11.07%, 17.67%, and 24.08%, respectively. Our results provide further evidence that COI DNA barcodes are effective for rapid and accurate identification of fishes and for identifying certain species that need further taxonomic investigation.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8416/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.8416/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.8416/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.8416/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.8416/5"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8416","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8416","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1755-0998.2011.03000.x","PMID:21676192"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8416"}}