{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-13T14:47:30Z","author":["Taylor, Rod","Lewin, Robert","Wingham, Jennifer","Palmer, Joanne","Dalal, Hasnain M.","Petre, Corinna"],"title":"Data from: Why do so few patients with heart failure participate in cardiac rehabilitation? A cross-sectional survey from England, Wales and Northern Ireland","host":"Dalal HM, Wingham J, Palmer J, Taylor R, Petre C, Lewin R (2012) Why do so few patients with heart failure participate in cardiac rehabilitation? A cross-sectional survey from England, Wales and Northern Ireland. BMJ Open 2(2): e000787.","keywords":["Quality in health care","Heart failure","Adult cardiology"],"description":"OBJECTIVES: To determine why so few patients with chronic heart failure in England, Wales, and Northern Ireland take part in cardiac rehabilitation. DESIGN: Two-stage, postal questionnaire-based, national survey. PARTICIPANTS AND SETTING: Stage 1: 277 cardiac rehabilitation centres in England, Wales, and Northern Ireland registered on the National Audit of Cardiac Rehabilitation register in 2009–10. Stage 2: 35 centres that indicated in stage 1 that they provide a separate cardiac rehabilitation programme for patients with heart failure. RESULTS: Full data were available for 224/277 (81%) cardiac rehabilitation centres. Only 90/224 (40%) routinely offered phase 3 cardiac rehabilitation to patients with heart failure. Of these 90 centres that offered rehabilitation, 43% did so only when heart failure was secondary to myocardial infarction or revascularisation. Less than half (39%) had a specific rehabilitation programme for heart failure. Of those not providing for patients with heart failure, 134/224 (60%) considered a lack of resources and 89/224 (40%) exclusion from commissioning contracts as the reason for not recruiting patients with heart failure. Overall, only 35/224 (16%) centres provided a separate rehabilitation programme for people with heart failure. CONCLUSION: Patients with heart failure as a primary diagnosis are excluded from most cardiac rehabilitation programmes in England, Wales, and Northern Ireland. A lack of resources and direct exclusion from local commissioning agreements are the main barriers for not offering rehabilitation to patients with heart failure.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.n6661sh1/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.n6661sh1/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.n6661sh1/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.38026","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.38026","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22454188","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2011-000787"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.n6661sh1"}}