{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"49;6;2013","keywords":["molecular dating","phylogeny","diversification","whole genome duplication","mtDNA"],"host":"Shedko SV, Miroshnichenko IL, Nemkova GA (2013) Phylogeny of salmonids (salmoniformes: Salmonidae) and its molecular dating: analysis of mtDNA data. Russian Journal of Genetics 49(6): 623-637.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.r42qf/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49427","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2013-06-17T18:46:47Z","author":["Miroshnichenko, Irina L.","Shedko, Sergei V.","Nemkova, Galina A."],"title":"Data from: Phylogeny of salmonids (salmoniformes: Salmonidae) and its molecular dating: analysis of mtDNA data","description":"Phylogenetic relationships among 41 species of salmonid fish and some aspects of their diversification-time history were studied using the GenBank and original mtDNA data. The position of the root of the Salmonidae phylogenetic tree was uncertain. Among the possible variants, the most reasonable seems to be that in which thymallins are grouped into the same clade as coregonins and the lineage of salmonins occupied a basal position relative to this clade. The genera of Salmoninae formed two distinct clades, i.e., (Brachymystax, Hucho) and (Salmo, Parahucho, (Salvelinus, (Parasalmo, Oncorhynchus)). Furthermore, the genera Parasalmo and Oncorhynchus were reciprocally monophyletic. The congruence of Salmonidae phylogenetic trees obtained using different types of phylogenetic markers is discussed. According to Bayesian dating, ancestral lineages of salmonids and their sister esocoids diverged about 106 million years ago. Sometime after, probably 100–70 million years ago, the salmonid-specific whole genome duplication took place. The divergence of salmonid lineages on the genus level occurred much later, within the time interval of 42–20 million years ago. The main wave of the diversification of salmonids at the species level occurred during the last 12 million years. The possible effect of genome duplication on the Salmonidae diversification pattern is discussed.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49427","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1134/S1022795413060112","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.r42qf"}}