{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"4;;2003","keywords":["population genetics","microsatellite","coho salmon"],"host":"Olsen JB, Miller SJ, Spearman WJ, Wenburg JK (2003) Patterns of intra- and inter-population genetic diversity in Alaskan coho salmon: implications for conservation. Conservation Genetics 4(5): 557-569.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.331sq/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.331sq/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.34376","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2011-07-13T18:04:02Z","author":["Spearman, William J","Olsen, Jeffrey B","Wenburg, John K","Miller, Steve J"],"title":"Data from: Patterns of intra- and inter-population genetic diversity in Alaskan coho salmon: implications for conservation","description":"Little is known about the genetic diversity of coho salmon in Alaska, although this area represents half of the species’ North American range.  In this study, nine microsatellite loci were used to genotype 32 putative coho salmon populations from seven regions of Alaska.  The primary objectives were to estimate and evaluate the degree and spatial distribution of neutral genetic diversity within and among populations of Alaskan coho salmon.  Genetic analysis yielded four results that provide insight into forces influencing genetic diversity in Alaskan coho salmon and have important conservation implications: 1) significant population differentiation was found within each region; 2) the degree of differentiation (FST = 0.099) among populations was as large or larger than that reported for other Pacific salmon species in Alaska; 3) phenetic clustering of populations showed weak geographic concordance; 4) strong genetic isolation by distance was only apparent at the finest geographic scale (within a drainage).  These results suggest that coho salmon populations are small relative to populations of other Pacific salmon, and the genetic diversity within and among coho salmon populations is influenced primarily by genetic drift, and not gene flow.  Resource management and conservation actions affecting coho salmon in Alaska must recognize that the populations are generally small, isolated, and probably exhibit local adaptation to different spawning and freshwater rearing habitats.  These factors justify managing and conserving Alaskan coho salmon at a fine geographic scale.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.34376","isReferencedBy":"doi:10.1023/A:1025684104113","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.331sq"}}