{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-14T17:48:38Z","author":["Jones, Adam G.","Harper, Cristin","Small, Clayton M.","Saucedo, Hector A.","Rose, Emily"],"title":"Data from: Genetic evidence for monogamy in the dwarf seahorse, Hippocampus zosterae","host":"Rose E, Small CM, Saucedo HA, Harper C, Jones AG (2014) Genetic evidence for monogamy in the dwarf seahorse, Hippocampus zosterae. Journal of Heredity, online in advance of print.","keywords":["mating system","microsatellite","sexual selection","kinship analysis","reproductive strategies","parentage analysis"],"description":"Syngnathid fishes (pipefishes, seahorses, and seadragons) exhibit a wide array of mating systems ranging from monogamy with long-term pair bonds to more promiscuous mating systems, such as polyandry and polygynandry. Some seahorses, including the dwarf seahorse Hippocampus zosterae, have been found to be socially monogamous. Although several seahorse species have also been shown to be genetically monogamous, parentage analysis has not yet been applied to the dwarf seahorse. We developed 8 novel microsatellites for the dwarf seahorse to conduct genetic parentage analysis to confirm that this species is indeed monogamous. Using 4 selected loci and a total of 16 pregnant male seahorses, with 8 collected in Florida and 8 sampled in Texas, we genotyped all of the offspring within each male’s brood to determine the maternal contributions to each brood. We found a maximum of 4 alleles per locus segregating within each pregnant male’s brood, a pattern consistent with each brood having exactly 1 mother and 1 father. These results support previous laboratory-based behavioral studies and indicate that the dwarf seahorse, H. zosterae, is genetically monogamous.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.2qk35/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.2qk35/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.2qk35/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66535","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66535","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25122921","doi:10.1093/jhered/esu050"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2qk35"}}