{"properties":{"genre":"unknown","timestamp":"2011-07-28T19:47:44Z","author":["Oakey, Rebecca J","Roberts, Roland G","O'Connell, Mary J","Chahal, Mandeep","McCole, Ruth B","Loughran, Noeleen B","Fraternali, Franca","Fernandes, Luis P"],"title":"Data from: A case-by-case analysis of four imprinted retrogenes","host":"McCole RB, Loughran NB, Chahal M, Fernandes LP, Roberts RG, Fraternali F, O'Connell MJ, Oakey RJ (2011) A case-by-case analysis of four imprinted retrogenes. Evolution 65(5): 1413–1427.","keywords":["Protein structure","Retrogene","Evolutionary Genomics","Gene Expression","Imprinting","Molecular Evolution"],"description":"Retroposition is a widespread phenomenon resulting in the generation of new genes that are initially related to a parent gene via very high coding sequence similarity. We examine the evolutionary fate of four retrogenes generated by such an event; mouse Inpp5f_v2, Mcts2, Nap1l5, and U2af1-rs1. These genes are all subject to the epigenetic phenomenon of parental imprinting. We first provide new data on the age of these retrogene insertions. Using codon-based models of sequence evolution, we show these retrogenes have diverse evolutionary trajectories, including divergence from the parent coding sequence under positive selection pressure, purifying selection pressure maintaining parent-retrogene similarity, and neutral evolution. Examination of the expression pattern of retrogenes shows an atypical, broad pattern across multiple tissues. Protein 3D structure modeling reveals that a positively selected residue in U2af1-rs1, not shared by its parent, may influence protein conformation. Our case-by-case analysis of the evolution of four imprinted retrogenes reveals that this interesting class of imprinted genes, while similar in regulation and sequence characteristics, follow very varied evolutionary paths.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8096/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.8096","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.8096","isReferencedBy":["PMID:21166792","doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01213.x"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8096"}}