{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-05-15T14:30:54Z","author":["Orti, Guillermo","Broughton, Richard E.","Arratia, Gloria","Betancur-R., Ricardo","Li, Chenhong"],"title":"Data from: Multi-locus phylogenetic analysis reveals the pattern and tempo of bony fish evolution","host":"Broughton RE, Betancur-R R, Li C, Arratia G, Orti G (2013) Multi-locus phylogenetic analysis reveals the pattern and tempo of bony fish evolution. PLoS Currents: Tree of Life.","keywords":["divergence date","phylogeny","ray-finned fishes","bony fishes"],"description":"Over half of all vertebrates are “fishes”, which exhibit enormous diversity in morphology, physiology, behavior, reproductive biology, and ecology.  Investigation of fundamental areas of vertebrate biology depend critically on a robust phylogeny of fishes, yet evolutionary relationships among the major actinopterygian and sarcopterygian lineages have not been conclusively resolved.  Although a consensus phylogeny of teleosts has been emerging recently, it has been based on analyses of various subsets of actinopterygian taxa, but not on a full sample of all bony fishes.  Here we conducted a comprehensive phylogenetic study on an unprecedented combination of broad taxonomic sampling of actinopterygian and sarcopterygian lineages (with a chondrichthyan outgroup) using a molecular data set of 21 independent loci.  These data yielded a resolved phylogenetic hypothesis for extant Osteichthyes, including 1) reciprocally monophyletic Sarcopterygii and Actinopterygii, as currently understood, with polypteriforms as the first diverging lineage within Actinopterygii; 2) a monophyletic group containing gars and bowfin (= Holostei) as sister group to Teleostei; and 3) the earliest diverging lineage among teleosts being Elopomorpha, rather than Osteoglossomorpha.  Relaxed-clock dating analysis employing a set of 24 newly applied fossil calibrations reveals divergence times that are more consistent with paleontological estimates than previous studies.  Establishing a new phylogenetic pattern with accurate divergence dates for bony fishes illustrates several areas where the fossil record is incomplete and provides critical new insights on diversification of this important vertebrate group.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f1t15/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.47415","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.47415","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23788273","doi:10.1371/currents.tol.2ca8041495ffafd0c92756e75247483e"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.f1t15"}}