{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-01-06T20:50:43Z","author":["Ebersberger, Ingo","Borner, Janus","von Haeseler, Arndt","Dell'Ampio, Emiliano","Pass, Günther","Walzl, Manfred G.","Meusemann, Karen","Misof, Bernhard","Minh, Bui Quang","Meyer, Benjamin","Aberer, Andre J.","Petersen, Malte","Szucsich, Nikolaus U.","Stamatakis, Alexandros","Peters, Ralph S."],"title":"Data from: Decisive datasets in phylogenomics: lessons from studies on the phylogenetic relationships of primarily wingless insects","host":"Dell'Ampio E, Meusemann K, Szucsich NU, Peters RS, Meyer B, Borner J, Petersen M, Aberer AJ, Stamatakis A, Walzl MG, Minh BQ, von Haeseler A, Ebersberger I, Pass G, Misof B (2013) Decisive datasets in phylogenomics: lessons from studies on the phylogenetic relationships of primarily wingless insects. Molecular Biology and Evolution 31(1): 239-249.","keywords":["ESTs","conflicting hypotheses","Likelihood quartet mapping","missing data","Phylogenomics"],"description":"Phylogenetic relationships of the primarily wingless insects are still considered unresolved. Even the most comprehensive phylogenomic studies that addressed this question did not yield congruent results. In order to get a grip on these problems, we here analyzed the sources of incongruence in these phylogenomic studies using an extended transcriptome dataset.Our analyses showed that unevenly distributed missing data can be severely misleading by inflating node support despite the absence of phylogenetic signal. In consequence, only decisive datasets should be used which exclusively comprise data blocks containing all taxa whose relationships are addressed. Additionally, we employed Four-cluster Likelihood-Mapping (FcLM) to measure the degree of congruence among genes of a dataset, as a measure of support alternative to bootstrap. FcLM showed incongruent signal among genes, which in our case is correlated with neither functional class assignment of these genes, nor with model misspecification due to unpartitioned analyses. The herein analyzed dataset is the currently largest dataset covering primarily wingless insects, but failed to elucidate their interordinal phylogenetic relationships. While this is unsatisfying from a phylogenetic perspective, we try to show that the analyses of structure and signal within phylogenomic data can protect us from biased phylogenetic inferences due to analytical artefacts.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mk8p7/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.55211","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.55211","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24140757","doi:10.1093/molbev/mst196"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mk8p7"}}