{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"12;;2010","keywords":["cuticle","evolution","integument"],"host":"Harvey THP, Dong X, Donoghue PCJ (2010) Are palaeoscolecids ancestral ecdysozoans? Evolution & Development 12(2): 177-200.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.fc615/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.43759","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2012-10-30T15:28:42Z","author":["Harvey, Thomas H. P.","Dong, Xiping","Donoghue, Philip C. J."],"title":"Data from: Are palaeoscolecids ancestral ecdysozoans?","description":"The reconstruction of ancestors is a central aim of comparative anatomy and evolutionary developmental biology, not least in attempts to understand the relationship between developmental and organismal evolution. Inferences based on living taxa can and should be tested against the fossil record, which provides an independent and direct view onto historical character combinations. Here, we consider the nature of the last common ancestor of living ecdysozoans through a detailed analysis of palaeoscolecids, an early and extinct group of introvert-bearing worms that have been proposed to be ancestral ecdysozoans. In a review of palaeoscolecid anatomy, including newly resolved details of the internal and external cuticle structure, we identify specific characters shared with various living nematoid and The reconstruction of ancestors is a central aim of comparative anatomy and evolutionary developmental biology, not least in attempts to understand the relationship between developmental and organismal evolution. Inferences based on living taxa can and should be tested against the fossil record, which provides an independent and direct view onto historical character combinations. Here, we consider the nature of the last common ancestor of living ecdysozoans through a detailed analysis of palaeoscolecids, an early and extinct group of introvert-bearing worms that have been proposed to be ancestral ecdysozoans. In a review of palaeoscolecid anatomy, including newly resolved details of the internal and external cuticle structure, we identify specific characters shared with various living nematoid and","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.43759","isReferencedBy":["PMID:20433458","doi:10.1111/j.1525-142X.2010.00403.x"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.fc615"}}