{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-10-11T17:03:14Z","author":["Brisson, Dustin","Borrini-Mayori, Katty","Hwang, Josephine","Khatchikian, Camilo E.","Foley, Erica A.","Quispe-Machaca, Victor R.","Levy, Michael Z.","Ancca-Juárez, Jenny"],"title":"Data from: Population structure of the Chagas disease vector, Triatoma infestans, at the urban-rural interface","host":"Foley EA, Khatchikian CE, Hwang J, Ancca-Juárez J, Borrini-Mayori K, Quispe-Machaca VR, Levy MZ, Brisson D (2013) Population structure of the Chagas disease vector, Triatoma infestans, at the urban-rural interface. Molecular Ecology 20(22): 5162-5171.","keywords":["Landscape Genetics","Population Genetics - Empirical","Disease Biology","Ecological Genetics","Insects"],"description":"The increasing rate of biological invasions resulting from human transport or human-mediated changes to the environment have had devastating ecologic and public health consequences. The kissing bug, Triatoma infestans, has dispersed through the Peruvian city of Arequipa. The biological invasion of this insect has resulted in a public health crisis, putting thousands of residents of this city at risk of infection by Trypanosoma cruzi and subsequent development of Chagas disease. Here we show that populations of Tria. infestans in geographically distinct districts within and around this urban center share a common recent evolutionary history although current gene flow is restricted even between proximal sites. The population structure among the Tria. infestans in different districts is not correlated with the geographic distance between districts. These data suggest that migration among the districts is mediated by factors beyond the short-range migratory capabilities of Tria. Infestans and that human movement has played a significant role in the structuring of the Tria. infestans population in the region. Rapid urbanization across southern South America will continue to create suitable environments for Tria. infestans and knowledge of its urban dispersal patterns may play a fundamental role in mitigating human disease risk.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.25gn8/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.52087","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.52087","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12471","PMID:24103030"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.25gn8"}}