{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-11-19T21:16:41Z","author":["Solís-Montero, Lislie","Lou, Anru","Zhao, Jiali","Vallejo-Marín, Mario"],"title":"Data from: Population structure and genetic diversity of native and invasive populations of Solanum rostratum (Solanaceae)","host":"Zhao J, Solís-Montero L, Lou A, Vallejo-Marín M (2013) Population structure and genetic diversity of native and invasive populations of Solanum rostratum (Solanaceae). PLoS ONE 8(11): e79807.","keywords":["population structure","multiple introductions","invasive species","genetic diversity","microsatellites"],"description":"Aims: We investigate native and introduced populations of Solanum rostratum, an annual, self-compatible plant that has been introduced around the globe. This study is the first to compare the genetic diversity of Solanum rostratum between native and introduced populations. We aim to (1) determine the level of genetic diversity across the studied regions; (2) explore the likely origins of invasive populations in China; and (3) investigate whether there is the evidence of multiple introductions into China. Methods: We genotyped 329 individuals at 10 microsatellite loci to determine the levels of genetic diversity and to investigate population structure of native and introduced populations of S. rostratum. We studied five populations in each of three regions across two continents: Mexico, the U.S.A. and China. Important Findings: We found the highest genetic diversity among Mexican populations of S. rostratum. Genetic diversity was significantly lower in Chinese and U.S.A. populations, but we found no regional difference in inbreeding coefficients (FIS) or population differentiation (FST). Population structure analyses indicate that Chinese and U.S.A. populations are more closely related to each other than to sampled Mexican populations, revealing that introduced populations in China share an origin with the sampled U.S.A. populations. The distinctiveness between some introduced populations indicates multiple introductions of S. rostratum into China.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mk58d/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.54733","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.54733","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0079807","PMID:24224008"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.mk58d"}}