{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-08-20T14:00:21Z","author":["Fluker, Brook L.","Kuhajda, Bernard R.","Harris, Phillip M."],"title":"Data from: The influence of life-history strategy on genetic differentiation and lineage divergence in darters (Percidae: Etheostomatinae)","host":"Fluker BL, Kuhajda BR, Harris PM (2014) The influence of life-history strategy on genetic differentiation and lineage divergence in darters (Percidae: Etheostomatinae). Evolution, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Population Genetics","Gene Flow","Phylogeography","Population Structure"],"description":"Recent studies determined that darters with specialized breeding strategies can exhibit deep lineage divergence over fine geographic scales without apparent physical barriers to gene flow. However, the extent to which intrinsic characteristics interact with extrinsic factors to influence population divergence and lineage diversification in darters is not well understood. This study employed comparative phylogeographic and population genetic methods to investigate the influence of life-history on gene flow, dispersal ability, and lineage divergence in two sympatric sister darters with differing breeding strategies. Our results revealed highly disparate phylogeographic histories, patterns of genetic structure, and dispersal abilities between the two species suggesting that life-history may contribute to lineage diversification in darters, especially by limiting dispersal among large river courses. Both species also showed striking differences in demographic history, indicating that extrinsic factors differentially affected each species during the Pleistocene. Collectively, our results indicate that intrinsic and extrinsic factors have influenced levels of gene flow among populations within both species examined. However, we suggest that life-history strategy may play a more important role in lineage diversification in darters than previously appreciated, a finding that has potentially important implications for understanding diversification of the rich North American freshwater fish fauna.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.2s07g/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.2s07g/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.68016","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.68016","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25130551","doi:10.1111/evo.12505"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2s07g"}}