{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-12-19T15:17:28Z","author":["Huari, Frank","Vargas, Víctor J.","Venegas, Pablo J.","Ticona, Andres","Mortensen, Emma","Suárez, Juana","Wood Jr, Perry L.","Aguilar, César","Guzmán, Alfredo","Robles, Daniel","Cusi, Juan C.","Ramírez, César","Sites Jr, Jack W.","Lundberg, Mikael"],"title":"Data from: Integrative taxonomy and preliminary assessment of species limits in the Liolaemus walkeri complex (Squamata, Liolaemidae) with descriptions of three new species from Peru","host":"Aguilar C, Wood Jr PL, Cusi JC, Guzmán A, Huari F, Lundberg M, Mortensen E, Ramírez C, Robles D, Suárez J, Ticona A, Vargas VJ, Venegas PJ, Sites Jr JW (2013) Integrative taxonomy and preliminary assessment of species limits in the Liolaemus walkeri complex (Squamata, Liolaemidae) with descriptions of three new species from Peru. Zookeys 364: 47–91.","keywords":["integrative taxonomy","new species","Liolaemus walkeri complex","viviparity"],"description":"Species delimitation studies based on integrative taxonomic approaches have received considerable attention in the last few years, and have provided the strongest hypotheses of species boundaries. We used three lines of evidence (molecular, morphological, and niche envelopes) to test for species boundaries in Peruvian populations of the Liolaemus walkeri complex. Our results show that different lines of evidence and analyses are congruent in different combinations, for unambiguous delimitation of three lineages that were “hidden” within known species, and now deserve species status. Our phylogenetic analysis shows that L. walkeri, L. tacnae and the three new species are strongly separated from other species assigned to the alticolor-bibronii group. Few conventional morphological characters distinguish the new species from closely related taxa and this highlights the need to integrate other sources of data to erect strong hypothesis of species limits. A taxonomic key for known Peruvian species of the subgenus Lioalemus is provided.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/4","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/12","doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc/11"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.57126","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.57126","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.3897/zookeys.364.6109","PMID:24453545"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.0q7pc"}}