{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-08-20T18:02:17Z","author":["Smith, Wm. Leo","Sparks, John S.","Chakrabarty, Prosanta","McMahan, Caleb D.","Davis, Matthew P."],"title":"Data from: Temporal patterns of diversification across global cichlid biodiversity (Acanthomorpha: Cichlidae)","host":"McMahan CD, Chakrabarty P, Sparks JS, Smith WL, Davis MP (2013) Data from: Temporal patterns of diversification across global cichlid biodiversity (Acanthomorpha: Cichlidae). PLoS ONE 8(8): e71162.","keywords":["cichlids","diversification","fossils","divergence times","evolution"],"description":"The contrasting distribution of species diversity across the major lineages of cichlids makes them an ideal group for investigating macroevolutionary processes. In this study, we investigate whether different rates of diversification may explain the disparity in species richness across cichlid lineages globally. We present the most taxonomically robust time-calibrated hypothesis of cichlid evolutionary relationships to date. We then utilize this temporal framework to investigate whether both species-rich and depauperate lineages are associated with rapid shifts in diversification rates and if exceptional species richness can be explained by clade age alone. A single significant rapid rate shift increase is detected within the evolutionary history of the African subfamily Pseudocrenilabrinae, which includes the haplochromins of the East African Great Lakes. Several lineages from the subfamilies Pseudocrenilabrinae (Australotilapiini, Oreochromini) and Cichlinae (Heroini) exhibit exceptional species richness given their clade age, a net rate of diversification, and relative rates of extinction, indicating that clade age alone is not a sufficient explanation for their increased diversity. Our results indicate that the Neotropical Cichlinae includes lineages that have not experienced a significant rapid burst in diversification when compared to certain African lineages (rift lake). Neotropical cichlids have remained comparatively understudied with regard to macroevolutionary patterns relative to African lineages, and our results indicate that of Neotropical lineages, the tribe Heroini may have an elevated rate of diversification in contrast to other Neotropical cichlids. These findings provide insight into our understanding of the diversification patterns across taxonomically disparate lineages in this diverse clade of freshwater fishes and one of the most species-rich families of vertebrates.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.t3q8b/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.t3q8b/2"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.49226","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.49226","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23990936","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0071162"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.t3q8b"}}