{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-09-27T18:21:27Z","author":["Hindrikson, Maris","Saarma, Urmas","Männil, Peep","Ozolins, Janis","Tammeleht, Egle","Remm, Jaanus"],"title":"Data from: Spatial genetic analyses reveal cryptic population structure and migration patterns in a continuously harvested grey wolf (Canis lupus) population in north-eastern Europe","host":"Hindrikson M, Remm J, Männil P, Ozolins J, Tammeleht E, Saarma U (2013) Spatial genetic analyses reveal cryptic population structure and migration patterns in a continuously harvested grey wolf (Canis lupus) population in north-eastern Europe. PLoS ONE 8(9): e75765.","keywords":["DResD","Social mammals","Population structure","Program STRUCTURE","Hunting","Landscape genetics","Conservation genetics","Harvesting"],"description":"Spatial genetics is a relatively new field in wildlife and conservation biology that is becoming an essential tool for unravelling the complexities of animal population processes, and for designing effective strategies for conservation and management. Conceptual and methodological developments in this field are therefore critical. Here we present two novel methodological approaches that further the analytical possibilities of STRUCTURE and DResD. Using these approaches we analyse structure and migrations in a grey wolf (Canis lupus) population in north-eastern Europe. We genotyped 16 microsatellite loci in 166 individuals sampled from the wolf population in Estonia and Latvia that has been under strong and continuous hunting pressure for decades. Our analysis demonstrated that this relatively small wolf population is represented by four genetic groups. We also used a novel methodological approach that uses linear interpolation to statistically test the spatial separation of genetic groups. The new method, which is capable of using program STRUCTURE output, can be applied widely in population genetics to reveal both core areas and areas of low significance for genetic groups. We also used a recently developed spatially explicit individual-based method DResD, and applied it for the first time to microsatellite data, revealing a migration corridor and barriers, and several contact zones.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2n97q/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.53162","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.53162","isReferencedBy":["PMID:24069446","doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0075765"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.2n97q"}}