{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2013-04-09T14:52:46Z","author":["Yek, Sze H.","Schiøtt, Morten","Boomsma, Jacobus J."],"title":"Data from: Differential gene expression in Acromyrmex leaf-cutting ants after challenges with two fungal pathogens","host":"Yek SH, Boomsma JJ, Schiøtt M (2013) Differential gene expression in Acromyrmex leaf-cutting ants after challenges with two fungal pathogens. Dryad Digital Repository. Molecular Ecology 22(8): 2173–2187.","keywords":["Genomics/Proteomics","Host Parasite Interactions","Disease Biology","Fungi","Gene Structure and Function","Insects"],"description":"Social insects in general and leaf-cutting ants in particular have increased selection pressures on their innate immune system due to their social lifestyle and monoclonality of the symbiotic fungal cultivar. As this symbiosis is obligate for both parties, prophylactic behavioural defences against infections are expected to increase either ant survival or fungus-garden survival, but also to possibly trade off when specific infections differ in potential danger. We examined the effectiveness of prophylactic behaviours and modulations of innate immune defences by a combination of inoculation bioassays and genome-wide transcriptomic studies (RNA-Seq), using an ant pathogen (Metarhizium brunneum) and a fungus-garden pathogen (Escovopsis weberi) and administering inoculations both directly and indirectly (via the symbiotic partner). Upon detection of pathogen conidia, ant workers responded by increasing both general activity and the frequency of specific defence behaviours (self-grooming, allo-grooming, garden-grooming) independent of the pathogen encountered. This trend was also evident in the patterns of gene expression change. Both direct and indirect (via fungus garden) inoculations with Metarhizium induced a general up-regulation of gene expression, including a number of well-known immune-related genes. In contrast, direct inoculation of the fungus garden by Escovopsis induced an overall down-regulation of ant gene expression, whereas indirect inoculation (via the ants) did not, suggesting that increased activity of ants to remove this fungus-garden pathogen is costly and involves trade-offs with the activation of other physiological pathways.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.nb35n/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.45803","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.45803","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/mec.12255","PMID:23480581"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.nb35n"}}