{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-09-18T17:28:50Z","author":["Athrey, Giri","Leberg, Paul L.","Lance, Richard F."],"title":"Data from: How far is too close? Restricted, sex-biased dispersal in black-capped vireos","host":"Athrey G, Lance RF, Leberg PL (2012) Data from: How far is too close? restricted, sex-biased dispersal in black-capped vireos. Molecular Ecology 21(17): 4359-4370.","keywords":["Landscape Genetics","Ecological Genetics","Birds","sex-biased dispersal","Population Ecology"],"description":"Understanding the interplay of dispersal and how it translates into gene flow is key to understanding population processes, and especially so for endangered species occupying fragmented habitats. In migratory songbirds, there is evidence that long-distance movement capabilities are not highly related to observed dispersal. Our objectives were to 1) define the fine-scale spatial genetic structure in the endangered black-capped vireos to shed light on dispersal patterns, and 2) to relate dispersal dynamics to overall population genetic structure using a simulation approach. We sampled 160 individuals over two years to describe the fine-scale genetic structuring, and used this information to model scenarios to compare with actual data on change in population structuring over a 100-year interval. We found that black-capped vireo exhibit male-philopatry, and restricted dispersal distances, relative to females. Our simulations support a sex-biased dispersal model. Additionally, we find that fragmentation related changes in rates of dispersal might be a likely cause for increasing levels of population structure over a 100-year period. We show that restricted dispersal can explain population structuring in this species, and that changes in dispersal rates due to fragmentation may be a continuing threat to genetic viability in this species.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.d2fm8/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.39747","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.39747","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05694.x","PMID:22747695"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.d2fm8"}}