{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-09-12T18:40:07Z","author":["Keller, Laurent","Buechel, Séverine D.","Wurm, Yannick"],"title":"Data from: Social chromosome variants differentially affect queen determination and the survival of workers in the fire ant Solenopsis invicta","host":"Buechel SD, Wurm Y, Keller L (2014) Social chromosome variants differentially affect queen determination and the survival of workers in the fire ant Solenopsis invicta. Molecular Ecology, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Behavior/Social Evolution","Development and Evolution","Ecological Genetics","Insects"],"description":"Intraspecific variation in social organization is common, yet the underlying causes are rarely known. An exception is the fire ant Solenopsis invicta in which the existence of two distinct forms of social colony organization is under the control of the two variants of a pair of social chromosomes, SB and Sb. Colonies containing exclusively SB/SB workers accept only one single queen and she must be SB/SB. By contrast, when colonies contain more than 10% of SB/Sb workers, they accept several queens but only SB/Sb queens. The variants of the social chromosome are associated with several additional important phenotypic differences, including the size, fecundity and dispersal strategies of queens, aggressiveness of workers, and sperm count in males. However, little is known about whether social chromosome variants affect fitness in other life stages. Here we perform experiments to determine whether differential selection occurs during development, and in adult workers. We find evidence that the Sb variant of the social chromosome increases the likelihood of female brood to develop into queens and that adult SB/Sb workers, the workers that cull SB/SB queens, are overrepresented in comparison to SB/SB workers. This demonstrates that supergenes such as the social chromosome can have complex effects on phenotypes at various stages of development.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.vb073/2","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.69924","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.69924","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25211290","doi:10.1111/mec.12915"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.vb073"}}