{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-02T15:36:45Z","author":["Berris, Theocharis","Rehani, Madan M."],"title":"Data from: International Atomic Energy Agency survey study with referring physicians on patient radiation exposure and its tracking: A prospective survey using a web based questionnaire","host":"Rehani MM, Berris T (2012) International Atomic Energy Agency survey study with referring physicians on patient radiation exposure and its tracking: A prospective survey using a web based questionnaire. BMJ Open 2(5): e001425.","keywords":["Medical physics","Diagnostic radiology","Computed tomography"],"description":"OBJECTIVES: To assess the following themes among referring physicians: A. Importance of acquiring information about previous diagnostic exposures; B. Knowledge about radiation doses involved, familiarity with radiation units and, age related radiosensitivity; C. Opinion on whether patients should be provided information about radiation dose; and, D. Self-assessment of appropriateness of referrals. DESIGN: A prospective survey using a web based questionnaire. SETTING: International survey among referring physicians. PARTICIPANTS: Referring physicians from 28 countries. MAIN OUTCOME MEASURES: Knowledge, opinion and practice of the four themes of the survey. RESULTS: 728 responses from 28 countries (52.3% from developed and 47.7% from developing countries) indicated that while the vast majority (71.7%) of physicians feel that being aware of previous history of CT scans would always or mostly lead them to a better decision on referring patients for CT scans, only 43.4% often enquire about it. The majority of referring physicians (60.5%) stated that having a system that provides quick information about patient exposure history would be useful. The knowledge about radiation doses involved is poor, as only one-third (34.7%) of respondents chose the correct option of the number of chest x-rays with equivalence of a CT scan. 70.9% of physicians stated that they do not feel uncomfortable when patients ask about radiation risk from CT scans they prescribe. Most physicians (85.6%) assessed that they have rarely prescribed CT scans of no clinical use in patient management. CONCLUSIONS: This first ever multi-national survey among referring physicians from 28 countries indicates support for a system that provides radiation exposure history of the patient, demonstrates poor knowledge about radiation doses, supports radiation risk communication with patients and, mandatory provisions for justification of a CT examination.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3hq09/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.41783","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.41783","isReferencedBy":["PMID:22997065","doi:10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001425"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3hq09"}}