{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2014-07-30T16:29:59Z","author":["Tang, Zhonglin","Wang, Hongyang","Wang, Chao","Liu, Bang","Li, Kui","Zhang, Yu"],"title":"Data from: Genome-wide analysis reveals artificial selection on coat colour and reproductive traits in Chinese domestic pigs","host":"Wang C, Wang H, Zhang Y, Tang Z, Li K, Liu B (2014) Genome-wide analysis reveals artificial selection on coat colour and reproductive traits in Chinese domestic pigs. Molecular Ecology Resources, online in advance of print.","keywords":["Agriculture","Genomics/Proteomics","Mammals","Adaptation","Ecological Genetics","Population Ecology"],"description":"Pigs from Asia and Europe were independently domesticated from ~9,000 years ago. During this period, strong artificial selection has led to dramatic phenotypic changes in domestic pigs. However, the genetic basis underlying these morphological and behavioural adaptations is relatively unknown, particularly for indigenous Chinese pigs. Here, we performed a genome-wide analysis to screen 196 regions with selective sweep signals in Tongcheng pigs, which are a typical indigenous Chinese breed. Genes located in these regions have been found to be involved in lipid metabolism, melanocyte differentiation, neural development, and other biological processes, which coincide with the evolutionary phenotypic changes in this breed. A synonymous substitution, c.669T>C, in ESR1, which co-localises with a major quantitative trait locus for litter size, shows extreme differences in allele frequency between Tongcheng pigs and wild boars. Notably, the variant C allele in this locus exhibits high allele frequency in most Chinese populations, suggesting a consequence of positive selection. Five genes (PRM1, PRM2, TNP2, GPR149 and JMJD1C) related to reproductive traits were found to have high haplotype similarity in Chinese breeds. Two selected genes, MITF and EDNRB, are implied to shape the two-end black colour trait in Tongcheng pig. Subsequent SNP microarray studies of five Chinese white-spotted breeds displayed a concordant signature at both loci, suggesting that these two genetic loci are responsible for colour variations in Chinese breeds. Utilising massively parallel sequencing, we characterised the candidate sites that adapt to artificial and environmental selections during the Chinese pig domestication. This study provides fundamental proof for further research on the evolutionary adaptation of Chinese pigs.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.8c930/10","doi:10.5061/dryad.8c930/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.8c930/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.8c930/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.8c930/6"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.66824","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.66824","isReferencedBy":["PMID:25132237","doi:10.1111/1755-0998.12311"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.8c930"}}