{"properties":{"genre":"dataset","timestamp":"2011-04-21T14:45:35Z","title":"Effect of macrobiotic exclusion on benthic communities: the role of fishes and crayfishes in southern Appalachian streams.","keywords":["sculpin","Coweeta","macrobiota","sediment","electric exclusion","algae","bioturbation","crayfish","invertebrates","land use","LTER"],"description":"We examined the role of macrobiota in structuring the benthic communities of two low-order southern Appalachian streams, one draining intact forest (Ball Creek) and one draining pasture (Jones Creek). Fishes and crayfishes were excluded from areas of both streams using an electric exclusion technique; chlorophyll a, ash free dry mass (AFDM), and invertebrates were sampled over a 40-day period. In both streams, chlorophyll a and AFDM were higher in exclusion than control areas, although these trends were not consistently significant across all sampling dates. In Jones Creek, significantly more large (> 4 mm) aquatic insect larvae were found in exclusion that control areas, most likely due to exclusion treatments providing a refuge from macrobiotic predators. This refuge effect was also evident in Ball Creek, were exclusion treatments contained significantly more filterers. Results indicate that macrobiota influence the structure of southern Appalachian benthic communities, by decreasing the amount of organic matter (algal and detrital) available for other consumers and by preferentially preying upon certain sizes and taxa of invertebrates. Compared to some low-order tropical streams, however, macrobiotic influences are low. Weaker effects may be attributed to decreased abundance of macrobiota and increased influence of benthic insects in southern Appalachian streams.1.None Available","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.9290","name":["Katharine Schofield","Judy L. Meyer","Emma Rosi","Catherine Pringle","Katherine Dowell"],"oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.9290","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","identifier":["knb-lter-cwt.3010.3","http://metacat.lternet.edu/knb/metacat/knb-lter-cwt.3010.3/xml"]}}