{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-12-12T16:48:15Z","author":["Audet, Céline","Normandeau, Eric","Bougas, Bérénice","Bernatchez, Louis"],"title":"Data from: Linking transcriptomic and genomic variation to growth in brook charr hybrids (Salvelinus fontinalis, Mitchill)","keywords":["RNA-seq","allelic imbalance","salmonid","transcriptomic","epistasis","cis-regulation"],"description":"Hybridization can lead to phenotypic differences arising from changes in gene expression patterns or new allele combinations. Variation in gene expression is thought to be controlled by differences in transcription regulation of parental alleles, either through cis or trans regulatory elements. A previous study among brook charr hybrids from different populations (Rupert, Laval, and domestic) showing distinct length at age during early life stages also revealed different patterns in transcription regulation inheritance of transcript abundance. In the present study, transcript abundance by means of RNA-seq and qRT-PCR, SNP genotypes and allelic imbalance were assessed in order to understand the molecular mechanisms underlying the observed transcriptomic and differences in length at age among domestic × Rupert hybrids and Laval × domestic hybrids. We found 198 differentially expressed genes between the two hybrid crosses and allelic imbalance could be analyzed for 69 of them. Among these 69 genes, 36 genes exhibited cis acting regulatory effects in both of the two crosses, thus confirming the prevalent role of cis acting regulatory elements in the regulation of differentially expressed genes among intraspecific hybrids. In addition, we detected a significant association between SNP genotypes of three genes and length at age. Our study is thus one of the few that have highlighted some of the molecular mechanisms potentially involved in the differential phenotypic expression in intraspecific hybrids for non-model species.","constituent":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3g19f/1","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.44981","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.44981","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.3g19f"}}