{"properties":{"genre":"Article","timestamp":"2012-10-15T14:26:43Z","author":["Hardy, Nate B.","Cook, Lyn G."],"title":"Data from: Testing for ecological limitation of diversification: a case study using parasitic plants","host":"Hardy NB, Cook LG (2012) Testing for ecological limitation of diversification: a case study using parasitic plants. American Naturalist 180(4): 438-449.","keywords":["Phylogeny","Evolution: host/parasite","Plant","Species diversity","Macroevolution","Methods: meta-analysis"],"description":"Imbalances in phylogenetic diversity could be the result of variable unbounded diversification rates, differing limits on diversity, or a combination of the two. We propose an approach to distinguish between rates and limits as the primary cause of phylogenetic imbalance, using parasitic plants as a model. With sister-taxon comparisons, we show that parasitic plant lineages are typically much less diverse than their autotrophic sisters. We then use age estimates for taxa used in the sister-taxon comparisons to test for correlations between clade age and diversity. We find that parasitic plant diversity is not significantly correlated with the age of the lineage, whereas there is a strong positive correlation between the age and diversity of autotrophic sister lineages. The Ericaceae sister-pair Monotropoideae (parasitic) and Arbutoideae (autotrophic) are sufficiently well samples at the species level to allow more parametric comparisons of diversification patterns. Model-fitting for this group supports ecological limitation in Monotropoideae and unconstrained diversification in Arbutoideae. Thus, differences in diversity between parasitic plants and their autotrophic sisters might be caused by a mixture of ecological limitation and unbounded diversification. A combination of sister-taxon comparisons of diversity and age, coupled with model-fitting of well-sampled phylogenies of focal taxa, provides a powerful test of likely causes of asymmetry in the diversity of lineages.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/9","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/5","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/6","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/7","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/8","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/1","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/3","doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70/4"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.40291","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.40291","isReferencedBy":["doi:10.1086/667588","PMID:22976008"],"node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.g6r70"}}