{"properties":{"genre":"dataset","timestamp":"2011-04-26T22:04:50Z","title":"Seedling recruitment in artificial gaps.","keywords":["gaps","Coweeta","LTER","seedlings"],"description":"We examined the role of both intermediate-sized gaps and a dense shrub layer on subsequent tree seedling recruitment in a southern Appalachian deciduous\nforest. We monitored the density of tree seedlings in twelve artificial gaps\nand adjacent canopy controls under two contrasting understory conditions.\nHalf of the experimental gaps were dominated by the dense, shade-producing\nshrub, Rhododendron maximum, while the remaining gaps were relatively open.\nCanopy gaps 20 m in diameter were created by girdling canopy trees, leaving\nstanding dead trees with minimal disturbance to the understory. Density of\nfirst-year and >first-year seedlings was monitored in transects extending\nfrom adjacent undisturbed forest through the experimental gaps.Our clusters of experimental gaps were located in two mixed oak stands that bracket the elevation range of this community, hereafter referred to as ?low elevation? (850 m) and ?high elevation? (1100 m) sites. Sites had a\nnortheast aspect and slopes ranged from 30 to 50 % (high elevation) and from\n45 to 70 % (low elevation). At both sites, we established six plots (12\nplots total), each corresponding to a single experimental gap. Three of the\nsix plots at each elevation had a dense R. maximum understory, while three\nplots lacked R. maximum. R. maximum has a patchy distribution at these\nsites, permitting us to locate experimental gaps (with and without R.\nmaximum) in close proximity, thus allowing for consistent overstory\ncomposition, slope, soils, and microclimate. Locations for experimental gaps\nwere selected in 1991, and canopy trees were marked for girdling to produce\ngaps of approximately 300 m2 (expanded gap definition, Runkle 1981). Up to\nfive trees from a variety of species were girdled to create each gap. A\ntransect, comprised of 40 contiguous 1 m2 quadrats, was established across\neach planned gap. Transects were generally oriented in a north-south\ndirection. Transects included 20 central quadrats exposed to gap conditions\nand 20 outer quadrats subtended by the surrounding canopy. There were a few\nexceptions to this layout, due to topographic considerations or patchiness\nof the R. maximum. In these cases, transects deviated from a north-south\norientation or were interrupted to maintain consistent understory conditions\n(e.g., R. maximum or non R. maximum). Following collection of pretreatment\ndata in 1993, we produced experimental canopy gaps by girdling trees in late\nsummer of the same year. The herbicide Garlon was applied to trees that\nleafed out the following spring. Girdled trees remained standing for the\nduration of our study, although large branches began to fall in the 4th\nyear. We censused tree seedlings along all transects annually in July or\nAugust from 1993 to 1997. We identified all seedlings and saplings less than 2 m\ntall to genus or species (for Acer rubrum, Liriodendron tulipifera, and\nQuercus prinus). Seedlings classified as Betula spp were likely Betula\nlenta, because Betula allegheniensis is restricted to the highest elevations\nat Coweeta. We were unable to confidently differentiate all seedlings of Q.\nvelutina, Q. coccinea, and Q. rubra, so these are grouped as Q. rubra-type.","identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.24469","name":["Brian Beckage","JamesClark"],"oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.24469","node_type":"Record","node_source":"Dryad","identifier":["knb-lter-cwt.1003.3","http://metacat.lternet.edu/knb/metacat/knb-lter-cwt.1003.3/xml"]}}