{"properties":{"genre":"Article","series":"7;;2013","keywords":["diversity","Janzen–Connell","negative feedback","natural enemies","coexistence"],"host":"Peay KG, Baraloto C, Fine PVA (2013) Strong coupling of plant and fungal community structure across western Amazonian rainforests. The ISME Journal 2013(7): 1852-1861.","constituent":["doi:10.5061/dryad.34569/2","doi:10.5061/dryad.34569/1"],"identifier_uri":"http://hdl.handle.net/10255/dryad.64271","node_source":"Dryad","node_type":"Record","timestamp":"2014-05-13T15:26:38Z","author":["Baraloto, Christopher","Peay, Kabir G.","Fine, Paul V. A."],"title":"Data from: Strong coupling of plant and fungal community structure across western Amazonian rainforests","description":"The Amazon basin harbors a diverse ecological community that has a critical role in the maintenance of the biosphere. Although plant and animal communities have received much attention, basic information is lacking for fungal or prokaryotic communities. This is despite the fact that recent ecological studies have suggested a prominent role for interactions with soil fungi in structuring the diversity and abundance of tropical rainforest trees. In this study, we characterize soil fungal communities across three major tropical forest types in the western Amazon basin (terra firme, seasonally flooded and white sand) using 454 pyrosequencing. Using these data, we examine the relationship between fungal diversity and tree species richness, and between fungal community composition and tree species composition, soil environment and spatial proximity. We find that the fungal community in these ecosystems is diverse, with high degrees of spatial variability related to forest type. We also find strong correlations between α- and β-diversity of soil fungi and trees. Both fungal and plant community β-diversity were also correlated with differences in environmental conditions. The correlation between plant and fungal richness was stronger in fungal lineages known for biotrophic strategies (for example, pathogens, mycorrhizas) compared with a lineage known primarily for saprotrophy (yeasts), suggesting that this coupling is, at least in part, due to direct plant–fungal interactions. These data provide a much-needed look at an understudied dimension of the biota in an important ecosystem and supports the hypothesis that fungal communities are involved in the regulation of tropical tree diversity.","oai":"oai:datadryad.org:10255/dryad.64271","isReferencedBy":["PMID:23598789","doi:10.1038/ismej.2013.66"],"doi":"doi:10.5061/dryad.34569"}}